I'M. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
WELCOME TO THE MARCH 17TH, 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS .
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD NOT MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR NOT
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL
SHERYL PRESENT SUPERVISOR ARE WALTON WALTON PRESENT
AND SUPERVISOR WONG WONG PRESENT.
MR. PRESIDENT YOU HAVE A QUORUM .
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF
THE ROMITA SALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS
LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE ROMITA
SALONI HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM
LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAMAKRISHNA LEARNING COMMUNITY
AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST
PEOPLES. >> COLLEAGUES WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD
INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL.
>> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
OF S.F. GOV TV TODAY TODAY THAT IS ESPECIALLY JAMES KAWANA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE
TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE.
MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
>> YES, MR. PRESIDENT. TODAY THE CLERK'S OFFICE IS
IN RECEIPT OF THREE MEMOS REQUESTING EXCUSAL FROM TODAY'S
BOARD MEETING FROM SUPERVISORS FIELDER SAUTER AND MELGAR.
MR. PRESIDENT AND I'LL JUST SAY TO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THAT
MEANS YOUR FIRST ON THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS
AND ROLL CALL FOR VOTES. >> OKAY.
ADDITIONALLY, THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES
ATTENDANCE FROM ALL OF YOU WHO ARE HERE TODAY IN THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER. AND WHEN YOU'RE NOT ABLE TO BE
HERE YOU CAN CATCH THE LIVE PROCEEDING ON S.F. GOVEE TV'S
CHANNEL 26 OR YOU CAN CATCH THE LIVE STREAMING AT W W W DOT
S.F. OR VTV.ORG. IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT
YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT IN WRITING YOU CAN SEND AN EMAIL TO BOX AT
S.F. GOV.ORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B GOODLATTE PLACE CITY HALL ROOM
244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102 IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A
REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE
AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE
ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS
DAYS IN ADVANCE. HERE'S THE TELEPHONE NUMBER
(415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. SO WE HAVE THREE REQUESTS FOR
EXCUSAL FROM SUPERVISORS FIELDER MELGAR AND SÖDER CAN I
HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE THEM FROM TODAY'S MEETING MOVED BY
MAHMOOD AND SECONDED BY CHEN THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
YES, MR. PRESIDENT. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
SUPERVISORS FIELDER MELGAR AND SADR ARE EXCUSED.
I WOULD ALSO JUST NOTE COLLEAGUES SO YOU WILL YOU WILL
SEE THAT WE ARE STARTING THIS MEETING DOWN THREE MEMBERS
WHICH HAS US AT EIGHT. WE NEED FOR THE MEETING TO
CONTINUE TO KEEP SIX PEOPLE IN THIS CHAMBER AT ALL TIMES.
SO WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO BE A LITTLE CAREFUL ABOUT, YOU KNOW,
MAKING SURE AND THE CLERK'S STAFF WILL KEEP US ON TRACK
WITH THAT AS WELL. MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES .
>> YES. APPROVAL OF THE FEBRUARY 10TH,
2026 BOARD MEETING MINUTES. >> ALL RIGHT.
CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED
BY CHANCE SECONDED BY MAHMUD. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG
WONG I'M SUPERVISOR CHAN SUPER CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA PLEASE
CALL ITEMS ONE THROUGH THREE TOGETHER ITEMS ONE THROUGH
THREE ARE ON CONSENT THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE
ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM CAN BE REMOVED
AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEMS ONE THROUGH THREE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT MANDEL MEN I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WILTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG
WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER FOUR ITEM
FOUR. >> THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE THE FIFTH CONTRACT AMENDMENT TO A CONTRACT BETWEEN
THE CITY THE OFFICE OF CONTRACT ADMINISTRATION AND THE
UNIVERSAL PROTECTION SERVICE LP DOING BUSINESS AS ALLIED
UNIVERSAL SECURITY SERVICES FOR UNARMED SECURITY GUARD SERVICES
AT THE SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL HOSPITAL TO EXTEND THE CONTRACT
BY SIX MONTHS FOR A TOTAL TERM FEBRUARY 15TH 2023 THROUGH
DECEMBER 14TH 2026 AND TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY
3.2 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 15.38 MILLION.
>> I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE CITY AND COUNTY TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE $1.4 MILLION GRANT FROM THE D H C.
S THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE SERVICES FOR
PARTICIPATION IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED TO CAPACITY
AND INFRASTRUCTURE TRANSITION EXPANSION AND DEVELOPMENT ROUND
FOUR PROGRAM INTERGOVERNMENTAL TRANSFER TO APPROVE THE GRANT
AGREEMENT AND TO AUTHORIZE THE CITY TO RELEASE ALL CLAIMS
AGAINST AGAINST THE D H C. S AND ITS THIRD PARTY
ADMINISTRATOR FOR ARISING OUT OF OR RELATING TO THE RECEIPT
OF GRANT FUNDS AND OR ACTIVITIES ASSOCIATED WITH THE
GRANT PROGRAM FOR A TERM OF ONE YEAR JANUARY 1ST 2026 THROUGH
DECEMBER 31ST 2026 AND FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY
1.4 MILLION AND WE COULD TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL OUT A NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX A
RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE CD THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE THE STANDARD AGREEMENTS
WITH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT UNDER THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
AND SUSTAINABLE COMMUNITIES PROGRAM FOR AN AWARD OF
APPROXIMATELY 47.6 MILLION FOR A 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROJECT AND PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION GRANT FOR
IMPROVEMENTS NEAR 1939 MARKET STREET THROUGH DECEMBER 10TH,
2018 AND TO AUTHORIZE THE CD TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND THE 12
MILLION LET'S SAY 12.57 MILLION FOR TRANSPORTATION STREETSCAPE
AND PEDESTRIAN IMPROVEMENTS AND OTHER TRANSIENT TRANSIT
ORIENTED PROGRAMING AND IMPROVEMENTS AND AGAIN SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER SEVEN ITEM SEVEN THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT
RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE OFFICE OF TREASURER AND TAX
COLLECTOR TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $3 MILLION GRANT FROM
JPMORGAN CHASE BANK AND A FOR IMPLEMENTING THE STOP SCAMS
ASSET PROGRAM. DECEMBER 15TH, 2025 THROUGH
DECEMBER 14TH 2028 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE POLICE CODE TO REQUIRE THAT
INDIVIDUALS WHO NOTARIZE OR ASSIST PEOPLE IN COMPLETING
IMMIGRATION DOCUMENTS OFFER A DOCUMENT PREPARED BY THE CITY
THAT IDENTIFIES FREE OR LOW COST IMMIGRATION LEGAL SERVICES
PROVIDERS AND CONSULATES AND TO AUTHORIZE THE HUMAN RIGHTS
COMMISSION TO PROVIDE ASSISTANCE TO MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC WHO WISH TO FILE A COMPLAINT WITH THE STATE
LICENSING OR ENFORCEMENT ENTITY AGAINST A NOTARY OR IMMIGRATION
CONSULTANT WHO ALLEGEDLY VIOLATED LEGAL REQUIREMENTS
APPLICABLE TO THEIR ACTIVITIES. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER NINE.
>> ITEM NINE RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE POLICE COMMISSION
STATEMENT OF PURPOSE PURSUANT TO CHARTER SECTION 4.102 SUB
TWO. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER TEN ITEM TEN
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT'S ANNUAL SURVEILLANCE REPORT FOR GUNSHOT
DETECTION TECHNOLOGY. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 11.
ITEM 11 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE AND THE ZONING
MAP TO ESTABLISH THE 20 TO 45 POST STREET SPECIAL USE
DISTRICT AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 12 ITEM 12 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO INITIATE THE
LANDMARK DESIGNATION FOR ENGINE COMPANY NUMBER 33 LOCATED AT
117 BROAD STREET UNDER ARTICLE TEN OF THE PLANNING CODE.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> AND MADAME CLERK.
LET'S GO TO OUR COMMITTEE REPORTS.
PLEASE CALL OUT A NUMBER 16. >> YES, ITEM 16.
I WILL FIRST SAY THAT THIS ITEM WAS CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY
MARCH 16TH AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT ITEM 16
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO RE ADOPT THE FORMER PLANNING CODE
SECTION AND ZONING MAP DESIGNATIONS CREATING THE
MISSION AND NINTH STREET SPECIAL USE DISTRICT AT 1270
MISSION STREET IN THE AREA GENERALLY BOUNDED BY MISSION
STREET ON THE SOUTH LASKI STREET ON THE EAST ASSESSOR'S
PARCEL BLOCK ON THE WEST AND ON THE NORTH WITH THE VARIOUS
BLOCK AND LOT NUMBER LOT NUMBERS CHANGING THE HEIGHT
LIMIT ON ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER 30 701 LOT NUMBERS
20 AND 21 FOR PROJECTS THAT COMPLY WITH THE REQUIREMENTS OF
THE ISSUED FROM 120 X TO 200 X AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER
17 YES. >> ITEM 17 THIS ORDINANCE
AMENDS THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO ENHANCE AND MODIFY THE SIDEWALK
FLOWER STAND PERMIT PROGRAM AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND
DETERMINATION. THIS ITEM WAS RECOMMENDED AS
AMENDED BUT WITH THE SAME TITLE ,SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 18.
ITEM 18 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR
MEETING ON MONDAY MARCH 16TH AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS A
COMMITTEE REPORT. ITEM 18 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO MODIFY THE JESSIE ALLEY'S
DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO INCLUDE THE NORTHERN SIDE OF
MISSION STREET TO EXCLUDE THE PUBLIC STREET PORTION OF
MISSION STREET BETWEEN JESSIE STREET EAST AND JESSIE STREET
WEST AND TO MAKE CLARIFYING REVISIONS THE MINOR ALLEY
DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO INCLUDE MINISTRY BETWEEN SHAW
ALLEY AND NEW MONTGOMERY STREET THE NATOMA DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION
LOCATION TO INCLUDE NATOMA STREET BETWEEN NEW MONTGOMERY
STREET AND 180FT NORTHEAST OF SECOND STREET THE SECOND STREET
DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO INCLUDE JESSIE STREET BETWEEN
SECOND STREET AND NEW MONTGOMERY STREET AND THE YERBA
BUENA LANE DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO INCLUDE THE
SOUTHERN SIDE OF MARKET STREET BETWEEN YERBA BUENA LANE AND TO
50FT NORTHEAST OF YOUR PUB WHEN A LANE TO EXCLUDE THE PUBLIC
STREET PORTION OF MARKET STREET AND TO AFFIRM THE SQUARE
DETERMINATIONS. >> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMUD, YOU'RE UP FIRST TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS
. >> COLLEAGUES, I HAVE TWO
RESOLUTIONS TO INTRODUCE TODAY .
THE FIRST IS A RESOLUTION SUPPORTING ASSEMBLY BILL 2017
BY SOME OF THEM WERE MAHANEY AND SPONSORED BY THE COMMISSION
ON ASIAN AND PACIFIC ISLANDER AMERICAN AFFAIRS.
THE MUSLIM IMPACT COUNCIL AND THE COUNCIL ON
AMERICAN-ISLAMIC RELATIONS CALIFORNIA.
THIS LEGISLATION WOULD RECOGNIZE EIDUL FITR AND EIDL
ADHA AND CALIFORNIA LAW AND ENSURE STUDENTS AND STATE
EMPLOYEES CAN OBSERVE THESE IMPORTANT RELIGIOUS HOLIDAYS
WITHOUT PENALTY. >> FOR MUSLIM COMMUNITIES
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND ACROSS CALIFORNIA, E IS ONE OF THE
MOST MEANINGFUL TIMES OF THE YEAR.
>> IT'S A TIME FOR PRAYER FAMILY GATHERINGS, CHARITY
AND CELEBRATION. >> BUT FOR MANY MUSLIM STUDENTS
AND WORKERS OBSERVING EID HAS MEANT CHOOSING BETWEEN THEIR
FAITH AND THEIR SCHOOL OR WORK RESPONSIBILITY IS A B 2017
HELPS ENSURE THAT PEOPLE CAN CELEBRATE THESE HOLIDAYS WITH
DIGNITY AND WITHOUT CONSEQUENCE.
IN A CITY AS DIVERSE AS SAN FRANCISCO RECOGNIZING
AND RESPECTING THE TRADITIONS OF OUR COMMUNITIES IS AN
IMPORTANT STEP TOWARDS EQUITY AND BELONGING.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR CO-SPONSORING AS WELL AS
ASSEMBLYMEMBER MATT HANEY FOR AUTHORING HB 2017
AND RECOGNIZING HALA HIJAZI FOR BRINGING FORWARD THE IDEA FOR
THIS LEGISLATION AND FOR HER CONTINUED LEADERSHIP
AND ADVOCACY FOR MUSLIM COMMUNITIES ACROSS CALIFORNIA.
>> MY SECOND RESOLUTION URGES THE GOVERNOR AND LEGISLATURE TO
CONTINUE FUNDING MARKET MOUCH A PROGRAM THAT DOUBLES CAL FRESH
DOLLARS WHEN FAMILIES BUY FRUITS AND VEGETABLES AT
FARMERS MARKETS. IT'S A SIMPLE PROGRAM THAT
MAKES A REAL DIFFERENCE HELPING FAMILIES STRETCH THEIR FOOD
BUDGETS WHILE SUPPORTING CALIFORNIA FARMERS.
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, THOUSANDS OF RESIDENTS RELY ON
THIS PROGRAM AT MARKETS ACROSS THE CITY INCLUDING THE HEART OF
THE CITY'S FARMERS MARKET AND THE TENDERLOIN IN CIVIC
CENTER, WHICH DISTRIBUTES MILLIONS OF DOLLARS EACH YEAR
IN FOOD ASSISTANCE. I ALSO WANT TO THANK TENDERLOIN
FOOD POLICY COUNCIL HOUSE A T AND D.C. FOR THEIR CONTINUED
ADVOCACY AROUND FOOD ACCESS AND PROGRAMS LIKE MARKET MATCH.
AT A TIME WHEN WE'RE SEEING GROCERY STORE CLOSURES
AND PERSISTENT FOOD ACCESS CHALLENGES IN NEIGHBORHOODS
LIKE THE TENDERLOIN, FILLMORE AND WESTERN ADDITION PROGRAMS
LIKE THIS ARE MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVER.
>> THIS RESOLUTION SIMPLY URGES THE STATE TO CONTINUE INVESTING
IN A PROGRAM THAT SUPPORTS FAMILIES, FARMERS AND HEALTHY
FOOD ACCESS. AND I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
CHEN AGAIN FOR CO-SPONSORING THIS RESOLUTION.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MONK MODE SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO ALLOW CANNABIS CAFES IN THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
SPECIFICALLY THIS ORDINANCE WILL ALLOW CANNABIS BUSINESSES
TO PREPARE AND SERVE SERVE FOOD AND NON-ALCOHOL BEVERAGES FOR
ONSITE CONSUMPTION. FRANKLY IT'S ODD TO ME THAT
THIS ACTIVITY IS CURRENTLY PROHIBITED AND SO THIS
LEGISLATION STRIKES ME AS PRETTY COMMON SENSE.
WE'VE TALKED MANY TIMES AT THIS BOARD ABOUT THE UNIQUE
REGULATORY AND TAX BURDENS CARRIED BY LEGAL CANNABIS
RETAILERS EVEN AS THEY COMPETE AGAINST A LARGER AND REGULATED
AND UNTAXED ILLICIT MARKET. >> IF WE WANT TO SHRINK THAT
ILLICIT MARKET, I BELIEVE WE SHOULD BE DOING WHAT WE
REASONABLY CAN TO SUPPORT THE LEGAL CANNABIS INDUSTRY.
AND CANNABIS CAFES ARE A REAL ECONOMIC OPPORTUNITY FOR THESE
BUSINESSES TO GO FROM SURVIVING TO THRIVING.
IN 2024 THE STATE LEGISLATURE PASSED AND THE GOVERNOR SIGNED
ASSEMBLYMEMBER MATT HANEY'S AB 1775 TO ALLOW CANNABIS CAFES
IN CALIFORNIA. THIS LEGISLATION WOULD THIS
ORDINANCE WOULD IMPLEMENT THAT LEGISLATION HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. NOW ONE MIGHT EXPECT THAT AFTER
THE PASSAGE OF HB 1775 ALLOWING ONSITE CONSUMPTION OF FOOD
AND NONALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES AT A CANNABIS BUSINESS WOULD BE A
SIMPLE PROJECT. IT WAS NOT.
>> BEN VAN HOUTEN OF EWG DESERVES A LOT OF CREDIT FOR
ALL THE HARD WORK HE PUT INTO FIGURING OUT HOW TO MAKE
CANNABIS CAFES A POSSIBILITY IN THE REAL WORLD NOT JUST ON
PAPER. AND THE RESULT IS AN ORDINANCE
THAT AMENDS OUR HEALTH PLANNING POLICE AND BUSINESS AND TAX
CODES. I WANT TO GIVE SPECIAL THANKS
TO SARAH CROWLEY AND THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE OFFICE
AND THE CAS PATEL, RAY LAU AND JEREMY SCHWARTZ IN THE
OFFICE OF CANNABIS FOR THEIR HELP ALONG THE WAY.
I WANT TO THANK DUNCAN LIE AND DAN LYMAN WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO CANNABIS ALLIANCE FOR THEIR HELPFUL PARTICIPATION
IN CRAFTING THIS. AND I WANT TO THANK MY
LEGISLATIVE AIDE SOPHIE MARIE FOR WORKING WITH ALL THESE
STAKEHOLDERS AND GETTING THIS ORDINANCE READY FOR
INTRODUCTION. I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT
COLLEAGUES AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL COLLEAGUES
TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION ALONGSIDE TUBEROSE
OR MAHMOOD INTRODUCED URGING THE SAVE MART COMPANIES TO
RECONSIDER ITS RECENT DECISION TO CLOSE THE LUCKY'S
SUPERMARKET AT 1750 FULTON STREET.
SINCE THE CLOSURE OF THE FILLMORE SAFEWAY IN 2025
RESIDENTS ACROSS NOPAL ALAMO SQUARE FILLMORE WESTERN EDITION
HAVE RELIED ON LUCKY'S SUPERMARKET AT FULTON TO GET
THEIR GROCERIES. THESE NEIGHBORHOODS ARE HOME TO
COMMUNITIES OF COLOR SENIORS, STUDENTS, YOUNG FAMILIES,
WORKING CLASS SAN FRANCISCANS, COMMUNITIES WHO HAVE BEEN
HISTORICALLY OVERLOOKED WHO DO NOT OFTEN HAVE RELIABLE ACCESS
TO A CAR AND WHO NEED NEARBY EASILY ACCESSIBLE MARKETS.
AND WITH THIS LUCKY SUPERMARKET NOW PREPARING TO CLOSE
IN SEPTEMBER, THESE RESIDENTS WILL ONCE AGAIN BE FORCED TO
SHOP FURTHER AND FURTHER AWAY FROM THEIR HOMES, LIMITING
THEIR ACCESS TO QUICK GROCERY NEEDS AND HURTING THEIR QUALITY
OF LIFE. >> THIS RESOLUTION CALLS ON
SAVE MART COMPANIES THE CORPORATE OPERATOR OF LUCKY TO
RECONSIDER ITS PLANS TO CLOSE AND TO WORK WITH THE
SURROUNDING COMMUNITIES TO DEVELOP A PLAN TO PRESERVE
GROCERY ACCESS IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> BUT AT THE SAME TIME WE MUST ALSO RECOGNIZE THAT WE CAN'T
JUST FORCE COMPANIES TO STAY OPEN WHEN THEY ARE LOSING
MONEY. THAT WOULD BE IGNORING REALITY
. SO I'M COMMITTED TO ALSO DOING
THE WORK TO BETTER UNDERSTAND EXACTLY WHY BY DATA AND NOT
JUST VIBES CERTAIN GROCERY STORES ARE CLOSING IN CERTAIN
NEIGHBORHOODS ACROSS THE CITY. WHAT DO WE AS A CITY WE AS A
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS NEED TO DO TO ENCOURAGE GROCERY STORES NOT
JUST TO OPEN WHERE THEY'RE NEEDED BUT ALSO TO STAY OPEN
AND SERVE THE COMMUNITIES WHO DESPERATELY NEED THESE
SERVICES. I'M THANKFUL FOR THE SUPPORT
FROM THE MAYOR'S OFFICE WHO'S WORKING ALONGSIDE SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD AND ME TO ENCOURAGE SAVE MART COMPANIES TO RECONSIDER
THE CLOSURE OF THIS SPECIFIC SITE AND ALSO TO INCREASE
GROCERY STORE ACCESS ACROSS THE ENTIRE CITY.
I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING THIS WORK ON BEHALF OF OUR
CONSTITUENTS ALONGSIDE ALL OF YOU.
THANK YOU COLLEAGUES AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD DID YOU WANT TO COMMENT?
YES. I JUST WANTED TO THANK
SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION
AND FOR WORKING WITH OUR OFFICE ON THE ISSUE AFFECTING
RESIDENTS ACROSS THE WESTERN CONDITION AND SURROUNDING
NEIGHBORHOODS. THE LUCKY'S MARKET AS ADVISOR
CHERYL NOTED, HAS BEEN A CRITICAL GROCERY OPTION FOR
RESIDENTS IN THE WESTERN TRADITION FILLMORE, ALAMO
SQUARE AND NORTH OF PANHANDLE IN DISTRICT FIVE FOR MANY YEARS
AND THE NECESSITY FOR IT HAS ONLY INCREASED SINCE THE
SAFEWAYS CLOSURE ON FILLMORE LAST YEAR.
IT ANNOUNCES CLOSURE FOR SEPTEMBER 11TH OF THIS YEAR
WHICH IS RAISING SERIOUS CONCERNS FOR AFFORDABLE
GROCERIES IN THIS PART OF THE CITY AND THE LOSS OF ANOTHER
GROCERY STORE IN ADDITION TO THE FILLMORE SAFEWAY IN SUCH A
SHORT PERIOD OF TIME CREATES A SERIOUS GAP IN FOOD ACCESS FOR
SENIORS FAMILIES AND RESIDENTS WHO RELY ON NEARBY NEARBY
GROCERY STORES AND PUBLIC TRANSIT.
THIS RESOLUTION WHICH I'M EXCITED TO SUPPORT WAS ADVISOR
CHERYL URGES THE SAVE MART COMPANIES TO RECONSIDER THIS
CLOSURE AND ENGAGE DIRECTLY WITH THE COMMUNITY TO EXPLORE
OPTIONS TO MAINTAIN GROCERY ACCESS IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
WE LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH SUPERVISOR CHERYL, THE
COMMUNITY AND SAVE MART TO FIND SOLUTIONS THAT SUPPORT THE
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE AN
INTRODUCTION FOR A RESOLUTION URGING THIS BODY TO KEEP THE
INDEPENDENT CIVILIAN OVERSIGHT POWERS OF OUR POLICE
COMMISSION. THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
COMMISSION EXISTS BECAUSE OUR COMMUNITY DEMANDED IT AFTER THE
DEATHS OF ALEX NIETO, AMILCAR PEREZ LOPEZ, MARIO WOODS
AND LUIS LONGORIA TO NAME A FEW.
SAN FRANCISCANS SPOKE UP, SPOKE OUT AND WON REAL STRUCTURAL
REFORMS. DE-ESCALATION STANDARDS USE OF
FORCE POLICY CRISIS INTERVENTION TRAINING BODY
CAMERA IMPLEMENTS MOTION. NONE OF THAT HAPPENED BY
ACCIDENT. IT HAPPENED BECAUSE THE
COMMISSION HAD THE INDEPENDENCE TO ACT WITHOUT POLITICAL
INTERFERENCE. >> THAT INDEPENDENCE IS ALSO
WHAT MADE OUR DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE REFORM PROCESS WORK.
IN 2016, FOLLOWING THOSE SAME HIGH PROFILE SHOOTINGS, SAN
FRANCISCO INVITED THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE TO
CONDUCT A TOP TO BOTTOM REVIEW OF THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT. >> THE RESULT WAS 270 TWO
RECOMMENDATIONS ACROSS USE OF FORCE BIAS ACCOUNTABILITY,
COMMUNITY POLICING AND HIRING PRACTICES.
WHEN THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION PULLED OUT OF THE PROCESS
IN 2017, SAN FRANCISCO DID NOT WALK AWAY.
THE CITY CONTINUED TO WORK VOLUNTARILY WITH THE CALIFORNIA
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE. EIGHT YEARS LATER, IN JANUARY
2025 S.F. PD WAS FOUND TO BE IN SUBSTANTIAL COMPLIANCE USE
OF FORCE DOWN OFFICER INVOLVED SHOOTINGS CUT IN HALF.
>> THAT IS WHAT REAL REFORM AND REAL OVERSIGHT LOOKS LIKE.
>> THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE PROPOSAL TO CHANGE EXACTLY THE
STRUCTURE THAT MADE THAT POSSIBLE IS UNJUST, INEQUITABLE
AND RACIST. >> THIS DECISION TO STRIP DOWN
THE INDEPENDENT POLICE OVERSIGHT WAS MADE STRICTLY BY
PEOPLE IN THE MAJORITY. ASK YOURSELF WHO IS HARMED
AND WHO MAKES THE DECISIONS. STRIPPING THE COMMISSION OF ITS
DISCIPLINARY AUTHORITY IS NOT A TECHNICAL FIX.
IT IS A FUNDAMENTAL SHIFT IN WHO HOLDS POWER OVER POLICE
ACCOUNTABILITY IN THIS CITY. THE POLICE COMMISSION WAS A
CENTRAL STAKEHOLDER IN THE ENTIRE DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE
REFORM PROCESS. WHEN YOU WEAKEN IT NOW IN THE
NAME OF STREAMLINING YOU PUT EVERYTHING THAT WAS BUILT AT
RISK. INDEPENDENT CIVILIAN OVERSIGHT
IS NOT A BUREAUCRATIC CHECK BOX.
NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED PRINCIPLES ARE CLEAR.
INDEPENDENCE, TRANSPARENCY AND INSULATION FROM POLITICAL
INTERFERENCE ARE NOT OPTIONAL FEATURES.
>> THEY ARE THE WHOLE POINT THE MOMENT OVERSIGHT BECOMES
SUBJECT TO POLITICAL PRESSURE IT STOPS BEING OVERSIGHT.
>> THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IS ON RECORD IN A REFORM AFFECTING
POLICE GOVERNANCE MUST GO THROUGH A TRANSPARENT PUBLIC
PROCESS WITH EXPERT INPUT AND FULL COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT.
EVEN STREAMLINING TASK FORCE MEMBER ED HARRINGTON STATED THE
COMMITTEE DID NOT HAVE THE KNOWLEDGE TO STEP INTO
SOMETHING THAT INVOLVED EFFICIENCY IS A LEGITIMATE GOAL
DISMANTLE CIVILIAN ACCOUNTABILITY TO ACHIEVE IT IS
NOT A TRADEOFF. THIS IS TO ACCEPT THE REST.
>> I SUBMIT THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON.
SUPERVISOR HUANG SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN.
SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MADAM CARD. COLLEAGUE TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING THE SAN FRANCISCO MTA TO HONOR
THE COMMITMENTS IT MADE TO DELIVER 465 UNITS OF AFFORDABLE
HOUSING DURING THE PATROL YARD MODERNIZATION PROJECTS.
>> THE MATERIAL MODERNIZATION PROJECT LOCATED AT 17
AND BRYANT STREET WAS DECIDED AS A ONCE IN OUR GENERATION
JOINT DEVELOPMENT PROJECT TO COMBINE A MODERN TRANSIT
FACILITY WITH 465 UNITS OF 100 PRESENT AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
MEETING THE CITY'S PRIORITIES OF PROVIDING RELIABLE PUBLIC
TRANSIT AND MEETING OUR REGIONAL HOUSING NEEDS.
ALLOCATION GOALS UNDER THE HOUSING ELEMENT TO BUILD OVER
46,000 AFFORDABLE HOMES FOR OVER A YEAR AND THROUGH MORE
THAN 55 PUBLIC MEETINGS TO PATROL YOUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
WORKING GROUP DEDICATED THOUSANDS OF HOURS TO SHAPING
THE PROJECT'S AFFORDABLE HOUSING COMPONENTS
IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO MTA.
>> EARLIER THIS MONTH THE SAN FRANCISCO MTA BOARD OF
DIRECTORS APPROVED AT A MASSIVE REDUCTION IN HOUSING SCOPE FOR
THE PATROL YARD MODERNIZATION PROJECTS REDUCING THE NUMBER OF
AFFORDABLE HOMES FROM 465 TO 100 UNITS NET LOSS OF 365
AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS OR 80% OF THE AFFORDABLE HOMES
PREVIOUSLY APPROVED BY THE MTA BOARD AND THIS BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS IN 2024. >> THIS IS A TREMENDOUS,
TREMENDOUS, TREMENDOUS POLICY FAILURES FOR THE AGENCY AND FOR
OUR CITY. THE SAN FRANCISCO MTA HAS
SIGNIFICANT INVENTORY OF PUBLIC LANDS INCLUDING 34 SITES THAT
IT HAS IDENTIFIED FOR FUTURE JOINT DEVELOPMENT THAT
COMPROMISE PARKING LOTS, PARKING GARAGES AND FACILITIES
WHICH PROVIDE A SIGNIFICANT OPPORTUNITY TO LEVERAGE NEW
100% AFFORDABLE DEVELOPMENT. AND THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND OUR MAYOR CONSIDERED THE AFFORDABILITY CRISIS THAT HAS
BEEN FACING OUR CITY FOR YEARS. WE CANNOT CONTINUE TO SHYING
AWAY FROM INVESTMENT THAT HELP US FIGHT AGAINST DISPLACEMENT
AND KEEP WORKING FAMILIES HOUSING.
I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT OUR PUBLIC AGENCIES RESTORE THE
TRUST THAT HAS BEEN LOST AND MAKE GOOD ON THEIR
COMMITMENTS TO DELIVER THE ADDITIONAL 365 UNITS OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. >> I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR HER CO-SPONSORS FOR HER EARLY
CO-SPONSOR SHIP. >> I ALSO HAVE A MEMORIAL I
WOULD LIKE TO I JOIN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF MR. JOSE
SINGSON. MR. JAO WAS BORN IN FEBRUARY
10TH, 1934 IN CHINA AND PASSED PEACEFULLY IN SAN FRANCISCO ON
FEBRUARY 15, 2026 AT THE AGE OF 92.
MR. JAO FACED MANY CHALLENGES AS A YOUNG PERSON AND LIKE MANY
OTHERS DURING THAT TIME DID NOT HAVE ACCESS TO EDUCATION.
HE LOST HIS PARENTS AT AGE OF TEN, LEAVING HIM AND HIS TWO
SISTER TO RELY ON EACH OTHER. AT AGE 15 HE LEFT HOME TO FIND
WORK HIS HARD WORK AND PERSEVERANCE LEAD TO
IMMIGRATING TO THE UNITED STATES WITH HIS FAMILY IN THEIR
90S. >> MR. DAO WAS BELOVED
AND MEMBER OF OUR COMMUNITY FOSTERING DEEP FRIENDSHIPS WITH
THOSE AROUND HIM. HE ENJOYED DUE IN HIS CHILDREN
THAT THE VALUE OF COMMUNITY SERVICES.
HIS DAUGHTER CHEE HUA JAO IS A LEADER OF A HOME CARE WORKER
MOVEMENT. >> FOR THE LAST 20 YEARS HE WAS
A DEVOTED HUSBAND AND FATHER OF FOUR AND IS AND IS SURVIVED BY
HIS CHILDREN, GRANDCHILDREN AND GREAT GRANDCHILDREN.
MAY HIS MEMORY BE A BLESSING FOR THOSE WHO WERE FORTUNATE TO
CROSS PATHS WITH HIM AND THEIR SOMETHING.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN. SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. AND SUPERVISOR CHAN HAS TO BE
REFERRED. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M OFFERING AN IMMORAL FOR MRS. BASIL WONG
A LONGTIME SAN FRANCISCAN AND PILLAR OF THE
CHINESE-AMERICAN COMMUNITY WHO PASSED AWAY MARCH 13TH, 2026 AT
THE AGE OF 96. >> SHE IMMIGRATED FROM CHINA
AND WAS MARRIED TO HARLEM. WONG, A WORLD WAR TWO VETERAN.
THEY BEGAN THEIR FAMILY IN SAN FRANCISCO IN 1947 WITH THEIR
FIRST HOME IN THE RICHMOND. MRS. WONG BECAME THE OPERATOR
OF THE 27 AVENUE MARKET, A CORNER GROCERY STORE IN THE
RICHMOND DISTRICT IN 1959 WHILE HER HUSBAND SERVED AS AN AGENT
WITH THE U.S. TREASURY DEPARTMENT, EVENTUALLY BECAME
THE FIRST U.S. CUSTOMS INSPECTOR OF CHINESE DESCENT
IN THE U.S. MAINLAND. DESPITE LIMITED FORMAL
EDUCATION IN THE U.S., MRS. WONG LAUNCH A CAREER AS ONE OF
THE FIRST CHINESE-AMERICAN WOMAN REALTORS IN SAN FRANCISCO
IN 1965 AND THROUGH HER KEEN BUSINESS ACUMEN, SOCIAL
AND BILINGUAL SKILLS. SHE BECAME A LEGENDARY REAL
ESTATE AGENT AND ENABLING MANY CHINESE AMERICANS TO REALIZE
THEIR DREAM AS FIRST TIME HOME OWNERS.
BEYOND THE TRAILBLAZING CAREER PATH, MRS. WONG WAS ALSO
DEDICATED TO SERVICE. SHE WAS PAST PRESIDENT OF THE
CHINESE AMERICAN REAL ESTATE ASSOCIATION AND A FOUNDING
MEMBER OF THE GATEWAYS SAVINGS AND LOAN BANK.
SHE WAS ONE OF THE FOUNDERS OF THE CHINESE GRACE BAPTIST
CHURCH IN SAN FRANCISCO'S RICHMOND DISTRICT PROVIDING
FAITH BASED BILINGUAL SERVICES SERVING MULTIPLE GENERATIONS.
SHE BALANCE ALL OF THIS WHILE RAISING FOUR CHILDREN.
PROUD PRODUCTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC SCHOOL SYSTEM
AND GRADUATE OF UC BERKELEY WHO LATER WENT ON TO ESTABLISH A
GREAT CAREER IN LAW MEDICINE AND REAL ESTATE RESPECTIVELY.
SHE WAS ALSO THE GRANDMOTHER OF TEN AND THE GREAT GRANDMOTHER
OF SEVEN. MRS. WONG, WHO NEVER RETIRED,
ALWAYS PREFER A GOOD HARD DAY'S WORK TO UNSTRUCTURED LEISURELY
DAYS AND CONTINUE HER UNINTERRUPTED ERUPTIVE CAREER
THROUGH AGE 96. AND FOR THAT IT WAS MY
PRIVILEGE AND IS MY PRIVILEGE TO BE ABLE TO OFFER THIS
IN MEMORIAM FOR HER AND HER FAMILY.
AND MAY SHE REST IN POWER. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHAN MR. PRESIDENT, THAT CONCLUDES THE
INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> THERE WE GO. LET'S GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL
ORDER RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS.
>> YES, THIS IS A SPECIAL ORDER AT 230.
IT'S THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> ALL RIGHT. AND TODAY I'M GOING TO START
DIRECTOR PATRICK REARDON. >> PLEASE COME UP.
>> COLLEAGUES, TODAY WE ARE HONORING PATRICK REARDON,
DIRECTOR OF THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING INSPECTION WHO WILL BE
RETIRING AT THE END OF THE WEEK BY ENSURING THAT OUR BUILDINGS
ARE CONSTRUCTED, MAINTAINED AND USED IN ACCORDANCE WITH OUR
CODES. THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTION PLAYS A CRITICAL ROLE IN ENSURING SAN
FRANCISCO'S SAFETY AND HABITABILITY.
FOR MORE THAN A QUARTER CENTURY FIRST AS AN INSPECTOR AND LATER
AS DIRECTOR PATRICK REARDON HAS SHAPED THE WAY DVI CARRIES OUT
ITS MISSION. >> HE WAS BORN IN COUNTY CORK,
IRELAND. HE RELOCATED TO SAN FRANCISCO
IN 1985 AND BEGAN WORKING AS A CARPENTER.
HE SPENT TIME IN AUSTRALIA BEFORE RETURNING TO THE BAY
AREA AND WAS EVENTUALLY HIRED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTION AS A FIELD INSPECTOR IN 2000.
>> THE EARLY 2000 SAW A BOOM IN SAN FRANCISCO CONSTRUCTION
AND PATRICK LED INSPECTIONS ON MANY OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST
ICONIC PROJECTS INCLUDING SALESFORCE TOWER ONE, RINCON
HILL, THE WARRIORS ARENA, THE SHRINERS TOWNHOMES AND THE
EXPANSION OF THE CONSERVATORY OF MUSIC.
PATRICK EARNED A PROMOTION TO SENIOR BUILDING INSPECTOR
IN 2008 AND THEN CHIEF BUILDING INSPECTOR IN 2013.
AS CHIEF HE LED ALL BUILDING INSPECTIONS CITYWIDE
AND OVERSAW DOZENS OF INSPECTORS IN 2020.
PATRICK WAS APPOINTED AS INTERIM AND THEN PERMANENT DBA
DIRECTOR UNDER HIS LEADERSHIP. THE DEPARTMENT MADE PROGRESS
IN A NUMBER OF AREAS INCLUDING DATA DRIVEN PROCESS
IMPROVEMENTS AND OPERATIONS, IMPLEMENTING NEW OVERSIGHT
MEASURES TO IMPROVE TRANSPARENCY AND STREAMLINE THE
PERMITTING AND INSPECTION PROCESS.
SIX YEARS AGO WHEN PATRICK STARTED AS DIRECTOR IT TOOK A
MEDIAN OF 272 DAYS TO ISSUE AN IN-HOUSE PERMIT.
TODAY ISSUANCE TIMES ARE DOWN MORE THAN 70%.
PATRICK WE ARE GRATEFUL FOR YOUR MANY CONTRIBUTIONS TO I
AND THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
YOU WERE THE RIGHT PERSON FOR THE JOB AT A TIME WHEN THE
DEPARTMENT NEEDED A STEADY, EXPERIENCED AND TRUSTWORTHY
HAND AT THE HELM. WE WISH YOU WELL ON YOUR
RETIREMENT AND WE CONGRATULATE YOUR WIFE, TWO DAUGHTERS
AND GRANDDAUGHTER WHO I AM SURE WILL FIND WAYS TO KEEP YOU
QUITE OCCUPIED IN THE YEARS AHEAD.
>> AND BEFORE I INVITE YOU TO SAY A FEW WORDS, I SEE THAT MY
COLLEAGUES ARE PUTTING GETTING THEMSELVES INTO THE QUEUE.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU FOR PRESENT.
>> PATRICK WHEN I LEARNED MORE ABOUT YOUR STORY I WAS VERY
MOVED BY THE FACT THAT YOU HAVE CONDUCTED OVER 23,007 HUNDRED
INSPECTIONS ON THE STRUCTURE OF EVERY SHAPE AND SIZE IN THE
CITY AND IT'S INSPIRING TO SEE YOUR STORY OF MOVING UP THE
RANKS FROM FEW INSPECTOR TO A DEPARTMENT DIRECTORS.
I AM VERY GRATEFUL TO YOU FOR YOUR STEWARDSHIP OF DBA DURING
A VERY TURBULENT PERIOD IN THE DEPARTMENT'S HISTORY.
I'M ALSO VERY GRATEFUL TO YOU FOR THE CRITICAL LIFE SAVING
WORK THAT DBA PROVIDED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WE OFTEN THINK OF CBI'S FUNCTIONS SUCH AS ENFORCING
PUMPING ELECTRICAL AND ALSO MECHANICAL CODES.
BUT I ALSO PAYS A VERY CRITICAL SOCIAL EQUITY ROLE FROM HOUSING
HABITABILITY TO DISABILITY ACCESS.
AND I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR ALL YOUR SERVICES, YOUR LEADERSHIP
AND I WISH YOU ALL THE BEST IN YOUR NEXT CHAPTER.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MADAM DIRECTOR. >> REALLY AND I JUST WANT TO
ONE OBVIOUSLY THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR SERVICE.
YOU TRANSITION IS HARD IN GENERAL AND YOU CAME ON
BOARD AT A TIME THAT WAS TUMULTUOUS FOR US HERE IN THE
CITY, PARTICULARLY WITH THE DEPARTMENT AND YOU DIDN'T MISS
A BEAT AND EVERYTHING WENT AS SMOOTH AS POSSIBLE IN YOUR ROLE
AND I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THAT.
DEVI DOESN'T ALWAYS IT'S NOT ALWAYS THE MOST LOVED
DEPARTMENT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT YOU MOST
CERTAINLY WORKED HARD TO BE ABLE TO PROVIDE THE SERVICE TO
THE PUBLIC THAT WAS NECESSARY. AND I JUST WANT TO APPRECIATE
YOU FOR THAT AND APPRECIATE YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND SAY
CONGRATULATIONS AND THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN DIRECTOR CHARETTE AND YOU KNOW I WANT TO
SAY THAT YOU HAVE DONE A LOT OF WORK GREAT WORK.
YOU KNOW DURING MY TIME AS SUPERVISOR REALLY WE ARE
GRATEFUL FOR I REMEMBER CALLING YOU ON THE WEEKEND DURING THE
STORM THAT WAS FOR THE ALEXANDRA THEATER'S BALLET
SIGNED AND THEN THERE WAS THE COLLAPSE OF THE ROOF OF THE
GOODWILL IN OUR DISTRICT WHEN IT WAS ACTUALLY EMPTY AL ALL
THESE ARE LIKE OFF HOURS TIMES AND YET YOU NOT ONLY PICK UP MY
CALL, YOU MAKE SURE THAT YOUR TEAM IT'S ON ON SITE.
THERE WERE FIRES THAT BROKE OUT IN THE RICHMOND DISTRICT THAT
WE NEED AN INSPECTOR TO BE ABLE TO COME AND CLEAR THE SITES YOU
MAKE SURE THAT YOU SEND THEM ON TIME AND ARRIVE TO REALLY HELP
US AND HELP THE FIREFIGHTERS AND EVERYBODY ON SITE.
YOU HAVE DONE SO MUCH THAT I THINK THAT MANY PEOPLE DIDN'T
KNOW OTHER THAN WHAT THEY HAVE GONE THROUGH THROUGH THE DVI
PROCESS. BUT YOU REALLY OFFLINE
AND OFTEN TIME NOT NORMAL OFFICE HOURS YOU ACTUALLY DONE
A LOT IN ESPECIALLY AN EMERGENCY SITUATION AND FOR
THAT I REALLY WANT TO COMMEND YOU AND LET PEOPLE KNOW IT
ACTUALLY TOOK A LOT TO DO WHAT YOU DO AND LET ALONE FOR THE
YEARS THAT YOU HAVE PUT IN FOR THE CITY AND FOR THE DEPARTMENT
AND WE'RE VERY GRATEFUL IT IT'S GOING TO BE A TREMENDOUS LOSS
FOR THE CITY WITHOUT YOUR KNOWLEDGE.
BUT I HAVE A FEELING THAT YOU'RE GOING TO STICK AROUND
AND WE'RE GOING TO BE ABLE TO TAP YOU, YOU KNOW, TO TO FOR
SOME HELP ACTUALLY I JUST VOLUNTEER YOU AND I KNOW THAT
BUT I JUST REALLY. AND FOR A SUPERVISOR LIKE ME,
YOU KNOW, LOOKING AT THE RICHMOND DISTRICT OFTENTIMES
JUST REALLY NEEDED THAT SOMEONE WHO LOVE THE DISTRICT LOVED THE
CITY LIKE THE WAY WE DO AND YOU DO THAT IN SO THANK YOU THANK
YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR SERVICE SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDELA AND I JUST WANT TO ADD MY VOICE TO THE
CHORUS OF PRAISE FOR YOUR WORK. I KNOW THAT YOU TOOK THE HELM
AT A CHALLENGING TIME. YOU KNOW OVER THE YEARS I'VE
HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO WORK WITH MANY AND KNOW MANY
DEPARTMENT HEADS AND I KNOW ON BEHALF OF MY STAFF
AND EVERYBODY THAT I MANY PEOPLE THAT I REPRESENT WE JUST
APPRECIATE YOUR RESPONSIVENESS AND PROFESSIONALISM.
CONGRATULATIONS ON A WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT.
THANK YOU. AND NOW DIRECTOR REARDON, THE
FLOOR IS YOURS. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MANDL
AND SUPERVISORS I CAN'T BELIEVE THAT I AM DESERVING OF ALL
THOSE KIND WORDS BUT I JUST WANT TO SAY IT'S TRULY BEEN AN
HONOR AND A PRIVILEGE TO DO THE WORK I HAVE BEEN DOING FOR THE
PAST 26 YEARS, ESPECIALLY IN THE PAST SIX YEARS.
AND I I'VE THOUGHT ABOUT IT AND I THINK THAT IF I GOT TO
REWIND I WOULD JUST DO IT ALL AGAIN THE SAME WAY THE SAME
WORK. AND I WANT TO SAY THAT I'M VERY
APPRECIATIVE OF YOUR TRUST AND YOUR SUPPORT OVER THE YEARS
. IT'S BEEN INCREDIBLE HOW WE ALL
MANAGED TO WORK AS A TEAM FOR THE BETTERMENT OF THE CITY
AND THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE IN THIS CITY.
I'D ALSO LIKE TO SAY THIS MY STAFF HAVE BEEN AMAZING.
I HAVE A GREAT TEAM MANY OF WHOM ARE HERE TODAY AND I'M
LEAVING THE DEPARTMENT IN GOOD HANDS WITH DAVID KANE.
HE WILL HE WILL CONTINUE TO DO GOOD WORK IN SERVICE OF OUR
CITY AND I WILL MISS YOU ALL AND ALL THE GOOD FRIENDS I HAVE
MADE IN CITY GOVERNMENT OVER THE YEARS AND I'M NOT GOING TO
THE MOON. I WILL BE IN SAN CARLOS AND I'M
HAPPY TO SHARE MY INFORMATION WITH ALL OF YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN DO TAP IN. YES IT'S OKAY AND JUST LIKE TO
FINISH BY SAYING HAPPY ST PATRICK'S DAY TO EVERYONE AND I
JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU ALL .
DIRECTOR, WHY DON'T YOU COME INTO THE WELL SO IT'S
ALL RIGHT. DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON
THANK YOU SO MUCH. PRESIDENT AND WOMAN COLLEAGUES
TODAY IT IS MY GREAT HONOR TO RECOGNIZE AND CELEBRATE MISS
TRACY TABOR. >> TODAY WE HONOR MISS TRACY
TABOR FOR HER 25 YEARS OF SERVICE TO THE YOUTH
AND FAMILIES OF DISTRICT TEN. TRACY'S JOURNEY BEGAN IN THE
CLASSROOM WHERE SHE SPENT A DECADE AS A PRESCHOOL TEACHER
WITH THE OAKLAND UNIFIED SCHOOL DISTRICT NURTURING AND SHAPING
YOUNG MINDS AT THE EARLIEST STAGES.
BUT HER CALLING TO SERVE EXTENDED FAR BEYOND THE
CLASSROOM AND 2001. THROUGH HER WORK WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO BROWN BOMBERS FOOTBALL TEAM, SHE WITNESSED A
HEARTBREAKING PATTERN. YOUNG MEN THRIVING DURING THE
SEASON ONLY TO STRUGGLE AFTERWARD TOO OFTEN FACING
INCARCERATION OR EVEN LOSING THEIR LIVES.
INSTEAD OF TURNING AWAY, MS. TAPER LEANED IN, SHE BEGAN
VOLUNTEERING WITH BROTHERS AGAINST GUNS OFFERING
AFTERSCHOOL TUTORING AND MENTORSHIP AND QUICKLY
BECAME A TRUSTED AND TRANSFORMATIVE PRESENCE
EVENTUALLY SERVING AS DIRECTOR OF PROGRAMS FOR TEN YEARS.
>> IN THAT ROLE SHE HELPED GUIDE COUNTLESS YOUNG PEOPLE
TOWARDS STABILITY OPPORTUNITY AND HOPE.
>> IN 2012 TRACY BROUGHT HER VISION AND LEADERSHIP TO YOUNG
COMMUNITY DEVELOPERS WHERE SHE CONTINUES TO SERVE AS DIRECTOR
OF SPECIAL INITIATIVES. THERE SHE HAS BEEN INSTRUMENTAL
IN DESIGNING AND IMPLEMENTING A WIDE RANGE OF IMPACTFUL
PROGRAMS FROM VIOLENCE PREVENTION AND CRISIS RESPONSE
TO JOB READINESS AND HEALING CENTERS TO SUPPORT FOR
TRANSITIONAL AGE YOUTH AND FAMILIES.
>> HER WORK HAS HELPED SHAPE INITIATIVES LIKE THE BAYVIEW
COMMUNITY RESPONSE NETWORK, THE PHENIX PROJECT THIS SCHOOL
CRISIS SUPPORTED INITIATIVE AND THE DISTRICT TEN SAFETY
PLAN EACH ROOTED IN THE BELIEF THAT OUR COMMUNITIES DESERVE
COORDINATED, COMPASSIONATE AND CULTURALLY RESPONSIVE
SYSTEMS OF CARE. >> WHAT SETS MS. TAPER APART IS
NOT JUST THE BREADTH OF HER WORK BUT THE DEPTH OF HER
COMMITMENT. SHE UNDERSTANDS THAT REAL
CHANGE HAPPENS THROUGH COLLABORATION AND SHE HAS BUILT
BRIDGES ACROSS ORGANIZATIONS, SYSTEMS AND COMMUNITIES TO
ENSURE NO YOUNG PERSON FALLS THROUGH THE CRACKS.
>> ONE OF THE COLLABORATION SHE IS MOST PROUD OF IS HER
PARTNERSHIP WITH THE GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS WILL BEGIN
IN 2013 AS AN OPPORTUNITY TO PROVIDE TEMPORARY EMPLOYMENT
DURING THE PLAYOFF SEASON GREW INTO A POWERFUL WORKFORCE
PIPELINE EMPLOYING OVER 250 COMMUNITY MEMBERS.
AND IN TRUE MISS TRACY FASHION, HER PROUDEST MOMENT WASN'T JUST
THE PROGRAM'S SUCCESS BUT PASSING IT ON RECOGNIZING THE
IMPORTANCE OF SUSTAINABILITY AND LEADERSHIP DEVELOPMENT.
SHE ENTRUSTED THE PROGRAM TO ONE OF HER MENTEES WHO HAS
SINCE EXPANDED IT TO INCLUDE MAJOR EVENTS LIKE THE SUPER
BOWL AND FIFA. THAT FULL CIRCLE MOMENT
WATCHING A YOUNG MAN SHE ONCE MENTORED GROW INTO A LEADER IS
THE VERY EMBODIMENT OF HER LIFE'S WORK.
>> MISS TRACY'S LEGACY IS ONE OF LOVE RESILIENCE
AND UNWAVERING BELIEF IN THE POTENTIAL OF OUR PEOPLE.
SHE HAS NOT ONLY CHANGED LIVES, SHE HAS CHANGED TRAJECTORIES,
STRENGTHENED COMMUNITIES AND HELPED TO BUILD A FUTURE
WHERE THE NEXT GENERATION IS EMPOWERED TO LEAD.
TODAY WE HONOR MS. TAPER NOT FOR WHICH SHE HAS DONE BEFORE
THE COUNTLESS LIVES SHE HAS TOUCHED THE SYSTEMS SHE HAS
HELPED TRANSFORM AND THE LEGACY SHE CONTINUES TO BUILD.
SAN FRANCISCO IS STRONGER, SAFER AND MORE COMPASSIONATE
BECAUSE OF YOU. THANK YOU TRACY FOR YOUR
SERVICE. YOUR LEADERSHIP.
>> AND FOR YOUR HEART. THANK YOU FOR.
>> I HAD TO WRITE SOMETHING BECAUSE I KNEW I WOULD BE
CRYING AND I PROBABLY WOULDN'T REMEMBER EVERYTHING.
SO FORGIVE ME IF I RE. FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU SO MUCH
AND I AM SO HONORED TO BE ACCEPTING THIS FROM YOU.
SUPERVISOR WATER AIR FROM THE CITY I LOVE.
I DIDN'T I WASN'T BORN HERE AND TO THOSE WHO ARE NAITO'S I
FLEW HERE BUT I GREW HERE SO I NEED TO MAKE THAT KNOWN.
>> MR. WALKED IN SOMETHING I'VE NEVER SHARED WITH YOU IS THAT
WHEN YOU OFFERED ME A JOB I SAID I HAD JUST PRAYED TO GOD.
IF YOU CANNOT OPEN A DOOR PLEASE OPEN A WINDOW BECAUSE I
WAS GOING THROUGH SOME THINGS AND I NEEDED A BREAK TO
CONTINUE AND YOU ARE OFFERING ME THIS OPPORTUNITY SO TO
RECEIVE THIS FROM YOU FROM YOU TODAY IS BEYOND WHAT I CAN SAY
AND WORDS HOWEVER I CAN SAY I APPRECIATE YOU AND I THANK YOU
AND IF YOU KNOW ME YOU KNOW I DO NOT PLAY WHEN IT COMES TO
SUPERVISOR WAITING I BEGAN MY COMMUNITY WORK AFTER WITNESSING
THE SENSELESS DEATH AND INCARCERATION OF OUR YOUNG
PEOPLE ESPECIALLY OUR BLACK YOUNG MEN.
AND AS A MOTHER OF A BLACK SON MY GOAL HAS ALWAYS BEEN
AND WILL CONTINUE TO BE TO KEEP YOU YOUTH IN THE WORDS OF DR.
JOE MARSHALL ALIVE AND FREE. THIS IS THE CORE OF EVERYTHING
I DO. SO WHEN I BUMP HEADS WITH
PEOPLE WHICH I OFTEN DO JUST KNOW THAT THAT'S WHAT I'M
THINKING WHEN I'M TALKING TO YOU.
MY INTENT IS TO SERVE THAT IS MY MINISTRY WHO I AM.
>> HOW DOES MY MINISTRY SHOW WHAT I'M THAT MOM TO A BLACK
SON? I'M THEIR FRIEND THAT'S DAYS
LATER TO CLEAN UP. I'M THE TEACHER THAT SUPPORTS
YOUR LESSON PLANS WITH BOOKS AND ACTIVITIES TO BRING YOUR
LESSON TO LIFE. I'M THAT FUN AUNTIE THAT LETS
THEM PUT THE MATTRESS ON THE FLOOR AND WRESTLE I'M THE ROOM
NOW NAP ROOM MOM THAT PLANS PURCHASE SEATS SETS UP
AND CLEANS UP FOR ALL THE CLASS PARTIES THE TEEN MOM WHO MAKES
SANDWICHES FOR THE WHOLE TEAM I'M THE COMMUNITY ADVOCATE WHO
WILL ALWAYS FIGHT TO ENSURE THAT ALL THE PARTNERS AT THE
TABLE HAVE RESOURCES. THIS IS THE MY RESUME AND THIS
IS WHY I STAND BEFORE YOU TODAY .
BUT ENOUGH ABOUT ME AS THIS IS WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH I KEEP
SEEING THIS QUOTE GET IN THE ROOM WITH WOMEN WHO REMIND YOU
OF YOUR POWER WHEN YOU FORGET THIS RESONATED WITH ME BECAUSE
BEING A WOMAN IN LEADERSHIP AND COMMUNITY AND JUST BEING A
WOMAN IS NOT EASY AND WE DO NEED SUPPORT AND TO EMPOWER
EACH OTHER SO SO TODAY I WOULD LIKE TO RECOGNIZE THE WOMEN
THAT EMPOWER ME AS WELL. A NOLA MAXWELL WHO I MET AT
PATROL HILL NEIGHBORHOOD HOUSE WHEN I WAS IN MIDDLE SCHOOL WAS
A WOMAN WHO ALWAYS SPOKE HER MIND MS..
>> ESPANOLA JACKSON WHO I LOVE WATCHING HER SPEAK TO THE
POWERS THAT BE ABOUT THE INJUSTICES IN OUR COMMUNITY.
>> MS. JOYCE ARMSTRONG WHO WAS THE YOUTH PROGRAM DIRECTOR AT
THE NEI AND GAVE ME MY FIRST JOB AND I'M HOPING I'M DOING
HER PROUD AND I WATCHED HER WITH HER STRONG LEADERSHIP
SKILLS. MS..
TANISHA HOLLINS WHO BROUGHT THE COMMUNITY TOGETHER TO START
THIRD STREET YOUTH CLINIC AND NOW SERVES AS HEAD OF
CALIFORNIA'S FOR SAFETY AND JUSTICE.
MS.. LATIFA SIMON, WHO I MET WHEN
SHE SERVED AS A LEADER OF YOUNG WOMEN'S FREEDOM CENTER AND HAD
JUST WON A MACARTHUR FELLOWSHIP FOR A LEADERSHIP AND IS ONE OF
THE MOST ELOQUENT SPEAKERS AND A STRONG COMMUNITY
ADVOCATE. >> MS. KAMALA HARRIS, WHO
RECEIVED FUNDS FROM NANCY PELOSI'S OFFICE TO START THE
BAYVIEW KEIRIN AND ALLOWED THE COMMUNITY ITS EXPERTISE TO
DESIGN AND IMPLEMENT THE SERVICES DR. SAYEEDA LED TO THE
2 TO 2 LA2 I CAN I SAY YOU KNOW DOCTOR DR. ASSI I'M SORRY WHO I
WANT TO BE WHEN I GROW UP BECAUSE SHE REMINDS US THAT THE
MASTER'S TOOLS WILL NEVER DISMANTLE THE MASTER'S HOUSE.
MS. THAT LIZ JACKSON SIMPSON WHO IS THE BLUEPRINT FOR MOST
JUVENILE PROBATION SERVICES IN SAN FRANCISCO CHIEF KATIE
MILLER WHO TAUGHT ME HOW TO WRITE WORK PLANS WHEN I STARTED
IN NONPROFIT MS. CLINIC WEATHER'S BEEN MOSTLY YOUNG WHO
ARE MASTERS OF YOUTH DEVELOPMENT AND PROGRAM
DELIVERY. MS. CHERISE DORSEY, WHO I MET
AS THE SENIOR PROGRAM SPECIALIST OF DC WYETH.
AND WHEN HER CLINIC GOT TOGETHER THE VISION STARTED
FLOWING AND WAS INCREDIBLE TO WATCH AS SHE NOW SERVES AS OF
DC WYETH OUR CHILDREN ARE IN GOOD HANDS.
OKAY SORRY MISS JASMINE DAWSON WHO HAS SERVED WITH ME ON TWO
DIFFERENT INITIATIVES AND HAS MANAGED TO ALWAYS BE GRACEFUL
UNDER FIRE WHILE GETTING THE JOB DONE AND I WOULD LIKE TO
ADD MS. AMONG COMBS TO THAT AS WELL.
MS.. CAROL TATUM WHO IS ONE OF THE
MOST GRACIOUS COMMUNITY LEADERS I HOPE I CAN LIVE UP TO HER
EXAMPLE MISS TRACY BROWN WHO IS TRACY FROM THE MISSION?
I'M TRACY FROM THE BAY VIEW TOGETHER IT'S TNT AND IS A
FIERCE PARTNER AND EXTRAORDINARY VISIONARY FOR
THE COMMUNITY. SHE ALSO SERVES AS PART OF THE
WOMEN OF D-10 OFFICE WITH MS. NATALIE G AND LINDSAY LOPEZ TO
SUPPORT SUPERVISING WALTON AND D-10 REALLY APPRECIATE YOU
ALL. MS. VALERIE TYLER AM I SARAH
NARON WHO RUNS COMMUNITY MEETINGS LIKE A DRILL SERGEANT
AND GETS THE JOB DONE? MR. MARA WALKER WHO IS
EXTRAORDINARY STORY TO HER PATH TO LEADERSHIP AND IS A THOUGHT
PARTNER IN THE WORK. MS. MELODY DANIELS EDDY
COUNTY'S POINT FAMILY WHO WORKS TIRELESSLY TO OVERSEE PROGRAMS
FOR YOUNG PEOPLE MY SISTER FRIEND DIANE GRAY WHOSE VISION
FOR YOUNG PEOPLE HAS IMPLEMENTED SEVERAL SUCCESSFUL
PROGRAMS THAT SERVE S.F. YOUTH AND WHO AGREE TO LET ME SHARE
HER MIND WITH ME TODAY. >> THANK YOU FOR COMING, MS.
VALENTINO SEDAN DANIEL MY RIDER DIE IN A WORK SHE IS THE MOST
DEDICATED COMMUNITY WORKER I HAVE EVER WORKED WITH AND IT IS
AN HONOR TO SIT NEXT TO HER EVERY DAY AND DO THIS WORK
AND JUST KNOW I DON'T PLAY ABOUT HER TOO BECAUSE THEY KNOW
I'LL SHOW UP AT DEAD JEOPARDY MEANING IF Y'ALL MESS WITH HER
A SHOUT OUT TO THE WOMEN OF Y C D MY LEADERSHIP RASHIDA JORDAN
DUVALL RAMKALAWAN AND ESPECIALLY MY TEAM DENICE
AMANDA ANITA STEPHANIE DESTINY KIARA TIFFANY NATASHA RUTHA
CORBETT MISKIN MS. SONG AND OF COURSE MY DAUGHTER MANILA
MANILA BACK TO ALL THE COMMUNITY WOMEN I WORK WITH DR.
PATSY TITO, GLORIA ROMERO, RUTH BARAJAS I SEE DON STECKEL HERE
I'M SORRY SARA Y JOANNA HERNANDEZ WHO ARE THOUGHT
PARTNERS IN A WORK MY PARSLEY MY HOMEGIRLS DON ROBIN ROBBINS,
CHERYL BENITA, LORNA AND ESPECIALLY RETIRED CAPTAIN
NIKKI GRIFFEY WHO TRAINED OVER 300 MEN AND WOMEN AT THE S.F.
FIRE DEPARTMENT OF TRAINING WHO OPENED THE DOORS TO THE
FIREHOUSE SO I COULD TAKE MY GIRLS FROM WEST POINT TO LEARN
ABOUT CAREERS IN THE FIRE DEPARTMENT.
AND OF COURSE MISS RENE FROM HURTS PLAYGROUND LONG TIME
FRAME LASTLY TO MY MOM AND GRANDMA MY GRANDMA WHO
TAUGHT ME THE POWER OF PRAYER AND MY FAITH IN JESUS CHRIST
AND MY MOM WHO WENT BACK TO SCHOOL TO EARN HER NURSING
DEGREE AFTER SHE GRADUATED SHE'D PUT TWO KIDS IN A CAR
AND DROVE FROM NEW JERSEY TO SAN FRANCISCO AND SPENT OVER 20
YEARS WORKING WITH YOUTH WHO HAD CANCER AND NEEDED A
TRANSPLANT. THIS YEAR MARKS THE 30TH YEAR
OF MY MOM'S PASSING SO FOR ME THIS IS A FITTING TRIBUTE TO
HER LEGACY. IF I MISSED ANYONE, PLEASE
ACCEPT MY APOLOGIES AND KNOW THAT I SEE YOU AND IF A LITTLE
OF THE LIGHT OF THESE AWESOME WOMEN SHOWN ON ME AND ARE
REFLECTED BACK TO OTHERS I FEEL I WOULD HAVE DONE WHAT I CAME
HERE TO DO. >> THIS MOMMY IS FOR YOU.
THANK YOU, TRACY. GO SEE TWO TRACY EVERYBODY FOR
ONE TO THE MOST IMPORTANT AND OKAY DISTRICT ONE
SUPERVISOR JAN THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAN DOMAIN THIS TODAY
THE SPECIAL COMMENDATION IS VERY SPECIAL TO ME PERSONALLY
BECAUSE THIS IS A FRIEND A LONG TIME COLLEAGUE OF MINE AND I'M
VERY GRATEFUL THAT I HAVE THE HONOR AND THE PRIVILEGE TO
RECOGNIZE HIM. TODAY I AM HONORING
AND RECOGNIZING OSCAR, RAUL SAYS YEAH AND THIS IS ON THE
OCCASION OF REALLY HONORING HIS CAREER WITH OUR CITY AND WITH
THE SAN FRANCISCO RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT.
HE SAID HE'S RETIRING. I CANNOT BELIEVE IT BECAUSE I
THINK HE'S YOUNGER THAN ME. SO WHAT'S HAPPENING?
>> BUT OSCAR AS A KID LEARN TO SWIM AT ROCKY PAUL BACK WHEN IT
ONLY COST A DIME AND SPENT MUCH OF HIS YOUTH AT FULLERTON
PLAYGROUND, THOSE EARLY EXPERIENCES PLANTED THE SEA FOR
A LIFELONG CONNECTION TO PARKS POOLS AND PEOPLE OSCAR WORK AS
A LOCKER ATTENDANT. >> THEN PART TIME LIFEGUARD
AND A PART TIME PERMANENT LIFEGUARD IN 1989 THROUGH
DEDICATION AND A DEEP LOVE FOR PUBLIC SERVICE, HE BECAME A
PERMANENT RECREATION DIRECTOR IN 2009.
HE ALSO SERVED AT MANY LOVE TO WAR AND RICHMOND RECREATION
CENTER BEFORE JOINING THE GOLDEN GATE PARK SENIOR CENTER
AS A FACILITY COORDINATOR, OSCAR PROUDLY TAUGHT TO LEARN
TO SWIM CLASSES FOR YOU ALWAYS ALWAYS EMPHASIZING SAFETY,
PREPARATION AND SELF-CONFIDENCE.
A TRUE LOVER OF THE WATER HE FAMOUSLY WORE A WETSUIT WHILE
TEACHING MUCH TO THE AMUSEMENT OF HIS STAFF.
HE ALSO HELPED LAUNCH THE DEPARTMENT'S FIRST SURF CAMP
AND PLAY A ROLE IN ESTABLISHING ONE OF THE FIRST OFFICIAL
PICKLEBALL PROGRAMS AND MANY, MANY AT THE SENIOR CENTER ALSO
EXPERIENCE OSCAR'S GREAT ENERGY WHERE HE BROUGHT LAUGHTER,
CREATIVITY AND CONNECTION TO THE PROGRAM WHETHER PERFORMING
MUSIC ON SHORT NOTICE SINGING OR UNEXPECTEDLY SPEAKING LIKE A
PIRATE TO MATCH THE WEEK'S THEME OSCAR HAS A GIFT FOR
BRINGING PEOPLE TOGETHER AND MAKING EVERYONE FEEL
WELCOME. MENTORSHIP AND FRIENDSHIP HAS
BEEN CENTRAL TO OSCAR'S JOURNEY.
HE OFTEN SPEAKS WITH GRATITUDE ABOUT HIS BEST FRIEND
AND MENTOR AND REALLY OUR MUTUAL FRIEND THE LATE SEAN
MCGREW WHOM HE DESCRIBES AS A FATHER FIGURE WHO TAUGHT HIM
THE VALUE OF TRUE FRIENDSHIP AND PROVIDING OUTSTANDING
CUSTOMER SERVICE AND PUBLIC SERVICE.
AS OSCAR LOOKS AHEAD TO RETIREMENT HE IS EXCITED, AS HE
MENTIONED, TO FOCUS ON HIS WELLNESS AND RETURN TO PAINTING
HIS LIFE LONG PASSION. AND SO ON BEHALF OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND THE BOARD SUPERVISOR OSCAR,
WE THANK YOU. WE THANK YOU FOR YOUR LIFETIME
OF SERVICE, YOUR HEART AND YOUR COMMITMENT TO BUILDING OUR
COMMUNITY AND WE'RE SO, SO GRATEFUL FOR YOUR SERVICE
AND YOUR LOVE FOR OUR COMMUNITY .
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK
YOU SUPERVISORS. >> I'M OVERWHELMED.
THANK YOU SO WE LOVE YOU, OSCAR OH, THAT'S RIGHT
. DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR HUANG
HELLO. >> HEY.
SUPERVISOR. >> TODAY I AM PROUD TO
RECOGNIZE TWO INCREDIBLE MEMBERS OF OUR SUNSET COMMUNITY
PAT AND BUFFY MAGUIRE ON ST PATRICK'S DAY AS PAT
AND BEEFIER LONGTIME COMMUNITY LEADERS WHOSE IMPACT ON THE
SUNSET DISTRICT CAN BE FELT IN BOTH BIG AND SMALL WAYS.
AS OWNERS OF JAVA BEACH CAFE THEY HAVE CREATED MORE THAN
JUST A LOCAL BUSINESS. THEY HAVE BUILT SPACES WHERE
NEIGHBORS CONNECT, FAMILIES GATHER AND COMMUNITY HAPPENS
EVERY SINGLE DAY. IN A DISTRICT LIKE THIS SUNSET,
THOSE SPACES ARE ESSENTIAL. THEY'RE PART OF WHAT MAKES OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD FEEL WELCOMING, CONNECTED AND STRONG.
AND IN HONOR OF WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH, I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE
BUFFY MCGUIRE FOR HER LEADERSHIP, HER CONTRIBUTIONS
TO SUNSET DISTRICT AND THE ROLE SHE PLAYS IN STRENGTHENING OUR
COMMUNITY EVERY DAY. AND ON A PERSONAL NOTE, THE
SANDWICH IS THERE ARE SO GOOD THAT WHEN I GRADUATED FROM
LINCOLN HIGH SCHOOL I ASKED MY FAMILY AND MY PARENTS TO GO TO
JAVA BEACH CAFE TO EAT THEIR SANDWICHES WITH ME.
BEYOND PAT AND BUFFY'S WORK AS SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS, THEY
HAVE BEEN DEEPLY INVOLVED IN THE CULTURAL AND CIVIC LIFE
OF OUR CITY. THEY HAVE HELPED UPLIFT
AND CELEBRATE IRISH HERITAGE IN SAN FRANCISCO WHILE ENSURING
THAT THOSE TRADITIONS REMAIN OPEN, INCLUSIVE AND ACCESSIBLE
TO EVERYONE WHO WANTS TO BE A PART OF IT.
THEY HAVE ALSO CONSISTENTLY SHOWN UP FOR THE SUNSET
SUPPORTING LOCAL EVENTS, STRENGTHENING OUR COMMERCIAL
CORRIDORS AND CONTRIBUTING TO THE OVERALL VITALITY OF OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. THEIR WORK REFLECTS THE VALUES
THAT DEFINE DISTRICT FOR WHICH OUR COMMUNITY RESILIENCE AND A
DEEP COMMITMENT TO ONE ANOTHER ON A DAY LIKE TODAY.
ST PATRICK'S DAY IS ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL TO RECOGNIZED
LEADERS WHO NOT ONLY CELEBRATE CULTURE BUT ALSO BRING PEOPLE
TOGETHER ACROSS BACKGROUNDS AND GENERATIONS.
PAT AND BUFFY TRULY REPRESENT THE VERY BEST OF THE SUNSET
DISTRICT AND I'M GRATEFUL FOR THEIR CONTINUED DEDICATION TO
OUR COMMUNITY ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS, IT IS MY HONOR TO PRESENT THIS PROCLAMATION TO
PAT AND DUFFY MCGUIRE IN RECOGNITION OF THEIR
LEADERSHIP SERVICE AND LASTING CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE SUNSET
DISTRICT. HAPPY ST PATRICK'S DAY
AND THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING THAT YOU DO.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG, CAN YOU HEAR
ME? HAPPY ST PATRICK'S DAY,
EVERYBODY. I SEE ALL THE GREEN I JUST KEEP
IT SHORT AND SAY THANK YOU SO MUCH ON BEHALF OF PAT AND I
AND THE ENTIRE MCGUIRE FAMILY THIS HAS BEEN QUITE A ST
PATRICK'S DAY TO REMEMBER FROM THE PARADE AND ALL OF THE
FESTIVITIES AND ALL OF THE TRADITIONS THAT KEEP THIS
CULTURE ALIVE IN THIS BEAUTIFUL CITY.
AND I WANT TO THANK OUR ANCESTORS WHO WERE IMMIGRANTS
WHO CAME HERE AND BUILT A LIFE FOR US.
AND SO I AM THE GRANDDAUGHTER, THE GREAT GRANDDAUGHTER AND THE
DAUGHTER IN LAW OF IRISH IMMIGRANTS WHO CAME TO SAN
FRANCISCO DIRECTLY AND SETTLED ON THE WEST SIDE AND SETTLED
IN THE SUNSET DISTRICT AND MADE A HOME BEFORE IT WAS QUITE AS
SEXY AS IT IS NOW. >> GROWING UP AND GOING TO HIGH
SCHOOL FROM THE SUNSET TO PACIFIC HEIGHTS WAS QUITE A
TREK THROUGH MANY MICROCLIMATES AND THROUGH MANY DIFFERENT
CULTURES SHALL WE SAY. BUT IT'S BEEN A WONDERFUL RIDE
AND WE'RE GRATEFUL TO HAVE THIS OPPORTUNITY TO REPRESENT OUR
COMMUNITY AND A SHOUT OUT TO THE IRISH-AMERICAN COMMUNITY
THAT ALWAYS SHOWS UP FOR US IN GOOD TIMES AND BAD.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH AND HAPPY ST PATRICK'S DAY SO
DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY AS WE WRAP UP RAMADAN THIS YEAR IT IS MY
HONOR TO RECOGNIZE PARKLANE RESTAURANT.
>> THE OWNERS OF PARKMAN COME TO THE PODIUM.
>> WE ARE CELEBRATING PARKLAND FOR OVER TWO DECADES THAT IT
HAS BEEN NOURISHING OUR COMMUNITIES WITH INCREDIBLE
FOOD AS WELL AS PROVIDING SERVICE THAT IS STEEPED
IN GENEROSITY AND HOSPITALITY. BUT ONE STORY BEGINS IN 1999
WHEN TWO BEST FRIENDS KHALID WOMEN AND MOHAMMED SHABAZZ
OPENED THE FIRST LOCATION IN THE TENDERLOIN AT THE CORNER
OF O'FARRELL AND JONES. LIKE SO MANY IMMIGRANTS WHO
ARRIVE IN THIS COUNTRY SEEKING OPPORTUNITY, THEY CAME WITH
DETERMINATION AND FAITH CARRYING WITH THEM THE
TRADITIONS AND FLAVORS THAT REMINDED THEM OF HOME WITH LONG
HOURS, PERSEVERANCE AND A DEEP BELIEF IN THEIR COMMUNITY, THEY
BUILT SOMETHING SPECIAL FROM THE BEGINNING BEGAN FOCUSED ON
SERVING AUTHENTIC HALAL FOOD THAT FELT FAMILIAR TO MANY
SOUTH ASIAN IMMIGRANTS WHILE REMAINING WELCOMING
AND AFFORDABLE TO EVERYONE IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> THE TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY QUICKLY EMBRACED BLACK ONE.
>> FAMILIES GATHERED. THEIR STUDENTS STOPPED IN LATE
NIGHT AFTER STUDYING WORKERS CAME BY AFTER LONG SHIFTS.
>> OVER TIME THE RESTAURANT BECAME MORE THAN A PLACE TO EAT
. IT BECAME A PLACE WHERE
NEIGHBORS CONNECTED AND WHERE MANY PEOPLE FELT A SENSE OF
HOME IN THE MIDDLE OF A BUSY CITY.
>> THANKS TO THAT COMMUNITY SUPPORT, WHAT STARTED AS A
SMALL RESTAURANT HAS GROWN INTO MULTIPLE LOCATIONS ACROSS THE
BAY AREA. AND YET EVEN WITH THAT GROWTH,
BACON HAS REMAINED ROOTED IN THE TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY THE
SAME COMMUNITY THAT FIRST WELCOMED IT.
GIVING BACK HAS ALWAYS BEEN CENTRAL TO ONE STORY.
EACH YEAR DURING THE HOLY MONTH OF RAMADAN, THE RESTAURANT
DONATES MEALS AND RESOURCES TO NONPROFIT PARTNERS ACROSS THE
BAY AREA AT NO COST TO THEM. THROUGH THESE EFFORTS, SPARC
ONE HELPED SERVE MORE THAN 2000 INDIVIDUALS EACH MONTH DURING
RAMADAN, REFLECTING A DEEP COMMITMENT TO FAITH AND CARING
FOR NEIGHBORHOODS. NEIGHBORS IN NEED.
>> IT IS ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL THAT WE RECOGNIZE PAKISTAN ONE
THIS WEEK DURING THIS FINAL DAYS OF RAMADAN FOR MANY IN OUR
MUSLIM COMMUNITY INCLUDING MYSELF.
THIS IS A TIME CENTERED ON REFLECTION AND GENEROSITY.
THOSE VALUES ARE EXACTLY WHAT BHAGWAN HAS PRACTICED YEAR
AFTER YEAR THROUGH ITS SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO.
>> TODAY THE NEXT GENERATION CONTINUES THE LEGACY THAT
HIGHER THAN MUHAMMAD BEGAN. FAMILY MEMBERS INCLUDE ERA
AMEEN, ALI AMIN AND DANIYAL SHABAZZ HAVE ARE HELPING GUIDE
THE RESTAURANT FORWARD AS PART OF THE NEXT GENERATION WHILE
STAYING DEEPLY COMMITTED TO THE SAME PRINCIPLES THAT BUILT THE
RESTAURANT FROM THE BEGINNING. DANIEL IS HERE WITH US TODAY
AND WILL BE ACCEPTING THIS COMMENDATION ON BEHALF OF THE
ENTIRE BLOCK.ONE FAMILY WHOSE HARD WORK IN THE KITCHEN AND IN
THE COMMUNITY HAS MADE THIS RESTAURANT SUCH AN IMPORTANT
PART OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> BUT JUAN REMINDS US THAT A
BELOVED FAMILY OWN RESTAURANT OFTEN SERVES AS THE HEART FOR
OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. >> THEY PERSEVERE.
THEY PRESERVE CULTURE, CELEBRATE TRADITIONS AND CREATE
GATHERING SPACES AND DEMONSTRATE WHAT IT MEANS
TO CARE FOR THE COMMUNITY THAT SUPPORTS THEM.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND THE RESIDENTS OF DISTRICT FIVE, I WANT TO THANK BACK JUAN
FOR THEIR YEARS OF SERVICE GENEROSITY AND THEIR CONTINUED
COMMITMENT TO FEEDING AND SUPPORTING OUR CITY AND FOR
SERVING THE BEST KNOWN IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THANK YOU AND SUPERVISOR CHAN. >> HOLD UP.
THANK YOU. I AM ONLY SPEAKING AND ADDING
THIS TO JUST WANT YOU TO KNOW THAT I HAVE ALWAYS BEEN A FAN
OF POP WINE AND AND THIS IS HOW YOU KNOW THAT IN MY 20 EYES
THAT KILOWATT AND PARK ONE WERE MY GO TO LIKE I ORDER AT PARK
ONE AND THEN I GO TO KILOWATT TO WAIT FOR MY ORDER AND TAKE
IT WHEREVER I GO TO TO HAVE THAT DINNER.
SO YOU HAVE A FAN NOT JUST IN ME BUT I KNOW THAT THERE ARE
MANY MANY SAN FRANCISCANS YOU ARE PART OF THE FABRIC OF WHAT
SAN FRANCISCO IS ABOUT YOUR FOOD AND JUST WHO YOU BEEN TO
THE COMMUNITY YOU MAKE SAN FRANCISCO A BETTER PLACE SO WE
ARE VERY, VERY GRATEFUL TO YOU. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD AND THANK YOU
ALL SUPERVISORS. WE APPRECIATE THE RECOGNITION.
YOU KNOW WE DON'T LIKE TO ADVOCATE FOR OURSELVES.
WE DON'T LIKE TO DISPLAY WHAT WE DO AND IT'S ALL BECAUSE OF
WHAT WE'VE WHAT WE'VE BEEN TAUGHT THE NEWER GENERATION
THAT I'M MOHAMMED SON SO I KNOW MY DAD AND MY UNCLE RIGHT HERE,
CHARLOTTE THEY'VE BEEN THEY WORK MANY YEARS VERY, VERY VERY
TOUGH YEARS BUT THEY WANTED TO GIVE BACK TO THE COMMUNITY THAT
GAVE TO THEM AND THIS IS ONE WAY FOR THEM TO BE RECOGNIZED.
I APPRECIATE THE HONOR THAT'S GIVEN TO THEM FOR THEM TO BE
RECOGNIZED. IT'S MORE OF AN HONOR FOR THEM.
SO WE REALLY APPRECIATE THE SUPPORT OF THE COMMUNITY.
WE HOPE TO BE HERE FOR MANY, MANY YEARS.
FURTHERMORE, OUR NEXT GENERATION TAKE IT OVER BUT WE
REALLY APPRECIATE ALL THE SUPPORT FROM THE COMMUNITY
AND WE LOOK FORWARD TO GIVING BACK AS MUCH AS WE CAN.
>> THANK YOU. HI MY DAD AND MY SELF WE WERE
PARTNERS AND WE WORKED SO HARD .
I CAME TEN YEARS OLD. I NEVER THOUGHT YOU WOULD HAVE
THIS MUCH SUCCESS. WE'RE GOING TO HAVE ONE DAY
THANKS TO SAN FRANCISCO TO GIVE US ALL THE SUPPORT YOU KNOW
WE'RE STILL WORKING ON MAKING CHICKEN TIKKA MASALA
AND BRIYANI TILL YOU GUYS GET TIRED OF IT.
SO THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR ALL THE SUPPORT
AND I'M REALLY GLAD YOU'RE HERE.
>> THANK YOU
. >> DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR
DORSEY THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MANDOLIN.
COLLEAGUES, I TODAY HAVE THE DISTINCT PRIVILEGE OF
RECOGNIZING AND HONORING ALICE ROGERS AND RICK DICKERSON.
>> WOULD YOU PLEASE APPROACH THE PODIUM?
YOU'RE TWO EXCEPTIONAL COMMUNITY LEADERS FROM DISTRICT
SIX WHOSE STEADY LEADERSHIP HAS HELPED TO FOSTER ONGOING
PARTNERSHIP ACCOUNTABILITY AND DIALOG BETWEEN THE
EMBARCADERO COMMUNITY AND THE CITY.
ALICE AND RICK HAVE SERVED IN A VOLUNTEER CAPACITY AS CO-CHAIRS
OF THE EMBARCADERO COMMUNITY ADVISORY COMMITTEE SINCE ITS
CREATION IN 2019. THE COMMITTEE WAS ESTABLISHED
TO HELP PROVIDE COMMUNITY LEADERSHIP AND INPUT AROUND THE
OPENING AND ONGOING OPERATIONS OF THE EMBARCADERO NAVIGATION
CENTER. SINCE THAT TIME ALICE AND RICK
HAVE HELPED TO GUIDE THIS BODY WITH CONSISTENCY, INTEGRITY
AND DEEP CARE FOR THE NEIGHBORHOOD THEY SERVE.
UNDER THEIR LEADERSHIP THE COMMITTEE HAS MET REGULARLY TO
DISCUSS DEVELOPMENTS RELATED TO THE PROGRAM TO ELEVATE
NEIGHBORHOOD CONCERNS AND TO CREATE A FORUM FOR INCLUSIVE
COMMUNICATION AND COLLABORATION AMONG ADVISORY COMMITTEE
MEMBERS, CITY DEPARTMENTS AND SERVICE PROVIDERS AND ALSO
THE BROADER PUBLIC. WHAT MAKES THEIR LEADERSHIP SO
MEANINGFUL IT IS THAT IS THAT IT HAS NEVER BEEN PASSIVE.
ALLISON AND RICK HAVE HELPED BUILD COMMUNITY UNDERSTANDING
AND SUPPORT FOR THE NAVIGATION CENTER WHILE ALSO HOLDING THE
CITY AND THE SITE OPERATOR AT HIRED ACCOUNTABLE TO THE
COMMITMENTS MADE TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
THEY HAVE UNDERSTOOD THAT SUCCESSFUL SHELTER OPERATIONS
REQUIRE NOT JUST VISION BUT TRUST, RESPONSIVENESS
AND SUSTAINED PARTNERSHIP. THEY HAVE HELPED FACILITATE
DIFFICULT CONVERSATIONS WITH THOUGHTFULNESS AND RESOLVE.
THEY HAVE MADE SURE THAT THE VOICES OF RESIDENTS,
STAKEHOLDERS AND NEIGHBORS ARE HEARD.
AND THEY HAVE REMAINED DEEPLY ENGAGED IN SUPPORTING A PROGRAM
THAT PROVIDES CRITICAL SHELTER AND SERVICES TO AS MANY AS 200
VULNERABLE INDIVIDUALS IN NEED EVERY NIGHT.
>> ALICE AND RICK REPRESENT THE VERY BEST OF CIVIC LEADERSHIP.
THEIR KNOWLEDGEABLE, UNFLAPPABLE AND DEEPLY
COMMITTED TO THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD AS WELL AS TO THE LARGER CITY
IT'S A PART OF. THEY ARE ADMIRED FOR ALWAYS
PARTICIPATING WITH CIVILITY AND CLASS EVEN ON OCCASIONS
WHEN THEY HAVE EVERY RIGHT TO BE ANGRY AND OUTRAGED.
AFTER YEARS OF CONSCIENTIOUS SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO, THEY
CONTINUE TO SHOW UP WITH HUMOR ,GRACE AND HEART FOR THE CITY
WE ALL LOVE. ALICE AND RICK.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN MADE INESTIMABLE BETTER FOR YOUR
CONTRIBUTIONS TO CIVIC INVOLVEMENT.
AND I'M PROUD TO RECOGNIZE YOU BOTH TODAY FOR YOUR SERVICE
AND DEDICATION. CONGRATULATIONS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. ARE YOU SURE YOU'RE TALKING
ABOUT THE RIGHT PEOPLE HERE? I.
I'M NOT ONE FOR FOUR SPEECHES. I'M NOT GOING TO BE ANYWHERE
NEAR AS ELOQUENT AS AS MATT WAS.
BUT IT'S BEEN IT'S IT'S BEEN AN HONOR TO BE ABLE TO TO HELP A
WORTHY CAUSE LIKE HOMELESS HOMELESSNESS AND THE HOMELESS
SHELTERS TO BE ABLE TO HAVE HAVE IT IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
AND I THINK THERE ARE A LOT OF PEOPLE IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD WHO
BELIEVED IT WAS IMPORTANT TO TRY AND AND ACCOMMODATE THAT
IN THE SOUTH BEACH INCOME POINT AND MISSION BAY BUT OVERALL
AREA IT WASN'T ALWAYS EASY AND IT DID YOU KNOW WE HIT THE
GRANT RATHER THAN HIT THE GROUND RUNNING IT ALL HIT THE
GROUND WITH COVID SO IT KIND OF MORPHED IT FOR A FEW YEARS BUT
I WILL SAY THAT THAT IT'S BEEN I'VE WORKED WITH A LOT OF
PEOPLE IN CITY STAFF OVER THE YEARS FOR THINGS IN THE SOUTH
BEACH AREA INCLUDING THE GIANTS BALLPARK WHEN IT WAS BUILT.
BUT I WANT TO SHOUT OUT A DO A SHOUT OUT FOR EMILY AND EMILY.
YOU WERE YOU WERE INVOLVED FROM THE VERY BEGINNING.
IT WASN'T ALWAYS EASY TIMES. IT WASN'T ALWAYS JUST GOOD
THINGS THAT WE WERE ALL TALKING ABOUT.
BUT YOU ALWAYS YOU ALWAYS WERE VERY STRAIGHTFORWARD AND I
THINK THAT'S VERY IMPORTANT AND HOW WE WE COME TOGETHER
WITH THE CITY WITH CITY STAFF AND NEIGHBORHOODS IS TO BE
FORTHRIGHT AND TO BE STRAIGHTFORWARD ABOUT THINGS.
AND IF YOU CAN'T DO SOMETHING, SAY IT CAN'T BE DONE AND YOU
KNOW, BE BE WILLING TO CONTINUE TO PLUG AWAY AT IT AND WORK AT
IT AND SHE SHE BROUGHT THAT FROM THE CITY SIDE WITH IT
AND I THINK IT WAS VERY, VERY INSTRUMENTAL IN MAKING ALISON
AND MYSELF BE ABLE TO TO HELP INTEGRATE THIS INTO THE
NEIGHBORHOOD A LITTLE BIT MORE. BUT I'M GOING TO LEAVE IT
DALLAS SHE'S SHE'S A LITTLE BIT MORE ELOQUENT THAN I AM.
THANK YOU, RICK. SUPERVISOR DARCY THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR THIS RECOGNITION AND THANK YOU FOR EMILY
AND DYLAN AND DOMINICA FOR NUDGING THAT ALONG.
>> IT'S QUITE AN HONOR TO BE HERE AFTER FOLLOWING ALL OF
THESE OTHER CITIZENS WHO HAVE JUST BEEN HONORED FOR LIFETIME
ACHIEVEMENT AND SO ON AND SO FORTH AND FEEDING PEOPLE
AND MAKING PEOPLE FEEL WHOLE. IT'S NICE TO SORT OF SLIPSTREAM
AFTER THAT. I, I JUST WANT TO SAY FROM THE
OUTSET I PERSONALLY HAD TWO GOALS FOR THE NAVIGATION CENTER
THAT WOULD BE WELL INTEGRATED INTO THE NEIGHBORHOOD WITH NO
ILL IMPACTS AND ALSO THAT WE ESTABLISHED REALLY A MANAGEMENT
AND OVERSIGHT MODEL SO THAT ALL NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN FRANCISCO
COULD KNOW THAT THEY COULD HAVE SHELTERS IN THEIR NEIGHBORHOODS
TO KNOW ILL EFFECT AND THAT THESE COMMUNITIES COULD BE
UPLIFTED AND BROUGHT BACK TO LIFE.
I HAVE ABOUT 120 SRO NEIGHBORS SO I KNOW THAT THE CONTINUUM
WORKS. >> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
THIS HONOR
TO ALL RIGHT. I WANT TO INVITE JOE SCHUMER TO
COME ON UP. >> I THINK THERE MIGHT BE A
LITTLE TEAM OF GLEN PARKERS THAT MIGHT WANT TO COME STAND
NEXT TO HIM OR BEHIND HIM OR SOMEWHERE WHERE CAN STAY IN THE
AUDIENCE IF THEY WANT TO. >> FOLKS, TODAY IT IS MY GREAT,
GREAT HONOR TO PRESENT A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO THE
VERY, VERY, VERY WONDERFUL JOE SHOVER WHO FOUNDED DESTINATION
BAKING COMPANY AT THE CORNER OF HENRY AND CASTRO A QUARTER
CENTURY AGO AND OPERATED IT THERE UNTIL HE OFFICIALLY LAID
DOWN HIS ROLLING PIN AND RETIRED IN DECEMBER.
>> JOE'S DANISHES COOKIES, CINNAMON ROLLS, CROISSANTS
AND OTHER PASTRIES WERE WILDLY POPULAR AMONG GLEN PARK
NEIGHBORS AND VISITORS. >> HIS BUSINESS WAS ALWAYS A
GREAT AND TASTY SPOT FOR SUPERVISOR OFFICE HOURS.
>> JOE BEGAN EACH DAY IN HIS BAKERY AT 4:30 A.M. BAKING FOR
SEVERAL HOURS BEFORE TAKING A QUICK LUNCH BREAK THEN
RETURNING IN THE AFTERNOON TO CONTINUE WORKING UNTIL 4 OR 5.
DESPITE THE EARLY MORNINGS AND LONG DAYS.
HE NEVER LOST HIS ENTHUSIASM FOR HIS WORK AND EVEN AFTER
DECADES OF EXPERIENCE COMMITTED HIMSELF TO IMPROVING HIS
RECIPES ARE LEARNING NEW ONES EVERY DAY.
JOE GREW UP IN GRANVILLE, A SMALL RURAL TOWN IN THE STATE
OF IOWA. >> HE CAME FROM A HOUSEHOLD OF
BAKERS AND REMEMBERS HELPING HIS MOTHER WITH BAKING WHEN HE
WAS LITTLE. >> AFTER MOVING TO DUBUQUE,
IOWA TO OBTAIN LAURA'S LAURA'S COLLEGE, JOE GOT HIS FIRST
OFFICIAL BAKING JOB AT A NEARBY BAKERY.
AFTER GRADUATING HE TAUGHT HE TAUGHT HIGH SCHOOL ENGLISH FOR
FOUR YEARS, THEN ATTENDED THE UNIVERSITY OF IOWA TO EARN HIS
MASTER'S DEGREE IN LIBRARY SCIENCE IN IOWA CITY.
JOE BEGAN WORKING PART TIME AT A SMALL FRENCH BAKERY WHEN A
FREEZE ON STATE JOBS MADE A CAREER IN LIBRARIES UNCERTAIN.
JOE DECIDED TO FOLLOW HIS PASSION FOR BAKING FULL TIME
ALTHOUGH HE FOUND A DESTINATION BAKING COMPANY 25 YEARS AGO.
HE HAS ACTUALLY BEEN BAKING AT THAT CORNER OF GLEN PARK.
I DID NOT KNOW THIS FOR MORE THAN 38 YEARS INCLUDING 13
YEARS WORKING AT CREIGHTON'S THE BAKERY THAT PREVIOUSLY
OCCUPIED THE SPACE WHEN THE OWNERS OF CREIGHTON'S RETIRED
THEY PASSED THE KEYS TO THE PLACE TO JOE WHO OPENED
DESTINATION BAKING COMPANY THE TUESDAY AFTER LABOR DAY IN 2000
. DESTINATION BAKING COMPANY WAS
A CORNERSTONE OF GLEN PARK FOR SO MANY YEARS SINCE THE
ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE BAKERY'S CLOSING, NEIGHBORS HAVE STOPPED
BY TO EXPRESS THEIR APPRECIATION TO JOE AND SHARE
WHAT WHICH OF THE PASTRIES THEY WILL MISS THE MOST.
I HAVE BEEN MISSING THE BUTTER HORN, THE CHEESE DANISH, THE
CHERRY DANISH A NUMBER OF OTHER ITEMS.
>> IT'S PROBABLY GOOD FOR MY WAISTLINE BUT NOT FOR MY TASTE
BUDS. >> THANK YOU JOE, FOR YOUR
CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND ESPECIALLY TO GLEN PARK. WE THANK YOU AND WISH YOU ALL
THE BEST THINGS IN YOUR WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT.
>> THANK YOU. AND THE FLOOR, SIR, IS YOURS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. PRESIDENT MANDELBAUM AND THE
WHOLE BOARD. I'D LIKE TO THANK YOU FOR THIS
COMMENDATION. IT'S BEEN SUCH A GREAT HONOR TO
SERVE A COMMUNITY OF GLEN PARK AND ALL THESE YEARS 25 YEARS
AND I'VE BEEN VERY LUCKY TO HAVE A FEW LOYAL CUSTOMERS
EXCUSE ME EMPLOYEES WHO SAW ME THROUGH FOR MANY, MANY YEARS
AND STUCK BY ME EVEN WHEN THINGS GOT ROUGH I.E. COVID
AND ETC. AND I'VE BEEN VERY BLESSED TO HAVE SOME OF THEM
ARE HERE TODAY. THE BEST GROUP OF FELLOW
MERCHANTS IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD, GLEN PARK IS VERY TIGHT
AND WE'VE ALL WE ALL HAVE EACH OTHER'S BACK AND I'M VERY
APPRECIATIVE OF THAT. >> OUR CUSTOMERS SUPPORTED US
FOR MANY, MANY YEARS. A LOT OF THEM BECAME FRIENDS
AND SOMETIMES EXTENDED FAMILY AND I MISS THEM ALL VERY MUCH.
BUT I GREW UP, AS YOU SAID, IN A VERY SMALL TOWN AND IT
REALLY FELT LIKE A LIKE A SMALL TOWN COMMUNITY OVER THERE.
AND I'D LIKE TO THANK MY HUSBAND OF MANY, MANY YEARS WHO
SUPPORTED ME THROUGH ALL OF THIS AND WAS VERY PATIENT
THROUGH THE GOOD TIMES AND THE BAD TIMES AND I WOULDN'T BE
STANDING HERE WITHOUT HIM. >> AND MY HOPE FOR THE FUTURE
IS THAT ALL THESE EMPTY STOREFRONTS ETC. THE CITY IS
LITTERED WITH WILL BE FILLED UP WITH INTERESTING AND VIBRANT
AND COLORFUL SMALL BUSINESSES THAT MAKE SAN FRANCISCO WHAT
SAN FRANCISCO IS. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
EVERYTHING. IT'S SIMPLE.
WHAT DO YOU WANT TO COME UP? GUESS.
OKAY. GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. SO MADAM CLERK, I THINK THAT
TAKES US TO OUR FIRST 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
>> YES, MR. PRESIDENT. THAT WOULD BE ITEMS.
ITEM 13 AND 14. >> YES, PLEASE CALL THEM.
OKAY, SO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AGREED TO CONVENE
AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE PURSUANT TO A RESOLUTION NUMBER
045 DASH 26 CONTAINED IN FILE NUMBER 251218 APPROVED ON
FEBRUARY 13TH 2026 FOR A PUBLIC HEARING OF THE BOARD TO CONVENE
AS A COMMITTEE AS I STATED FOR A PUBLIC HEARING TO ORDER THE
CONDITIONAL VACATION OF THE DESIGNATION OF PORTIONS OF
CHRISTMAS TREE POINT ROAD AND EASTERN ALIGNMENT OF TWIN
PEAKS BOULEVARD AS A PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY FOR ROADWAY
AND SIDEWALK PURPOSES AND TO ORDER THE READ DESIGNATION OF
EASTERN TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD AS A PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY FOR
RECREATION AND PARK PURPOSES TO APPROVE THE INTERDEPARTMENTAL
TRANSFER OF EASTERN TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD INTO AND ASSESSOR'S
PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER 2643 LOT NUMBER ZERO 14 FROM PUBLIC
WORKS TO THE RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT.
TO APPLY THE PARK CODE AND REGULATIONS AND THE
EXCAVATION AND BACKFILL REQUIREMENTS OF THE PUBLIC
WORKS CODE AND ASSOCIATED ORDERS REGULATIONS, STANDARDS
AND PROCEDURES TO EASTERN TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD TO ENABLE THE
RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT TO ISSUE EXCAVATION PERMITS FOR
EASTERN TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD. TO CLARIFY THAT THE CITY HAS
APPROVED A GRANT RESTRICTION REQUIRING THAT THE TWIN PEAKS
PROMENADE BE OPERATED AS A PUBLIC OPEN SPACE IN PERPETUITY
. >> TO ALL OF THAT TO FACILITATE
THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE PROJECT TO
AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
SO COLLEAGUES, WE ARE NOW SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE TO CONSIDER THE STREET VACATION FOR THE TWIN PEAKS
PROMENADE PROJECT AND I BELIEVE WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM REC
THE REC PARK DEPARTMENT NOW PLEASE TAKE IT AWAY.
>> THANK YOU AND THANK YOU. CLERK OF THE BOARD AND IF I CAN
GET THE OVERHEAD PLEASE FOR THE POWERPOINT AND SO TV PLEASE.
>> THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON, BOARD MEMBERS.
MY NAME IS CHRIS TOWNS. I'M A PLANNER WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT AND I WILL BE
PRESENTING THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE STREET VACATION
AND INTER-DEPARTMENTAL PROPERTY TRANSFER ITEM BEFORE YOU TODAY
I'LL PREFACE BY MENTIONING THAT THE STREET VACATION ITEM BEFORE
YOU IS ASSOCIATED WITH THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE PROJECT
AND BROADER SITE IMPROVEMENTS WHOSE VARIOUS GRANT ACCEPTANCES
WERE PREVIOUSLY APPROVED BY THE BOARD TOTALING ABOUT $4.25
MILLION. THEREFORE THE BOARDS APPROVAL
OF THIS ITEM WOULD BE A CONTINUUM OF PAST RELATED
APPROVALS AND ALLOW THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE PROJECT TO
PROCEED INTO CONSTRUCTION AND WITH ALREADY APPROVED GRANT
FUNDING. >> SO WITH THAT I'LL I'LL OPEN
WITH THE TWIN PEAKS OPEN SPACE OVERVIEW TWIN PEAKS ITSELF IS A
31 ACRE REC AND PARK DEPARTMENT OPEN SPACE IN THE TWIN PEAKS
NEIGHBORHOOD FEATURING TWO DISTINCT PEAKS SURROUNDED BY
GRASSY HILLSIDE EXPANSES. TWIN PEAKS IS ONE OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO'S MOST ICONIC OPEN SPACES.
>> ITS UNIQUE GEOGRAPHIC FEATURE IS LOCATED, YOU KNOW,
DISTINCT BUT TWO DISTINCT PEAKS LOCATED IN THE CENTER OF THE
CITY IS AN INTERNATIONALLY RECOGNIZED OPEN SPACE
AND OFFERS PANORAMIC VIEWS OF THE CITY AND BROADER BAY AREA.
TWIN PEAKS IS ALSO A NATURAL AREA PER REC PARKS NATURAL
RESOURCE MANAGEMENT PLAN DUE TO ITS IMPORTANCE AS A NATURAL
HILLSIDE HABITAT FOR PLANTS AND ANIMALS FOR A BRIEF
OVERVIEW OF THE VARIOUS PHASES OF WORK THAT HAVE ALREADY TAKEN
PLACE AT TWIN PEAKS OVER THE PAST NEARLY DECADE, I'D LIKE TO
HIGHLIGHT THAT FROM 2013 TO 2014 A NEW MULTI-USE TRAIL
ADJACENT TO THE SOUTHERN TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD WAS ESTABLISHED
. IN 2015 THERE WAS THE ADDITION
OF THREE CROSSWALKS TOWARDS THE NORTH, MIDDLE AND SOUTHERN END
OF TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD. AND FROM 2016 TO 2020 WAS WHEN
THE FIGURE EIGHT REDESIGN PLANNING STUDY WAS CONDUCTED BY
SFM TO THIS WAS A FOUR YEAR PILOT PROJECT STUDY TO STUDY
VEHICULAR ROAD CLOSURE TO ALLOW PEDESTRIAN AND BICYCLIST USE OF
THE EASTERN HALF OF TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD RESULTING
IN PERMANENT CLOSURE OF THE ROADWAY TO VEHICULAR TRAFFIC
IN 2020. IN 2017 THE TWIN PEAKS TRAIL
IMPROVEMENT PROJECT PHASE ONE FOR TWO TRAIL SEGMENTS WAS
COMPLETED IN 2025. PHASE TWO FOR THREE ADDITIONAL
TRAIL SEGMENTS WAS COMPLETED AND AT THIS TIME REC PARK IS
PURSUING THE STREET VACATION TO FACILITATE THE TWIN PEAKS
PROMENADE PROJECT WHICH WOULD IMPLEMENT COMPREHENSIVE SURFACE
IMPROVEMENTS TO TRANSFORM THE DECOMMISSIONED ROADWAY INTO A
LINEAR PARK OR PROMENADE. WITH CONSTRUCTION SLATED TO
BEGIN IN SUMMER OF 2026 AND OPEN TO THE PUBLIC IN EARLY
2027, THE REQUEST IS FREE VACATION AS DEPICTED IN DARK
GREEN ON THE MAP OCCUPIES THE EASTERN HALF OF THE FIGURE
EIGHT ROADWAY ATOP TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD AND WITH WOULD
FACILITATE THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE
PROJECT SINCE IT CORRESPONDS TO THE PROJECT FOOTPRINT THE
REQUESTED STREET VACATION IS ESSENTIALLY THE LEGISLATIVE
MEANS BY WHICH THE EXISTING DECOMMISSIONED ROADWAY PUBLIC
RIGHT OF WAY UNDER PUBLIC WORKS JURISDICTION WOULD BE
JURISDICTIONALLY TRANSFERRED FROM PUBLIC WORKS TO REC PARK
ALLOWING THE CONDITIONAL VACATION IN WHICH THE ROADWAY
WOULD CHANGE FROM A PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY FOR ROADWAY
AND SIDEWALK PURPOSES TO A ROADWAY A PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY
RATHER FOR RECREATION AND PARK PURPOSES.
THIS WOULD ALLOW REC PARK TO MANAGE AND MAINTAIN THE
PROMENADE AS A RECREATIONAL OPEN SPACE WHILE RETAINING A
PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY DESIGNATION THAT WOULD ACCOMMODATE AN
EXISTING UTILITY FRANCHISE AGREEMENT.
THE STREET VACATION IS A REQUIRED PREMISE FOR THE
PROMENADE PROJECT SINCE ITS PERMISSION FOR RECREATIONAL USE
UNDER REC PARK JURISDICTION IS NEEDED IN ORDER TO HOST THE
NEEDED ESTABLISHMENT IN ORDER TO COMMENCE CONSTRUCTION A
SUPPLEMENTAL ASPECT OF THE LEGISLATION INCLUDES THE
INTER-DEPARTMENTAL TRANSFER OF BLOCK 2643014 FROM PUBLIC WORKS
TO REC PARK AS DEPICTED ON THE JURISDICTIONAL MAP ON THE RIGHT
THE LOT HIGHLIGHTED IN YELLOW PARALLELS THE STREET VACATION
PROJECT AREA ALONG THE EASTERN HILLSIDE AND IS SURROUNDED BY A
CLUSTER OF ALREADY RTD OWNED PROPERTIES.
THE BENEFITS OF THIS TRANSFER INCLUDE CONSOLIDATE AND HAVE
CLUSTERED LOTS ALREADY UNDER RTD JURISDICTION THEREBY
SIMPLIFYING OUR JURISDICTIONAL BOUNDARY MAINTENANCE
EFFICIENCIES AND INCREASES THE AMOUNT OF PROPERTY PRESERVE
PUBLIC OPEN SPACE TO HELP ENSURE ITS NATURAL VALUE IS
PROTECTED. THE REC PARK COMMISSION
PREVIOUSLY RECOMMENDED THAT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS APPROVE
THE INTER-DEPARTMENTAL TRANSFER OF THE PROMENADE AS WELL AS THE
LOT 14 SO THE BOARD'S APPROVAL OF THIS ACTION WOULD BRING
CLOSURE TO THIS TRANSACTION. AND LASTLY THE TRANSFER IS
SUPPORTED BY PUBLIC WORKS AS INDICATED IN THE PUBLIC WORKS
ORDER AS PART OF YOUR PACKET FOR SHARED VISUAL REFERENCE I
JUST WANT TO CLOSE WITH SOME IMAGES OF THE PROMENADE PROJECT
THAT THE STREET VACATION WOULD FACILITATE.
AS YOU CAN SEE THE PROMENADE PLAN IS RELATIVELY SIMPLE IT'S
COMPOSED OF A SORT OF CENTRAL ASPHALT PATHWAY WITH AGGREGATE
PATHWAY ALONG THE HILLSIDE EDGE FLANKED BY NATIVE LANDSCAPING
ON BOTH SIDES. AND THAT CONCLUDES MY
PRESENTATION STOP ISABELLE FOR ANY QUESTIONS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR THE PRESENTATION.
I DO NOT SEE ANY QUESTIONS. SO MADAM CLERK LET'S CALL FOR
PUBLIC COMMENT ON THIS MATTER AT THIS TIME IF YOU ARE HERE
IN THE CHAMBER AND YOU WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE YOUR PUBLIC
COMMENTS SPECIFIC TO THIS PUBLIC HEARING FOR THE STREET
VACATION ORDER FOR THE INTERDEPARTMENTAL PROPERTY
TRANSFER FOR THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE PROJECT ITEM 13
AND 14 NOW IS YOUR CHANCE. STEP OVER TO THE RIGHT HAND
SIDE OF THE CHAMBER AND USE THE PUBLIC PODIUM.
WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
SENIOR SPEAKERS PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
AND SEEING NO OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER.
THIS MATTER HAS BEEN HEARD AND IS NOW FILED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 14.
>> SO ITEM 14 WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE
LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE.
IT WAS A PART OF THE CALL THAT I JUST MADE PURSUANT TO ITEMS
13 AND 14 FOR THE STREET VACATION ORDER.
MR. PRESIDENT. >> GOT IT.
CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 14.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
ALL RIGHT. MANDEL MAN EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR
WONG AI WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING. MADAM CLERK LET'S CALL OUR NEXT
3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 15.
>> YES THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WAS IS CONVENING A COMMITTEE OF
THE WHOLE CALLING A MATTER FROM THE RULES COMMITTEE TO A
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE. PURSUANT TO A MOTION M 20 6-023
CONTAINED IN FILE NUMBER 26 02254 ITEM 15 THIS IS A PUBLIC
HEARING TO DISCUSS THE FINDINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE
PROPOSITION E COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK FORCE'S FINAL
REPORT AND THE DRAFT CHARTER AMENDMENT ENTITLED BOARDS,
COMMISSIONS AND ADVISORY BODIES WHICH PROPOSES TO IMPLEMENT THE
TASK FORCE'S RECOMMENDATIONS PURSUANT TO CHARTER SECTION
FOUR POINT 100.1 SUB E AND TO REQUEST THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR
HIS OFFICE TO REPORT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
TODAY WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM CITY STAFF AND PROPERTY TASK
FORCE MEMBERS ON THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE
COMMISSION'S STREAMLINING TASK FORCE.
PROPOSITION E WHICH WAS APPROVED BY SAN FRANCISCO
VOTERS IN NOVEMBER 2024, ESTABLISHED THE TASK FORCE
AND CHARGED IT WITH REVIEWING AND RECOMMENDING POTENTIAL
CHANGES TO THE CITY'S MORE THAN 150 BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS ON
PROPERTY. PROVIDED THAT TASK FORCE
MEMBERS WOULD BE APPOINTED BY THE MAYOR, THE PRESIDENT OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. HELLO, MR. HARRINGTON.
THANK YOU FOR BEING OUR FIRST SUPERVISOR PRESIDENT PELICANS
AND THEN MY APPOINTMENT THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR, THE CITY
ATTORNEY AND THE COMPTROLLER. THE TASK FORCE'S MANDATE WAS TO
IDENTIFY OPPORTUNITIES TO MODIFY CONSOLIDATE OR ELIMINATE
PUBLIC BODIES TO IMPROVE THE ADMINISTRATION OF CITY
GOVERNMENT WHILE PRESERVING MEANINGFUL OPPORTUNITIES FOR
PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT. OVER THE COURSE OF 2025 THE
TASK FORCE WITH EXTENSIVE SUPPORT FROM STAFF IN THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE CONDUCTED A DETAILED REVIEW OF
EACH PUBLIC BODY ONE BY ONE. TO DATE THEY'VE HELD 23 PUBLIC
MEETINGS AND CONSIDERED MORE THAN 1200 PIECES OF WRITTEN
AND VERBAL COMMENT. THE WORK PRODUCT OF THE TASK
FORCE HAS BEEN A REPORT AN EXTENSIVE REPORT WHICH IS
AVAILABLE FOR ALL OF US TO REVIEW AND TWO PIECES OF
LEGISLATION ALSO AVAILABLE FOR ALL OF ALL OF US TO REVIEW.
>> THE FIRST IS AN ORDINANCE THAT REFLECTS THE TASK FORCES
RECOMMENDED CHANGES TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE.
THAT ORDINANCE WAS INTRODUCED ON MARCH 30TH ON MARCH 3RD
AND IS CURRENTLY BEING HELD UNDER THE 30 DAY RULE.
THE RECOMMENDATION THAT THAT ORDINANCE WILL TAKE EFFECT
AFTER 90 DAYS UNLESS REJECTED BY A SUPERMAJORITY OF THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS. >> AND JUST TO BE CLEAR, THERE
IS NO ACTION BEING TAKEN ON THAT ORDINANCE TODAY.
THE SECOND PIECE OF LEGISLATION IS A PROPOSED CHARTER AMENDMENT
. >> NOW THAT CHARTER AMENDMENT
EXISTS IT IS UNDER WAY ON WEBSITES AS I SAID OR IT IS ON
AT LEAST A WEBSITE. IT IS AVAILABLE FOR REVIEW
AND CONSIDERATION BY THIS BODY AND THE PUBLIC.
>> AND I HOPE THAT THE CHAIR WILL NOT TAKE OFFENSE AND THAT
THE MEMBERS OF THE TASK FORCE WILL NOT TAKE OFFENSE IF I SAY
FROM THE OUTSET THAT IT IS HIGHLY UNLIKELY THAT THIS THAT
I OR ANY OTHER MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WILL
INTRODUCE THAT PARTICULAR CHARTER AMENDMENT OR THAT THIS
BOARD WOULD SEND THAT THAT PARTICULAR CHARTER AMENDMENT ON
TO THE VOTERS IN NOVEMBER. NOW THAT THAT'S A LIKE THAT
MEMBER'S CLERK DOES NOT WANT YOU CLAPPING IT'S AGAINST OUR
RULES. >> NOW I HAVE ASKED THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE TO BEGIN WORKING WITH US ON DRAFTING A
CHARTER AMENDMENT TO IMPLEMENT SOME OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS
AND THERE ARE IN THAT REPORT AND IN THAT CHARTER AMENDMENT A
HOST OF RECOMMENDATIONS THAT ARE NON-CONTROVERSIAL.
I THINK THAT ALTHOUGH YOU NEVER KNOW IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT BUT I
THINK THERE IS CONSENSUS SUPPORT FOR A WHOLE BUNCH OF
THE WORK THAT WAS PROPOSED. >> I THINK YOU KNOW WHAT IS
GOING TO BE INTERESTING OVER THE BASICALLY THE NEXT SIX
WEEKS THAT WE HAVE TO THINK ABOUT INTRODUCING SOMETHING
BEFORE OUR MAY DEADLINE IS YOU KNOW WHICH OF THE THINGS THAT
THERE MAY BE A DIVERSITY OF PERSPECTIVE ON IN WHICH OF
THOSE CASES IS THE JUICE WORTH THE SQUEEZE?
>> I HAVE HEARD A LOT AND MY COLLEAGUES HAVE HEARD A LOT
ABOUT A NUMBER OF COMMISSIONS OF LONG STANDING THAT HAVE BEEN
IN OUR CHARTER FOR A VERY LONG TIME AND WHOSE EXISTENCE IN OUR
CHARTER OR IN THE VIEW OF A LOT OF FOLKS IS IMPORTANT AS AN
EXPRESSION OF OUR VALUES AND OUR COMMITMENT TO THOSE
PARTICULAR THINGS. I BELIEVE THAT THAT WAS A
POSITION THAT MAY HAVE BEEN TAKEN BY THE CHAIR OF THE TASK
FORCE THE TASK FORCE. AGAIN, I WANT TO THANK ALL OF
THE MEMBERS AND I THINK THEY'RE CHARGED WITH TO SORT OF THINK
THROUGH WHAT WAS THE MOST IN THEIR VIEW REASONABLE,
RATIONAL OR IT WAS SORT OF THE DR. SPOCK ZATION OF OUR
CHARTER. >> BUT THAT'S NOT WHAT POLITICS
IS. THAT'S NOT WHAT WE'RE GOING TO
DO IN THIS CHAMBER AND IT'S NOT WHAT THE VOTERS ARE GOING TO BE
ASKED TO DO IN NOVEMBER. >> SO WE DO WANT TO HEAR ABOUT
THE WORK YOU'VE DONE. WE DO WANT TO HEAR THE REASONS
FOR THE RECOMMENDATIONS THAT YOU MADE.
BUT I AS I SAID, I THINK THIS BOARD IS VERY LIKELY TO DEPART
FROM THE TASK FORCE RECOMMENDATIONS IN A NUMBER OF
AREAS. >> BEFORE I BEGIN BEFORE WE
BEGIN I'VE BEEN GOING ON FOR A WHILE.
I APOLOGIZE. >> BUT BEFORE WE BEGIN, I DO
WANT TO THANK CITY ADMINISTRATOR CHU AND YOUR
STAFF ESPECIALLY RACHEL ALONZO FOR ALL THE WORK THAT HAS GONE
INTO THIS LONG PROCESS OF IMPLEMENTING PROP.
IT HAS BEEN A LOT OF WORK. I DO WANT TO THANK THE MEMBERS
OF THE TASK FORCE THE CHAIR AT HARRINGTON, ANDREA BURRUS,
SOPHIE HAYWARD. >> NATASHA MITCHELL AND SOPHIE
AND SOPHIA KETTLER. I WOULD BE REMISS IF I DID NOT
THANK MELANIE MATHESON IN MY OFFICE WHO HAS BEEN FOLLOWING
THIS CLOSELY AND TRYING TO MAKE SENSE OF ALL THE VARIOUS
DEBATES AROUND ALL THE VARIOUS ISSUES THAT HAVE BEEN TOUCHED
ON BY THE TASK FORCE'S WORK. AND OF COURSE I WANT TO THANK
THE MANY MEMBERS THE PUBLIC COMMISSIONERS AND ADVOCATES WHO
ATTENDED PUBLIC MEETINGS, GAVE PUBLIC COMMENT, SAT DOWN WITH
ME OR MY STAFF TO DISCUSS SPECIFIC ASPECTS OF THE PROCESS
OR ATTEND OR HAVE SHOWN UP TODAY.
WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM CHAIR HARRINGTON.
I THINK WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM CITY ADMINISTRATOR CHU OR
MAYBE NOT. MAYBE NOT SHAKING THE HEAD.
>> OKAY. WE'RE IN HERE FROM CITY
ADMINISTRATOR SORRY FROM CHAIR HARRINGTON AND THEN I THINK
WE'RE GONNA HEAR FROM RACHEL ALONZO AND THAT MIGHT BE IT.
BUT I CAN BE CORRECTED AND AND THEN THERE WILL BE AN
OPPORTUNITY IF SUPERVISORS WANT TO SAY THINGS OR ASK QUESTIONS
WE CAN DO THAT AND THEN WE'LL BE THE OPPORTUNITY FOR A LOT OF
FOLKS WHO CARE ABOUT A LOT OF DIFFERENT THINGS THAT HAVE BEEN
TOUCHED ON BY THIS TASK FORCE TO MAKE THEIR VOICES HEARD HERE
IN THE CHAMBER. >> SO WITH THAT WE WILL START
WITH CHAIR HARRINGTON AND THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU FOR ORGANIZING THIS TODAY AND WELCOMING
AND WELCOMING US TO THE ROOM AND WE TAKE NO OFFENSE.
WE WERE THERE TO SERVE. WE ARE GIVING YOU PRODUCTS THAT
YOU HAVE AN OPTION TO DEAL WITH THE WAY YOU CHOOSE TO.
YOU'VE MADE MANY OF THE COMMENTS I WAS GOING TO MAKE
INTRODUCING THE FOLKS AND I APPRECIATE THAT.
I DO WANT TO ADD THANKS TO THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR AND THE CITY
COMPTROLLER FOR PROVIDING OUR STAFF BECAUSE WITHOUT THAT THE
JOB WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN DONE. AND IN A MOMENT I WILL BE
INTRODUCING RACHEL ALONZO WHO IS OUR PROJECT DIRECTOR
AND SHE'LL BE WALKING YOU THROUGH A VERY BRIEF KIND OF
SUMMARY OF WHAT WAS GOING ON AND WHAT HAPPENED WITH THE
ORGANIZATIONAL PROCESS. >> JUST A COUPLE QUICK COMMENTS
BEFORE THAT. QUESTIONS THAT HAVE COME UP AS
WE'VE GONE AROUND AND TALKED TO PEOPLE.
THE FIRST QUESTION I THINK IS DID WE EXCEED OUR MANDATE?
PROPOSITION E SAID WE SHOULD BE CONVENED TO ADVISE THE
MAYOR AND THE BOARD ON WAY ON QUOTE WAYS TO ELIMINATE,
CONSOLIDATE OR LIMIT THE POWER AND DUTIES OF APPOINTED BOARDS
AND COMMISSIONS FOR THE MORE EFFECTIVE, EFFICIENT
AND ECONOMICAL ADMINISTRATION OF CITY AND COUNTY GOVERNMENT
UNQUOTE. I BELIEVE WE STAYED WITHIN THAT
MANDATE BUT I ALSO CONCEDE THAT WHAT THE TASK FORCE DID WENT
MUCH FURTHER THAN MANY OF THE ADVOCATES FOR PROPERTY HAD EVER
ENVISIONED. AND SO I DO UNDERSTAND THE
DISCONNECT THAT'S THERE. BUT THAT IS WHY OUR WORK IS
BEING GIVEN TO YOU TO CHOOSE TO DO WITH WHAT YOU AS YOU GO THE
OTHER QUESTION IS DO WE ENGAGE ENOUGH AND IS THERE EVER ENOUGH
IN SAN FRANCISCO? WE DID HEAR FROM OVER 1000
PEOPLE. >> OUR STAFF SPENT MULTIPLE
MULTIPLE HOURS TALKING TO STAFF AND ADVOCATES AS WE WENT
THROUGH THIS PROCESS. AND I ALSO REALIZE THAT
SOMETIMES LISTENING TO IS NOT THE EQUIVALENT OF AGREEING WITH
AND PEOPLE MAY NOT HAVE FELT LISTENED TO IF WE DIDN'T AGREE
WITH THEM. BUT WE TRIED.
WE MADE A NUMBER OF CHANGES TO WHAT'S THERE AND IT IS BEFORE
YOU IN THE NEXT FEW MONTHS TO DEAL WITH AS YOU WANT TO.
AND WITH THAT I WILL TURN IT OVER TO RACHEL TO BE GIVING YOU
THAT BRIEF PRESENTATION AND THEN WE ARE ALL HERE FOR
ANY QUESTIONS OR COMMENTS YOU MIGHT HAVE.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS RACHEL ALONSO.
I'M A PROJECT DIRECTOR IN THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE.
>> AS OTHERS HAVE MENTIONED, I'M HERE TO PROVIDE AN OVERVIEW
OF THE COMMISSION'S STREAMLINING TASK FORCE AND ITS
RECOMMENDATIONS WHICH ARE BASED ON OVER A YEAR OF WORK
AND INFORMED BY EXTENSIVE PUBLIC INPUT.
THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO AGREE AND DISAGREE WITH THE
RECOMMENDATIONS AND I IMAGINE MANY OF YOU HAVE HEARD FROM
CONSTITUENTS WITH SUGGESTED IMPROVEMENTS.
>> SO MY GOAL TODAY IS TO EXPLAIN THE PROCESS
AND RATIONALE FOR RECOMMENDATIONS SO WE CAN HAND
IT OFF TO YOU TO DECIDE WHAT SHOULD MOVE FORWARD.
AND AGAIN, NO OFFENSE TAKEN IF YOU WANT TO MAKE CHANGES.
I HAVE BEEN EXPECTING THAT THE WHOLE TIME.
>> NEXT SLIDE PLEASE. LIAM THANK YOU SO.
TODAY'S PRESENTATION WILL COVER FOUR AREAS.
I'M GOING TO TRY TO KEEP IT QUICK.
NEXT SLIDE. QUICK ORIENTATION.
NEXT SLIDE. SO VOTERS PASSED PROP E
IN NOVEMBER 2024 WHICH CREATED A COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK
FORCE AND GAVE IT A VERY CLEAR THREE FOLD MANDATE PER THE
BOLDED GREEN TEXT ON THE TOP OF THE SLIDE.
>> SO THE FIRST THING IS TO FOCUS ON CHANGING PUBLIC
MEETING BODIES WHICH CAN INCLUDE THE ELIMINATION
AND MERGER OF BODIES OR CHANGES TO THEIR POWERS AND DUTIES.
>> THE SECOND PART OF THE MANDATE IS ABOUT THAT ANY
CHANGES SHOULD BE FOR THE GOAL TO MEET THE GOAL OF IMPROVING
THE ADMINISTRATION OF CITY GOVERNMENT.
>> AND THEN THIRD, THE MAYOR AND THE BOARD HAVE THE
FINAL SAY. >> THE TASK FORCE MADE
RECOMMENDATIONS TO THE MAYOR AND THE BOARD.
IT IS NOW UP TO YOU. TODAY IS THE HANDOFF.
SO BECAUSE OF THE MANDATE RECOMMENDATIONS ARE ONLY ABOUT
PUBLIC MEETING BODIES. I DO WANT TO NOTE THAT UP FRONT
WE INTENTIONALLY MADE SURE NOT TO TOUCH ANYTHING SPECIFIC TO
DEPARTMENT S ALTHOUGH IN SOME CASES IT IS HARD TO DELINEATE
BETWEEN THE TWO. >> BUT THE TASK FORCE WAS VERY
CAUTIOUS ABOUT THAT. >> THEN AT THE BOTTOM OF THE
SLIDE WE JUST HAVE INFORMATION ABOUT THE FIVE TASK FORCE
MEMBERS AND THEY WERE SUPPORTED BY STAFF FROM THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR AND COMPTROLLERS OFFICES.
>> NEXT SLIDE PLEASE. >> SO PROP EIGHT ITSELF SET OUT
A SERIES OF DEADLINES. AND THE FIRST WAS TO CONVENE
IN JANUARY 2025. >> AND I KNOW THAT A YEAR MAY
SOUND LIKE A LOT OF TIME BUT IT WAS ACTUALLY A REALLY FAST
PACED PROJECT OVER THE LAST MONTH OR SO.
>> WE SUBMITTED OUR FINAL REPORT AND NEARLY 500 PIECES OF
LEGISLATION TO THE CLERK OF THE BOARD'S OFFICE.
>> TODAY'S MEETING FULFILLS THE MANDATE OF PROP TO HAVE A
HEARING ABOUT THE TASK FORCE'S REPORT RECOMMENDATIONS
AND CHARTER AMENDMENT. AND I'LL COME BACK AT THE END
OF THIS PRESENTATION TO TALK ABOUT NEXT STEPS FOR EACH PIECE
OF LEGISLATION. BUT AGAIN NO DECISIONS ARE
BEING MADE TODAY. THIS IS JUST INFORMATIONAL
AND DISCUSSION. >> NEXT SLIDE.
SO THIS ONE PROVIDES A QUICK ORIENTATION TO THE UNIVERSE OF
THE 152 PUBLIC MEETING BODIES UNDER DISCUSSION TODAY.
>> SOME OF THOSE BODIES ARE IN THE CHARTER BUT MOST ARE
IN CODE. AND SOME ARE DECISION MAKING OR
OVERSEE DEPARTMENTS BUT MOST ARE ADVISORY AND REGARDLESS OF
THEIR ROLE OR THE ESTABLISHING AUTHORITY, WE KNOW THAT PUBLIC
BODIES CAN HELP OUR GOVERNMENT STAY TRANSPARENT
AND ACCOUNTABLE. >> HOWEVER MANY OF THEM HAVE
EXISTED FOR DECADES WITHOUT MEANINGFUL EVALUATION AND MAY
BE DUPLICATIVE OR HAVE OUTLIVED THEIR USEFUL PURPOSE.
>> MEANWHILE, DIFFERENT CHARACTERISTICS OF THE BODIES
MAKE THE COMMISSION SYSTEM AS A WHOLE CONFUSING AND DIFFICULT
TO ENGAGE WITH. BEST PRACTICES HAVE BEEN HAVE
BEEN APPLIED INCONSISTENTLY. >> NEXT SLIDE.
SO NOW WE'LL REVIEW THE TASK FORCE'S PRIMARY GOALS AND THE
PUBLIC PROCESS THAT LED US HERE TODAY.
>> NEXT SLIDE. >> SO AGAIN PROPERLY CHARGED
THE TASK FORCE OF MAKING RECOMMENDATIONS IS ABOUT
CHANGING ELIMINATING OR COMBINING PUBLIC BODIES TO
IMPROVE THE ADMINISTRATION OF CITY GOVERNMENT.
>> NOW THIS WORK WAS GUIDED BY FOUR KEY PRINCIPLES FOR THE
TASK FORCE. SO FIRST WAS ABOUT INCREASING
ACCOUNTABILITY AND THAT MEANS CLARIFYING WHO'S RESPONSIBLE
FOR KEY CITY DECISIONS SO THAT SAN FRANCISCANS CAN MORE EASILY
HOLD THEIR ELECTED OFFICIALS ACCOUNTABLE.
THE SECOND KEY PRINCIPLE IS ABOUT CREATING GREATER
CONSISTENCY IN THE COMMISSION SYSTEM SO THAT IT'S MORE
ACCESSIBLE AND UNDERSTANDABLE TO THE PUBLIC.
AND A ONE SIZE FITS ALL APPROACH IS DEFINITELY NOT
APPROPRIATE. >> BUT WE DID FEEL THAT THERE
WAS ROOM FOR ALIGNMENT AND SIMPLIFICATION.
>> THIRD KEY PRINCIPLE IS RESPONSIBLE STEWARDSHIP OF
TAXPAYER DOLLARS. IN ONE FISCAL YEAR ALONE CITY
STAFF SUPPORTED OVER 1500 COMMISSION MEETINGS OFTEN
REPEATING THE SAME PRESENTATIONS ACROSS
OVERLAPPING BODIES. >> BY CONSOLIDATING WHERE
APPROPRIATE WE CAN REDUCE DUPLICATION AND FOCUS STAFF
TIME WHERE IT MATTERS MOST. AND THEN LAST BUT NOT LEAST IS
ELEVATING AND COORDINATING PUBLIC INPUT.
>> AND THAT'S NOT ABOUT REDUCING PARTICIPATION BUT IT'S
ABOUT STRENGTHENING IT ACTUALLY.
>> SO RIGHT NOW VOICES ARE SPREAD ACROSS 152 BODIES
AND THAT CAN LEAD TO FRAGMENTED CONVERSATION TEAMS.
>> SO BY CREATING CLEARER, BETTER STRUCTURED FORUMS PUBLIC
INPUT CAN BE MORE STRATEGIC AND MORE INFLUENTIAL.
AND THAT LEADS ME TO MY NEXT SLIDE WHICH IS ABOUT THE
IMPORTANCE OF PUBLIC INPUT AND STAKEHOLDER ENGAGEMENT FOR
THE TASK FORCE'S EFFORT. >> SO WE DID WORK HARD TO CAST
AS WIDE A NET AS POSSIBLE WITHIN THESE TIME CONSTRAINTS.
AS THE CHAIR SAID, YOU CAN NEVER DO ENOUGH OUTREACH IN SAN
FRANCISCO. BUT I DO WANT TO THANK EACH
SUPERVISOR FOR MEETING WITH US AND STAYING ENGAGED THROUGHOUT
THE PROCESS. WE'VE STAYED IN TOUCH WITH YOUR
OFFICES AND ASKED YOUR AIDES TO HELP SPREAD THE WORD ABOUT OUR
MEETINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS. WE ALSO SENT A SURVEY TO ALL
DEPARTMENTS TO HELP SUPPLEMENT OUR UNDERSTANDING OF THE CITY'S
COMMISSIONS, HOSTED A WORKSHOP WITH COMMISSION SECRETARIES WHO
WORK DIRECTLY WITH THESE BODIES AND NOTIFIED DEPARTMENT HEADS
AND KEY STAFF ABOUT UPCOMING MEETINGS SO THAT THEY COULD
HELP US SPREAD THE WORD TO THEIR COMMISSIONS AND OTHER
STAKEHOLDERS. >> WE MAINTAINED A WEBSITE TO
ENSURE THAT THERE WAS A SINGLE SOURCE OF TRUTH
AND TRANSPARENCY ABOUT THE TASK FORCE'S WORK.
>> AND AT THE HEIGHT OF OUR WORK THAT WEBSITE RECEIVED OVER
1200 MONTHLY VIEWS. AND KNOWING THAT THE PUBLIC
DESERVED ADVANCE NOTICE ABOUT OUR RECOMMENDATIONS BECAUSE OF
HOW IMPACTFUL THEY MIGHT BE, WE SHARED THOSE RECOMMENDATIONS
ONE AND A HALF WEEKS BEFORE EACH MEETING.
>> AND THAT STRATEGY DID SEEM TO WORK BECAUSE PEOPLE REALLY
SHOWED UP PREPARED TO SPEAK ABOUT DETAILS.
THEY HAVE SHOWN UP AGAIN TODAY. YOU SEE THEM HERE.
WE HAD OVER 26 MEETINGS AND ONE OF THOSE WAS HOSTED OFFSITE
IN THE BAYVIEW. WE HEARD FROM OVER 300 PEOPLE
PROVIDE OVER 600 PUBLIC COMMENTS.
IN ADDITION TO RECEIVING MORE THAN 700 PIECES OF WRITTEN
FEEDBACK. >> AND I DO WANT TO STRESS TOO
THAT TODAY'S HEARING IS THE CULMINATION OF A LONG PROCESS
THAT WAS FULLY IN THE PUBLIC VIEW.
OF COURSE THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO AGREE AND DISAGREE ABOUT THE
TASK FORCE'S RECOMMENDATIONS AND THAT MEANS THAT THEY'RE
PAYING ATTENTION AND IT'S TO BE EXPECTED GIVEN THE BREADTH OF
COMPLEXITY OF THIS WORK. >> NEXT SLIDE.
SO PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT OCCURRED THROUGHOUT A STRUCTURED
YEARLONG REVIEW PROCESS AND AGAIN A YEAR MAY SOUND LIKE
A LONG TIME BUT IT REALLY WASN'T GIVEN HOW MUCH THERE WAS
TO TACKLE IT TOOK TIME TO THOUGHTFULLY ANALYZE 152 BODIES
AND MEETING AT LEAST EVERY TWO WEEKS SOMETIMES INTO THE
EVENING WAS A SIGNIFICANT TIME COMMITMENT FOR TASK FORCE
MEMBERS WHO BALANCED THIS WORK ALONGSIDE THEIR OTHER
RESPONSIBILITIES. >> FIRST WE COMPILED A
COMPREHENSIVE LIST OF ALL OF THE CITY'S PUBLIC BODIES WHICH
ACTUALLY DIDN'T EXIST BEFORE. AFTER THAT THE TASK FORCE
DEVELOPED COMMON STANDARDS FOR DIFFERENT TYPES OF BODIES TO
HELP GUIDE STAFF'S ANALYSIS. >> WE STARTED REVIEWING EACH
BODY ONE BY ONE IN THE FALL AND THOSE WERE GROUPED BY
POLICY AREA SO THAT SIMILAR BODIES COULD BE DISCUSSED
TOGETHER. >> AND AT THE END OF THE YEAR
THE TASK FORCE REVIEWED ITS PRELIMINARY DECISIONS
AND BUTTONED UP LOOSE ENDS. SO THE REPORT AND LEGISLATION
COULD BE SUBMITTED IN EARLY 2026.
>> NEXT SLIDE. SO HOW IS EACH BODY ANALYZED?
BY USING OBJECTIVE CRITERIA AND THOSE COVERED WHETHER
BODIES WERE LEGALLY REQUIRED MEETING OFTEN DUPLICATIVE OR
NARROWLY FOCUSED. >> AND THIS EVALUATION WAS
SIMPLY ONE PIECE OF A LARGER PROCESS.
>> WE WANTED TO APPLY THE SAME THINKING TO EACH BODY.
>> AS I SAID BEFORE, THE TASK FORCE KNEW BETTER THAN TO RELY
ON ONE ONE SIZE FITS ALL SOLUTIONS.
>> SO THE FINAL DECISIONS WERE NUANCED AND TAILORED TO THE
NEEDS OF INDIVIDUAL BODIES. >> AFTER MUCH DELIBERATION
AND PUBLIC INPUT. NEXT SLIDE.
SO USING A DELIBERATE PUBLIC PROCESS AND OBJECTIVE ANALYSIS
AS AN ANCHOR FOR THE WORK, THE TASK FORCE DEVELOPED ITS
RECOMMENDATIONS WHICH I'LL DIVE INTO NOW.
>> THE RACKS FALL INTO FOUR KEY AREAS AND THE FIRST TO NEXT
SLIDE. THE FIRST IS TO REDUCE THE
NUMBER OF COMMISSIONS FROM 150 2 TO 87.
>> WE DID NOT APPROACH THIS WITH A SET NUMBER IN MIND.
WE KNEW THAT EACH BODY DESERVED INDIVIDUAL WELL THOUGHT
AND ANALYSIS. AND AGAIN PROP E DID
CONTEMPLATE THIS TYPE OF CHANGE EVEN MENTIONING THAT SOME
COMMISSIONS HAVE FULFILLED THEIR ORIGINAL MANDATES,
OUTLIVED THEIR USEFUL PURPOSES OR ARE DUPLICATIVE OF EACH
OTHER. >> MOST OF THE BODIES
IDENTIFIED FOR ELIMINATION ARE INACTIVE AND IN CODE RATHER
THAN CHARTER OR THEY ARE GROUPS COMPRISED OF CITY STAFF.
>> THESE DECISIONS WERE MADE FOR THREE PRIMARY REASONS.
>> SO FIRST THE PERSPECTIVE THAT FRAGMENTED AND DUPLICATIVE
PUBLIC MEETING BODIES DILUTE EACH OTHER'S IMPACT.
>> HAVING A SMALLER UNIVERSE OF BODIES CAN ACTUALLY STRENGTHEN
THE COMMISSION SYSTEM BY ALLOWING THOSE THAT ARE KEPT TO
BE MORE VISIBLE AND ROBUST VENUES FOR PUBLIC
PARTICIPATION. >> SECOND, SOME BODIES HAVE
ALREADY ACHIEVED THEIR STATED PURPOSE SUCH AS THE POST POST
EARTHQUAKE REBUILD CITY HALL PRESERVATION ADVISORY COMMITTEE
. AND THEN FINALLY SOME BODIES
SUCH AS IPIC AND THE DIGNITY FUND'S SERVICE PROVIDERS
WORKING GROUP COULD CONTINUE MEETING INFORMALLY VIA PASSIVE
MEETING BODIES DON'T NEED TO BE CODIFIED.
>> NEXT SLIDE. >> THE SECOND RECOMMENDATION IS
THE MOVING APPROXIMATELY 20 BODIES FROM THE CHARTER TO THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE. >> AND THIS MAINTAINS THE
EXISTENCE OF THOSE BODIES WHILE PLACING ANY FUTURE CHANGES
WITHIN THE CITY'S REGULAR LEGISLATIVE PROCESS WHICH STILL
REQUIRES PUBLIC HEARINGS LIKE THESE PUBLIC INPUT AND A VOTE
OF THE BOARD INSTEAD OF REQUIRING COSTLY AND TIME
CONSUMING CITYWIDE BALLOT CAMPAIGNS TO MAKE CHANGES.
>> NEXT SLIDE. THE THIRD RECOMMENDATION IS TO
CLARIFY AND UPDATE COMMISSION RESPONSIBILITIES INCLUDING
ALLOWING THE MAYOR TO HIRE AND FIRE MOST DEPARTMENT HEADS
AND CHANGING COMMISSIONER APPOINTMENT AND REMOVAL
PROCESSES. THESE CHANGES ARE MADE FOR TWO
PRIMARY REASONS SO FIRST VOTERS EXPECT TO BE ABLE TO HOLD THE
MAYOR ACCOUNTABLE FOR DEPARTMENTAL PERFORMANCE.
AND SECOND COMMISSIONS SHOULD BE SEEN AS AN EXTENSION OF THE
EXECUTIVE BRANCH. >> MOST COMMISSIONS ARE NOT
INTENDED TO SERVE AS A CHECK AND BALANCE OVER THE MAYOR'S
AUTHORITY ALTHOUGH THERE ARE CERTAINLY EXCEPTIONS FOR BODIES
LIKE CIVIL SERVICE ETHICS, ELECTIONS AND RETIREMENT.
>> NEXT SLIDE. THE TASK FORCE ALSO CATEGORIZED
MOST BODIES AS EITHER DECISION MAKING OR ADVISORY.
AND BOTH OF THOSE PROVIDE A CRUCIAL PUBLIC FORUM.
THE TASK FORCE WANTED TO TREAT THEM DIFFERENTLY.
>> NEXT SLIDE. SO THE FOURTH AND FINAL
RECOMMENDATION IS ABOUT ALIGNING MOST BODIES TO
SPECIFIC STANDARDS. THAT INCLUDES MAKING MANY SI
QUALIFICATIONS DESIRABLE INSTEAD OF REQUIRED SINCE IT
HAS BEEN CHALLENGING TO FIND CANDIDATES AND TO ALLOW GOOD
EFFECTIVE PEOPLE TO SERVE THEIR CITY.
SECOND IS ADDING THREE YEAR SUNSET DATES TO MOST ADVISORY
BODIES AND THAT DOES NOT MEAN THAT BODIES MUST AUTOMATICALLY
DISBAND JUST THAT THEIR WORKLOAD AND PURPOSE WILL BE
REGULARLY EVALUATED. >> GENERALLY THE TASK FORCE
ALSO RECOMMENDS THAT MEMBERS SERVE FOR NO MORE THAN 12 YEARS
ON ANY SINGLE BODY IN ORDER TO ALLOW FOR BROADER PARTICIPATION
AND FRESH PERSPECTIVES. >> THE TASK FORCE ALSO
ADDRESSED HOW COMMISSIONERS ARE REMOVED SINCE NO ONE HAS BEEN
SUCCESSFULLY REMOVED FOR CAUSE IN AT LEAST 40 YEARS.
MOST APPOINTMENTS ARE RECOMMENDED TO BE AT WELL WITH
FOR CAUSE PROTECTIONS LIMITED TO BODIES THAT NEED MORE
INSULATION LIKE CIVIL SERVICE ETHICS AND THE BOARD OF
APPEALS. >> THE TASK FORCE ALSO PROPOSES
SIMPLIFYING THE FOR CAUSE REMOVAL PROCESS BY REMOVING THE
ETHICS COMMISSION HEARING AND REDUCING THE BOARD VOTE
THRESHOLD FROM 9 TO 6. >> NEXT SLIDE INTO YOUR NEXT
SLIDE. IN TERMS OF APPOINTMENTS IT'S
RECOMMENDED THAT WE KEEP BODIES WITH SPLIT APPOINTMENTS
AND CONTINUING ALLOWING A SUPERMAJORITY OF THE BOARD TO
VETO MAYORAL APPOINTEES. >> NEXT SLIDE.
ALMOST DONE HERE. SO FINAL RECOMMENDATIONS
INCLUDE SOME MISCELLANEOUS ITEMS LEAVING COMPENSATION
AND BENEFITS DECISIONS TO YOUR DISCRETION.
>> PROPOSING SOME NAMING CONVENTIONS.
THE FINAL REPORT ALSO IDENTIFIES WAYS FOR THE CITY TO
BETTER MANAGE PUBLIC MEETING BODIES INCLUDING FASTER
APPOINTMENTS, MORE TRAINING AND BETTER INFORMATION
MANAGEMENT ABOUT MEETING ROOMS AND COMMISSION DETAILS.
>> NEXT SLIDE. I'M GOING TO GO THROUGH THIS
REALLY QUICKLY BECAUSE I THINK PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN ALREADY
COVERED MOST OF THIS. WE HAVE TWO PIECES OF
LEGISLATION YOU'RE NOT MAKING DECISIONS TODAY.
IT IS UP TO YOU IF YOU WANT TO INTRODUCE A MODIFIED VERSION OF
THE CHARTER AMENDMENT AND IT WOULD GO THROUGH THE NORMAL
LEGISLATIVE PROCESS IN MAY AND JUNE.
YOU HAVE UNTIL JULY TO DECIDE TO PLACE IT ON THE BALLOT FOR
THE NOVEMBER ELECTION. >> NEXT SLIDE AND NEXT SLIDE.
>> THE ORDINANCE THE TASK FORCE WAS ABLE TO DIRECTLY INTRODUCE
AN ORDINANCE REGARDING CODE CHANGES THAT HAPPENED EARLIER
THIS MONTH. IT'S CURRENTLY ON A 30 DAY HOLD
AND I IMAGINE THERE WILL BE ANOTHER HEARING ABOUT IT
SOMETIME IN APRIL. >> AND AGAIN THAT WILL TAKE
EFFECT IN EARLY JUNE UNLESS EIGHT OF YOU VOTE TO REJECT IT.
AND YOU COULD ALSO AMEND IT BUT THAT WOULD ALSO REQUIRE EIGHT
VOTES TO PASS. NEXT SLIDE.
AND THAT IS THE END. I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT THIS
MARKS A MILESTONE IN A LONG PUBLIC PROCESS THAT WAS
CONDUCTED INTENTIONALLY AND WITH FULL TRANSPARENCY TO
FULFILL A MANDATE OF THE VOTERS.
>> KUDOS TO MY COLLEAGUES FROM THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR
AND CONTROLLER'S OFFICES PARTICULARLY SENIOR SENIOR
ANALYSTS JOANNA BELL AND HENRY O'CONNELL FOR THEIR
THOUGHTFULNESS AND DILIGENCE. AND THANK YOU FOR THAT TO THE
TASK FORCE MEMBERS FOR THEIR DEDICATION.
AND CHIEF ASSISTANT CITY ATTORNEY JOHN GOVERNOR FOR
AGREEING TO TAKE ON THIS EFFORT.
>> I'M JOINED TODAY BY THE BOARD APPOINTED CHAIR AT
HARRINGTON. >> YOU ALREADY HEARD FROM HIM
AS WELL AS OTHER TASK FORCE MEMBERS.
>> WE'D BE HAPPY TO TAKE YOUR QUESTIONS AND THANK YOU AGAIN
FOR YOUR TIME AND ATTENTION. >> THANK YOU.
MISS ALONZO, I'M GOING TO START WITH THE QUESTION THEN HAND IT
OVER TO SUPERVISOR WALTON. I WONDER IF MAYBE CHAIR
HARRINGTON COULD COME BACK UP THERE WERE THERE NOT EVERY NOT
ALL OF YOUR DECISIONS WERE UNANIMOUS, RIGHT?
IN SOME CASES YOU WERE IN THE MINORITY.
I WONDER IF YOU COULD TALK A LITTLE BIT ABOUT THE AREAS
WHERE THERE WAS NOT UNANIMITY. AND IF YOU COULD SORT OF
CAPTURE THE FLAVOR OF KIND OF THE THE ISSUES WHERE THE THE
TASK FORCE MIGHT NOT HAVE BEEN UNITED.
>> CERTAINLY. AND IF I CAN TAKE ADVANTAGE OF
THE TIME TO ALSO KIND OF WALK THROUGH A BIT ABOUT WHO WE'VE
HEARD FROM AND WHERE PEOPLE ARE UNHAPPY WITH THE RESULTS
AND CAN MERGE THE TWO TOGETHER. YEAH, I WOULD GROUP THEM IN A
VARIETY OF WAYS BUT THE MOST CONCERNS STARTING WITH THAT
THERE'S FOUR GROUPS THAT ARE CURRENTLY IN THE CHARTER THAT
THE TASK FORCE RECOMMENDED MOVED TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE. THAT'S THE COMMISSION ON STATUS
OF WOMEN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION, ENVIRONMENT
COMMISSION AND YOUTH COMMISSION.
THOSE COMMISSIONS HAVE ALL EXPRESSED AN INTEREST
IN STAYING IN THE CHARTER. THEY DO NOT WANT TO BE TAKEN
OUT OF THE CHARTER. THOSE ARE ONES THAT I THINK
BOTH SUBSTANTIVELY AND SYMBOLICALLY THAT WAS A
DIFFERENCE OF OPINION IN TERMS OF OUR GROUP.
THERE WAS A SENSE THAT THE FLEXIBILITY WAS NEEDED FOR SOME
OF THESE AND THAT FLEXIBILITY COULD BE GIVEN AN
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE AND GOING TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE WAS
NOT A DEMOTION. CLEARLY PEOPLE FELT DIFFERENTLY
ABOUT THAT POINT OF VIEW. >> THE NEXT GROUPING ARE THREE
AREAS HOMELESSNESS, CHILDREN, YOUTH AND FAMILIES AND AGING
AND DISABILITY WHERE THERE HAVE BEEN AN ACCUMULATION OF CHARTER
AND ADMINISTRATIVE CODE AND OTHER CODE GROUPS BUILT UP
OVER THE YEARS SOME BY INITIATIVE, SOME BY BOARD
ACTION AND SOME BEFORE DEPARTMENTS EVEN EXISTED THAT
THAT ARE NOW HANDLING THOSE KIND OF THINGS.
WE MADE AN ATTEMPT TO GO AHEAD AND GROUP THOSE BODIES TOGETHER
AND TRY TO REARRANGE THEM INTO A WAY THAT WE THOUGHT AT LEAST
WOULD BE MORE APPROPRIATE AND WOULD TAKE ADVANTAGE OF ALL
THE KNOWLEDGE OF THE PEOPLE THAT WERE INVOLVED.
CLEARLY THERE'S PEOPLE WHO DON'T BELIEVE IN THAT AND I'M
HOPING THAT THE BOARD WILL TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THAT AND TALK TO
FOLKS ABOUT WHAT'S THE RIGHT GROUPING.
I AM HOPING THAT WE DON'T JUST SAY THE RIGHT GROUPING ALREADY
EXISTS. I'M NOT SURE THAT'S TRUE.
I THINK THIS IS A BETTER WAY TO DO IT BUT I'M NOT SURE IT'S
NECESSARILY THE WAY THAT WE CHOSE TO DO IT.
SO I'M HOPING THE BOARD CAN WORK ON THAT.
>> THERE ARE SOME GENERAL VIEW ISSUES AT WILL COMMISSIONERS
HIRING FIRING AUTHORITY DEPARTMENT HEADS.
A LOT OF DISCUSSION HAS HAPPENED ABOUT THAT.
I DON'T NEED TO REPEAT THE FEELINGS ON THAT.
>> THERE ARE A COUPLE OF ISSUES SPECIFIC IN TERMS OF PUBLIC
SAFETY. THE POLICE EMPLOY DISCIPLINE
EMPLOYEE DISCIPLINE IN POLICE DEPARTMENT AND THE SHERIFFS ARE
AN OVERSIGHT. SUBPOENA POWER SPLIT
APPOINTMENT BREAKDOWN BEING IN THE CHARTER, THOSE KIND OF
THINGS. >> THOSE ARE THE LARGEST ONES
THAT I'VE HEARD THE MOST ABOUT. THE NEXT GROUPING ARE ONES THAT
PEOPLE CLEARLY HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT BUT IT'S A SMALLER GROUP
OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE EXPRESSED THOSE CONCERNS.
THAT WOULD BE THE ARTS COMMISSION RESTORING AND WE
LEFT THE ART COMMISSION IN THE CHARTER BUT WE TOOK ITS DUTIES
AND MADE THEM IN GOING INTO THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE FOR
FLEXIBILITY. SOME MEMBERS OF THE ART
COMMISSION COMMUNITY WOULD LIKE THAT RESTORED BACK TO THE
CHARTER. THE ETHICS COMMISSION WE HAD A
LOT OF DISCUSSION ABOUT THE ETHICS COMMISSION'S ACCESS TO
THE BALLOT NOT THE GENERAL ASPECTS OF THE COMMISSION BUT
JUST THE ACCESS TO THE BALLOT. I'M SURE THAT WILL COME UP.
THE BUILDING INSPECTION COMMISSION WE HEARD FROM SOME
SOME PEOPLE BUT NOT A BIG OUTCRY IN TERMS OF LEAVING THAT
IN THE CHARTER AND THE SAME WITH THE SMALL BUSINESS
COMMISSION. THE AREAS THAT I'VE HEARD
LITTLE OR NO CONCERNED ABOUT UNTIL MAYBE I MENTIONED THEM
TODAY AND WE'LL SEE WHAT HAPPENS BUT THE VAST MAJORITY
OF THE CHANGES WE MADE TO CITY CODES IN TERMS OF ELIMINATING
GROUPS THAT ARE IN THE CITY CODE WE HAVE HEARD VERY LITTLE
COMMENT ABOUT MOST THAT YOU COULD PUT ON ONE HAND THE
COMMENTS THAT PEOPLE HAVE DIRECTED ABOUT THOSE KINDS OF
THINGS KNOW OUTSIDE THOSE THREE GROUPINGS OF CHILDREN HOMELESS
AND AGING. BUT MOST OF WHAT WE DID IN THAT
IN THE CODE WAS INACTIVE STAFF GROUPS.
THOSE KIND OF THINGS. WE DID VOTE TO ELIMINATE PUBLIC
WORKS COMMISSION AND THE SANITATION STREETS COMMISSIONS.
WE HEARD ONLY ONE COMMENT THAT I RECALL AND THAT WAS FROM THE
CHAIR OF THE PUBLIC WORKS COMMISSION ENCOURAGING US TO
DISSOLVE HER COMMISSION. WE HEARD WE HEARD VERY LITTLE
ABOUT MOVING SOME BODIES FROM CHARTER TO CODE.
SURPRISINGLY IN SOME CASES THAT WOULD BE THE HUMAN SERVICES
COMMISSION, THE ENTERTAINMENT COMMISSION, THE MTA CITIZENS
ADVISORY COUNCIL, PARKS AND RECREATION, OPEN SPACE
ADVISORY COUNCIL CITIZENS GENERAL OBLIGATION BOND
OVERSIGHT PUC RATE FAIRNESS BOARD THAT DEPARTMENT OF
CHILDREN YOUTH IN THEIR FAMILIES SERVICE PROVIDERS,
WORKING GROUPS. IF YOU LOOK AT THE TOTAL WHEN
WE SAY THERE'S 1500 PEOPLE DOING THIS, 295 ARE IN THIS ONE
GROUP YOU CAN'T HAVE A BROWN ACT GROUP WITH 295 PEOPLE
IN IT. SO THAT WAS CHANGED TO SEVEN
PEOPLE AND I THINK THERE'S SOME GENERAL AGREEMENT ON THAT.
THE ABATEMENT APPEALS BOARD IN THE ACCESS APPEALS BOARD
MOVING AROUND A BIT BUT KEEPING THEIR AUTHORITY.
AND THE FINAL ONE WAS THAT WE'VE HEARD VERY LITTLE ABOUT
IS DROPPING SEATS SPECIFIC EXPERIENCE REQUIREMENTS.
THERE ARE A NUMBER OF COMMISSIONS AND COMMITTEES
IN THE CITY. SOMEONE RAISED THE ISSUE ABOUT
THE BALLOT SIMPLIFICATION COMMITTEE AND WHY WOULD WE MAKE
THOSE GENERIC KIND OF REQUIREMENTS AS OPPOSED TO
SPECIFIC? I LOOKED AT THE BOARD'S WEBSITE
THE LAST COUPLE OF DAYS. FOUR OF THE FIVE MEMBERS ARE
OFFICIALLY IN INACTIVE. THEY'RE NOT EVEN OFFICIALLY
IN THE POSITIONS THEY HAPPEN TO KEEP COMING BECAUSE THEY WANT
TO BE GOOD PEOPLE. SO THERE'S A THERE'S A REASON
TO CHANGE THAT SO THAT WE CAN ACTUALLY HAVE THESE THINGS
STAFFED UP. AND I THINK THOSE ARE THAT
THOSE ARE THE THINGS THAT WE'VE HEARD.
THOSE ARE THE KIND OF COMMENTS THAT WE'VE BEEN HEARING FROM
PEOPLE. >> AND AGAIN, HAPPY TO ANSWER
ANY FURTHER QUESTIONS YOU MIGHT HAVE.
THANK YOU. >> CHAIR HARRINGTON.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MADAM AND I JUST HAVE
ONE QUESTION AND SOME VERY BRIEF COMMENTS OR AT LEAST I
CONSIDER IT BRIEF. BUT I THERE WAS A STATEMENT
ABOUT HAVING ANOTHER HEARING AT SOME POINT AND I WANT TO KNOW
IS THAT A MANDATE OR IS THAT JUST SOMETHING THAT THE TASK
FORCE TO SUGGEST THEN YOU DO NOT HAVE TO HAVE ANY HEARING ON
THE ORDINANCE THAT CAN GO THROUGH OR YOU CAN HAVE A
HEARING ON THAT AND YOU DON'T HAVE TO HAVE ANY HEARING ON A
CHARTER AMENDMENT UNLESS SOMEONE HERE INTRODUCES ONE.
>> OKAY. BECAUSE THAT STATEMENT WAS
MADE. SO I WAS JUST WE WERE EXPECTING
THAT THIS WOULD HAPPEN BUT THERE IS NO REQUIREMENT.
GOT IT. WELL, I THINK THAT'S A LOT TO
SPEAK TOWARDS. YOU KNOW, PART OF MY FEELINGS
ABOUT THE TASK FORCE ONE, I WANT TO THANK THE TASK FORCE
FOR YOUR DEDICATION AND YOUR COMMITMENT TO THE WORK.
I TRULY BELIEVE THAT YOU TOOK THE WORK VERY SERIOUSLY.
I ALSO TRULY BELIEVE THAT YOU INVOLVE THE PUBLIC.
SO I DO WANT TO I DO WANT TO STATE THAT BECAUSE I, I FEEL
THAT I SHOULD SAY SOMETHING POSITIVE ABOUT THE WORK THAT
YOU DID. BUT I DO ALSO 100% THINK THAT
YOU EXCEEDED THE MANDATE AND INSERTED OPINIONS
AND POLITICS INTO THE PROCESS FOR SURE.
>> I ALSO WANT TO SAY THAT THE TASK FORCE WAS ABOUT AS DIVERSE
AS A STACK OF $1 BILLS. IT WASN'T DIVERSE AT ALL
AND AND IT'S ALMOST DISHEARTENING FOR SURE IN SAN
FRANCISCO BUT VERY HURTFUL TO HAVE SEEN ALL THE WORK THAT
WE'VE ALL DONE FOR SO MANY YEARS TO HAVE DIVERSE VOICES AT
THE TABLE IN THIS CITY AND TO SEE THAT TASK FORCE LACK ANY
DIVERSITY WAS WAS VERY HARMFUL AND IT'S NOT YOUR FAULT.
IT'S NOT MEMBERS OF THE TASK FORCE FAULT BUT IT'S A LOT OF
PEOPLE'S FAULT THAT THIS TASK FORCE WAS SO DEVOID OF ANY TYPE
OF DIVERSITY. I KNOW SAN FRANCISCO IS
CHANGING. I KNOW THE WELCOME DIVERSITY IS
NOT THE SAME AS IT USED TO BE BUT THAT SHOULD BE COMPLETELY
UNACCEPTABLE IN A CITY LIKE SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND I HAVE TO SAY THAT HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE.
>> AND IF YOU'RE PROPOSING TO CHANGE BODIES THAT COMMUNITIES
VOTED ON THAT ARE IN THE CHARTER PROPOSING TO ELIMINATE
INDEPENDENT OVERSIGHT OF LAW ENFORCEMENT BODIES, ALL THOSE
THINGS ARE JUST MIND BOGGLING TO ME THAT THAT IS SOMETHING
THAT COULD COME FROM A BODY OF FOLKS THAT I CONSIDER TO BE
HIGHLY INTELLIGENT YOU KNOW, WORKING TO DECREASE THE
DIVERSITY ON COMMISSIONS AND COMMITTEES EVEN AS
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES IS DOWNRIGHT SCARY FOR A PERSON
WHO LOOKS LIKE ME IN SAN FRANCISCO.
COULD SOMEBODY BE MORE EFFICIENT?
COULD SOMEBODY OPERATE DIFFERENT?
OF COURSE. >> BUT ACHIEVING EFFICIENCY AT
THE EXPENSE OF DIVERSITY AT THE EXPENSE OF COMMUNITY VOICE, AT
THE EXPENSE OF COORDINATION AT THE EXPENSE OF RESPECT FOR
VARIOUS INCOMES THAT IS NOT WHAT ANYBODY INTENDED TO BE
FROM THIS PROCESS. AND SO I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT
SOME OF WHAT I SEE UM NOT ALL BUT SOME OF WHAT I SEE IS NOT
ONLY ACCEPTABLE BUT ALMOST CRIMINAL TO WHAT THE
CONSEQUENCES WILL BE TO COMMUNITIES IN THIS CITY.
>> AND I HOPE THAT PEOPLE ARE AWARE OF THAT AND THIS IS NOT
ATTACK ON THE TASK FORCE BUT IT'S CERTAINLY ATTACK ON PEOPLE
WHO WANT TO ATTACK THE VERY FABRIC OF THIS CITY.
AND I THINK I KNOW SOME PEOPLE ARE GOING TO SAY THAT, YOU KNOW
,I MAY BE GOING TOO FAR WITH MY COMMENTS.
I MAY BE GOING TOO FAR. BUT WHAT I SEE BUT BUT I CAN
READ VERY WELL AND I ALSO KNOW THIS CITY VERY WELL AND I ALSO
KNOW WHICH CHANGE IT LOOKS LIKE VERY WELL.
AND I ALSO KNOW WITH THE LACK OF INCLUSION LOOKS LIKE AND IN
2026 WE HAVE TO DO BETTER IN SAN FRANCISCO AND IF THE
LEADERSHIP OF THIS CITY IS OKAY WITH WHAT TOOK PLACE WITH THIS
TASK FORCE, THAT'S A PROBLEM FOR ME AND I HAVE TO MAKE SURE
THAT I SAY THAT ON THE RECORD. THANK YOU.
>> PRESIDENT AMENDMENT HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE.
THERE IS A LOT OF WORK TO GET THROUGH FOR THIS HEARING SO WE
JUST ASK PURSUANT TO THE BOARD'S RULES OF ORDER NO
SOUNDS OF SOMETHING YOU CAN ASSOCIATE WITH AND YOU'RE PROUD
OF AND OR NO SOUNDS OF SOMETHING THAT YOU'RE NOT HAPPY
WITH. JUST WAVE YOUR HANDS IF YOU'D
LIKE TO SHOW SUPPORT. >> THANK YOU CIGARETS CHERYL
THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN I DON'T MEAN TO MAKE YOU STAND
THERE. SOMEONE ELSE CAN ANSWER THIS
ALSO BUT YOU KNOW THERE ARE OBVIOUSLY A HUGE NUMBER OF
INDIVIDUAL BODIES THAT THIS REPORT TOUCHES AND SO WE'LL
HAVE TO MAKE INDIVIDUAL DECISIONS ON THOSE.
>> BUT AS WE GO THROUGH THOSE, HOW SHOULD HOW SHOULD WE THINK
ABOUT USING THIS REPORT AS A GENERAL FRAMEWORK AS WE GO
THROUGH DECISION MAKING PROCESSES?
>> WELL, CLEARLY YOU CAN READ THE ENTIRE THING AND WING IT
BUT I WOULD THINK THAT YOU WOULD BE GETTING MORE FROM YOUR
CONSTITUENTS SAYING THESE ARE THE THINGS WE'RE HAPPY ABOUT
AND UNHAPPY ABOUT. THERE IS A LISTING IN THE FRONT
THAT'S ALPHABETICAL AND YOU CAN GO TO THOSE AND THAT GIVES YOU
A LINK TO THE ACTUAL REASONING BEHIND OUR DECISIONS AND WHAT
THAT MIGHT BE. SO IN SOME CASES YOU'LL SEE
THIS GROUP HAS NOT MET IN FOUR YEARS.
THERE ARE SOME GROUPS THAT HAVE NEVER MET THEY WERE THERE WERE
APPROVED BUT NEVER NO ONE WAS EVER APPOINTED.
>> THERE ARE OTHER ONES WHERE THERE ARE AS I SAID, THOSE
GROUPINGS AND WE'VE TRIED TO KEEP THOSE TOGETHER BUT WE ALSO
HAVE SOME HANDOUTS OR WORKSHEETS THAT WE CAN GIVE YOU
TO HELP YOU KIND OF SAY WHY DID YOU TAKE THESE FIVE GROUPS
AND MAKE IT INTO THESE FOUR AND WE CAN GO THROUGH THAT WITH
YOU AND OUR STAFF AND WE WILL BE HAPPY TO DO THAT.
BUT SINCE IT IS SO INVOLVED I WOULD EXPECT THAT YOU WOULD YOU
WOULD CONSIDER IT AND THINGS WHERE YOU WILL HEAR FROM PEOPLE
TODAY AND YOUR CONSTITUENTS WILL SAY THIS IS SOMETHING THAT
I DON'T LIKE OR THIS IS SOMETHING I DO LIKE AND THEN
AGAIN WE'D BE HAPPY TO KIND OF GIVE YOU MORE INFORMATION ABOUT
WHY WE MADE THAT. THE PROPOSAL WE MADE IF THAT
MAKES SENSE. >> YEAH, THAT DOES.
THANK YOU. MY LAST QUESTION ON PAGE EIGHT
YOU HAD GUIDING PRINCIPLES OF THE STREAMLINING EFFORT.
>> THERE WERE FOUR GUIDING PRINCIPLES YOU LISTED HERE.
>> I WON'T READ THEM BUT OF THOSE ARE ARE THERE ANY THAT
YOU WOULD SPECIFICALLY SAY REALLY KEEP IN MIND YOU KNOW
THIS IS SOMETHING THAT WE REALLY THOUGHT WAS ESPECIALLY
IMPORTANT AS A GUIDING PRINCIPLE OF THE REPORT.
>> THERE WAS A COUPLE OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS.
>> RIGHT. AND AGAIN, THIS IS NOT ONE I
THINK WE HAVE UNIVERSAL AGREEMENT ON BUT THE IDEA OF
ACCOUNTABILITY AND CHECKS AND BALANCES IN THE CITY WE
VERY EARLY ON MADE A DECISION THAT WE HAD A CONVERSATION
ABOUT WHAT IS THE REASON FOR COMMISSIONS TO EXIST
AND CLEARLY PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT WAS ONE OF THE CLEAR ONES.
BUT THE OTHER CHOICE WAS OUR COMMISSION SET UP TO BE A CHECK
AND BALANCE ON THE MAYOR AND WHAT WE CAME UP WITH WAS WITH
WE DECIDED THAT SOME ARE ETHICS CIVIL SERVICE ELECTIONS, SOME
OF THOSE KIND BUT THE REAL CHECKS AND BALANCES ARE THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, THE COMPTROLLER, THE CITY ATTORNEY,
ALL THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR, ALL THOSE KINDS OF THINGS AND WE
DID NOT BELIEVE THAT EVERY OTHER COMMISSION SET UP IN THE
CITY WAS AUTOMATICALLY SET UP TO SAY NO TO THE MAYOR, THAT
THERE WAS A REASON THAT THE MAYOR WAS IN CHARGE OF THE CITY
AND ELECTED AND THAT MOST COMMISSIONS SHOULD BE APPOINTED
BY THE MAYOR AND OR THE BOARD AND THE BOARD HAD THE RIGHT TO
VETO THOSE APPOINTMENTS BUT THAT WHEN ALL IS SAID AND DONE
YOU SHOULD OFFER THE ADVICE TO THE MAYOR BECAUSE HE OBVIOUSLY
OR SHE EXPECTS THAT FROM YOU. BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY THE
MAYOR SHOULD WIN THAT ARGUMENT IF IF THERE IS AN ARGUMENT
ABOUT WHAT SHOULD HAPPEN. SO THAT WAS ONE OF THE KEY ONES
AND AS RACHEL SAID, PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT THIS MAY NOT SOUND
LIKE IT TO YOU BUT THERE ARE THERE ARE SOME ORGANIZED
RATIONAL STRUCTURES IN THE CITY WHERE YOU HAVE TO GO TO SO MANY
DIFFERENT GROUPS TO BE HEARD THAT HAVING ONE IMPORTANT
AND OFFICIAL GROUP AS OPPOSED TO FIVE RANDOM GROUPS ACTUALLY
WE THOUGHT WOULD IMPROVE THE ABILITY OF THE CITY TO HEAR
FROM PEOPLE AND TAKE ACTION. GREAT.
THANK YOU. AND TO ALL THE MEMBERS OF THE
COMMISSION, THANK YOU FOR YOUR HARD WORK AND ALSO TO THE STAFF
TO RACHEL. >> THANK YOU FOR WORKING SO
HARD ON THIS. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND I JUST
WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO EVERYBODY FOR THEIR WORK ON
THIS. I WILL CONFESS THAT OF THE
BALLOT MEASURES THAT CONTEMPLATED CHANGES TO
STREAMLINING COMMISSIONS THIS ISN'T THE ONE THAT I THAT I
SUPPORTED AND LARGELY THAT WAS BECAUSE OF THE THERE WAS AN
ARGUMENT THAT THIS WAS THERE WAS NO GUARANTEE THAT PASSING
THIS WOULD ACCOMPLISH ANYTHING. AND I ACTUALLY I FEEL THAT THE
PEOPLE WHO HAVE WORKED ON IT IT PROVED ME WRONG AND I'M HAPPY
TO BE PROVEN WRONG. I THINK YOU'VE DONE SOME REALLY
GREAT WORK ON THIS. >> SO I THINK I THINK WE CAN
PROBABLY ALL AGREE THAT WE'RE NOT HAPPY WITH ALL OF IT BUT I
THINK I DON'T THINK THERE WAS EVER AND EXPECT AN EXPECTATION
THAT YOU WERE GOING TO ACHIEVE THAT.
THERE'S A COUPLE OF THINGS I WANT TO JUST TEASE OUT BECAUSE
YOU MENTIONED I BELIEVE MR. HARRINGTON, THE ARTS COMMISSION
WAS KEPT IN THE CHARTER AS THERE SHALL BE AN ARTS
COMMISSION BUT SOME OF THE RESPONSIBILITIES PRESCRIPTIVE
ELEMENTS WERE MOVED TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE AND I'M
WONDERING IF THAT'S A MODEL TO ADDRESS SOME OF THE OTHER
COMMISSIONS AS WELL. I SPENT MUCH OF MY CAREER JUST
FOR COLLEAGUES IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE SO I JUST
HAVE A LOT OF AXES TO GRIND ABOUT THINGS THAT WE HAVE PUT
IN TO CHARTER THE CHARTER OR OTHERWISE ENACTED AT THE BALLOT
BOX THAT WE CAN'T CHANGE NOW BECAUSE WE HAVE TO GO BACK TO
VOTERS EVERY TIME THERE'S JUST A MINOR CHANGE.
IT FELT TO ME LIKE THE ARTS COMMISSION SOLUTION WAS AN
ELEGANT ONE THAT ASSURES THE COMMISSION THAT THIS REFLECTS
OUR VALUES THAT WE'RE GOING TO HAVE THIS BUT WE'RE NOT GOING
TO TIE OUR HANDS IF WE WANT TO MAKE CHANGES TO BETTER SERVE
ARTS IN SAN FRANCISCO. IS THAT SOMETHING WE SHOULD BE
THINKING ABOUT FOR THE YOUTH COMMISSION DEPARTMENT OR
ENVIRONMENT DEPARTMENT OF THE STATE OR COMMISSION ON THE
STATUS OF WOMEN? >> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION.
SUPERVISOR THE WE DID HAVE A LOT OF DISCUSSION ABOUT THAT
AND WE COULD ONLY ADJUST COMMISSIONS BECAUSE UNJUST
DEPARTMENTS. SO THAT WAS PART OF THE ISSUES.
SO IN SOME CASES WE RECOMMENDED THAT A COMMISSION BE BROUGHT TO
THE CITY TO THE CODE BUT THE DEPARTMENT STILL IN THE CHARTER
AND IF YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT FLEXIBILITY AND MANAGING THE
CITY IT'S REALLY THE DEPARTMENTS AND THE AND THE
INFLEXIBILITY OF HAVING DEPARTMENTS IN THE CHARTER THAT
MAKES THAT SO DIFFICULT. IT ALSO CAN BE DIFFICULT
BECAUSE OF THE NUMBER AND THE JUST AMOUNT OF JUST STUFF
RELATED TO THE COMMISSIONS. I THINK THE AIRPORT COMMISSION
HAS TWO PARAGRAPHS AND MTA HAS 14 PAGES.
YEAH THERE'S REALLY DIFFERENT VIEWS OF HOW MUCH SHOULD BE
IN THE CHARTER THAT I BRING IT TO TO TWO THINGS ONE IS POWER
AND THE OTHER IS TRUST. IF YOU HAVE POWER AND YOU TRUST
PEOPLE YOU WOULD LIKE LESS IN THE CHARTER AND MORE IN THE
CODE TO GIVE YOU FLEXIBILITY IF YOU DON'T HAVE POWER
AND HISTORICALLY HAVE NOT HAD POWER OR YOU HAVE REAL TRUST
ISSUES IN TERMS OF WHAT THE CITY IS DOING, YOU WOULD LIKE
THE RELATIVE CERTAINTY OF BEING IN THE CHARTER AND THAT'S NOT
JUST FOR YOUR COMMISSION BUT IT'S FOR ALL THE DUTIES OF THAT
COMMISSION. AND I THINK THAT'S THE THAT'S
THE TWO SIDES OF ONE COIN THAT WE WERE DEALING WITH THE ENTIRE
TIME WE THOUGHT FOR THE ARTS COMMISSION THAT WOULD BE A
POSSIBLE MODEL THAT LEAVING THE ART COMMISSION IN THE CHARTER
TO RECOGNIZE THAT WE VALUE THE THE WHOLE IDEA OF ARTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO. BUT PUTTING THE DETAILS INTO
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE WHICH WOULD ALLOW THE BOARD AND THE
MAYOR OVER TIME TO CHANGE THOSE THINGS AS WE'RE REQUIRED
AND NOT HAVING TO GO BACK TO THE BOARD WAS A MORE ELEGANT
SOLUTION. I DON'T KNOW HOW MUCH AGREEMENT
THERE IS ON THAT BUT THAT WAS IN THEORY A MODEL AND WE WE GOT
TO IT LATE IN THE PROCESS. >> OKAY.
THE OTHER I JUST WANTED TO TEASE OUT ALSO JUST THE PROCESS
ON SOME OF THE THE UNDER THE POLICE COMMISSION
AND DISCIPLINE AND MY REACTION TO IT WHEN I SAW IT, IT FELT TO
ME LIKE THIS WAS A SOLUTION IN SEARCH OF A PROBLEM.
I HAVE OVER THE YEARS GOING BACK I MEAN I WORKED IN THE
S.F. PD FOR A COUPLE OF YEARS BUT HAVE BEEN FAMILIAR WITH THE
POLICE COMMISSION GOING BACK TO MY FORMER BOSS DENNIS HERRERA
WHEN HE WAS ON THE POLICE COMMISSION I MY SENSE IS THAT
THE DISCIPLINARY PROCESS THAT THE POLICE COMMISSION HAS RUN
OVER THE YEARS HAS BEEN A GOOD ONE.
>> THAT'S FAIR. >> AND OTHER THAN YOU KNOW I
GUESS IT WAS JUST WHAT I'M READING HERE IS THAT THIS WAS
JUST TO SORT OF ALIGN IT WITH THE PRACTICE OF THE FIRE
COMMISSION. IS THERE MORE TO THAT?
I'M JUST TRYING TO UNPACK WHAT WAS THE MOVE TO TO TAKE THIS
AWAY FROM THE POLICE. >> SO THERE'S A COUPLE OF PARTS
TO THAT. OKAY.
YOU MAY HAVE FELT IT RAN VERY, VERY WELL.
WE WE HAVE NOT HEARD THAT UNIVERSALLY.
SO THERE HAVE BEEN CRITICISMS OF THE POLICE DISCIPLINE
PROCESS FOR TAKING A WAIT TOO LONG.
THERE ARE SOME CASES THAT TAKE YEARS AND YEARS.
THERE HAVE BEEN CRITICISMS OF HAVING A POLICE COMMISSIONER
WITH MINIMAL TRAINING TO THE EVIDENTIARY HEARINGS AND THEN
HAVING AN ADMINISTRATIVE LAW JUDGE AT THE VERY END OF THE
PROCESS. AND SO ONE OF THE CHANGES WAS
MAYBE THE ADMINISTRATIVE LAW JUDGE SHOULD DO THE EVIDENTIARY
HEARING AND NOT TO SOMEWHAT TRAINED COMMISSIONER DOING
THAT. IT IS ABSOLUTELY THE CASE
IN EVERY PLACE ELSE EVERY OTHER DEPARTMENT IN THE CITY EXCEPT
POLICE AND FIRE THAT THE DEPARTMENT HEAD HAS A CRITICAL
ROLE IN DISCIPLINE. SO WHY SHOULDN'T THE POLICE
CHIEF HAVE A CRITICAL ROLE IN DISCIPLINE WITH AN APPEAL TO
THE TO THE COMMISSION SO WE TRIED TO REARRANGE IT TO MAKE
SENSE OF THAT. THIS WAS ONE OF THOSE THAT I
DID VOTE AGAINST NOT SO MUCH BECAUSE I DIDN'T THINK OUR
PROCESS MADE MORE SENSE THAN THE CURRENT ONE BUT BECAUSE WE
WERE THE WRONG PEOPLE MAKING THE DECISION THAT THIS WAS
INNATELY A POLITICAL DECISION AND WE WERE ADDING A TECHNICAL
RESPONSE TO IT AND I WOULD HOPE THAT THE POLICE COMMISSION, THE
POLICE CHIEF, THE PWA, THE ACLU AND OTHERS WOULD LOOK AT IT
THEMSELVES AND SAY IS THIS IS THIS THE BEST WE COULD DO?
WE HAD A PROPOSAL. I DO NOT EXPECT THAT WILL BE
IN THE CHARTER AMENDMENT BUT I DO I DON'T THINK WE SHOULD JUST
SAY WHAT WE HAVE RIGHT NOW WORKS.
>> I DON'T BELIEVE IT DOES. I DON'T BELIEVE THAT IT WORKS
AS WELL AS IT COULD. OKAY, GREAT.
>> THANKS. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, I THINK WE CAN
OPEN THIS ITEM TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> YES, MR. PRESIDENT. AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES
YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT. YOU CAN LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER BEFORE WE GO TO THE SPEAKERS WHO ARE
PRESENT IN THE CHAMBER, WE DO HAVE THROUGH A PRIOR
ARRANGEMENT A FIRST SPEAKER WHO WILL BE A CALLER REQUESTING AN
A.D.A. ACCOMMODATION TO MY STAFF.
IF YOU'RE READY PLEASE SEND THE CALLER THROUGH.
WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
WELCOME COLOR. >> THANK YOU.
CAN YOU HEAR ME OKAY? YES, WE CAN.
>> ALL RIGHT. THERE I GO.
GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS PATRICK ARNETT.
SHAWN IS WIDELY THOUGHT THAT THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE HAS
BECOME SPURS BULLY PULPIT INTO THE BULLY PULPIT.
AS I INDICATED IN A WRITTEN TESTIMONY SUBMITTED FOR TODAY'S
MEETING, THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SHOULD IGNORE
INCORRECT INFORMATION IN THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE'S
POWERPOINT PRESENTATION TODAY THAT PROPOSITION ALLOWS THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MAY VETO, DUPLICATE OR AMEND THE CHARTER
AMENDMENT OR PROPOSED ORDINANCE BY BIG VOTES MEANING A TWO
THIRDS SUPERMAJORITY. THAT IS NOT WHAT THE
PROPOSITION STATES THE TASK FORCE WAS BULLYING THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. PROPOSITION INSTEAD OF AN
ORDINANCE WOULD GO INTO EFFECT 90 DAYS AFTER THE DATE OF
INTRODUCTION UNLESS TWO THIRDS OF ALL MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS VOTE DISAPPROVE THE ORDINANCE PROPERLY WAS TOTALLY
SILENT ON DUPLICATION OF ANY LEGISLATION ALL SECTION 5.31
DUPLICATION OF FILING THE BOARD'S RULES OF ORDER STATES
AT THE REQUEST OF ANY SUPERVISOR PRIOR TO THE ROLL
CALL FOR ACTION ON A MATTER THE PRESIDENT OR THE CHAIR OF THE
COMMITTEE SHALL ORDER A FILE DUPLICATE THE TASK FORCE
CLEARLY DIDN'T DUPLICATION OF A FINAL MATTER IS THE SOLE
PRIVILEGE BY A SINGLE SUPERVISOR THAT IT DOESN'T
REQUIRE A VOTE AT ALL. SO MUCH FOR THE VOICE RATHER
THAN PROBLEM STYLE REFORMS VOTERS EXPECTED THE PROP EIGHT
TASK FORCE DEVELOPED AND SUBMITTED PROP EIGHT STYLE
RECOMMENDATIONS IN ITS FINAL REPORT TO THIS BOARD.
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SHOULD CAREFULLY DUPLICATE BOTH THE
PROPOSED CHARTER AMENDMENTS AND THE INITIAL PROPOSED
ORDINANCE. AMENDING THE BOARD SHOULD
SCHEDULE A FULL ROUND OF HEARINGS TO RECONSIDER
RECOMMENDATIONS IN THE DUPLICATED FILES MADE BY THIS
FIVE MEMBER TASK FORCE OF APPOINTED MEMBERS WHO AREN'T
ACCOUNTABLE TO SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS.
DURING A TOWN HALL EVENT ON MARCH 11TH, 2026 SPONSORED BY
REAL REFORM IS IN THE SAN FRANCISCO LEAGUE OF WOMEN
VOTERS STREAMLINING TASK FORCE CHAIRPERSON PAT HARRINGTON
STATED THERE WAS A RANGE OF TOPICS FOR POSSIBLE CHANGES THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS COULD CONSIDER MAYBE ASK HIM OR THE
LEAGUE OF WOMEN VOTERS FOR THE BULLET POINT LIST OF TOPICS.
FAILURE BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO REJECT ANY OF
THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE'S RECOMMENDATIONS WILL BE
SUFFICIENT GROUNDS TO OPPOSE THIS PROPOSED CHARTER
AMENDMENT. VOTERS EXPECT A ROBUST BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS REVISIONS TO THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE'S
RECOMMENDATION BE HEARD IT DETAILED RULES COMMITTEE PUBLIC
HEARINGS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
WELCOME TO OUR FIRST PERSON WHO IS IN THE CHAMBER.
IS THAT YOU, MARGARET BRODKIN. >> WELCOME.
WELCOME. >> THANK YOU.
AND MARGARET BRODKIN AND I HAVE BRAGGED THAT I AM THE ONLY
PERSON IN THE CITY WHO HAS BEEN A DEPARTMENT HEAD DCI OF A
MEMBER OF TWO COMMISSIONS. I AM CURRENTLY PRESIDENT OF
JUVENILE PROBATION AND A LEADER OF SEVERAL GROUNDBREAKING
CAMPAIGNS TO CREATE BODIES FROM THE CHARTER IN 19 91 THE
CHILDREN YOUTH AND FAMILIES COMMISSION WAS PASSED
AND CREATED AND IT HAS BECOME A MODEL FOR THE COUNTRY.
I HAVE SPENT THE LAST DECADE WORKING WITH CITIES
AND COUNTIES THROUGHOUT THE STATE AND COUNTRY TO REPLICATE
WHAT WE'VE DONE IN SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE IT'S
CONSIDERED A MODEL. CITIES LITERALLY TAKE THE
LANGUAGE IN OUR CHARTER WHICH IS A MODEL FOR PLANNING
AND OVERSIGHT AND PUT IT IN THEIR OWN CHARTERS OR
CHARTER. IT'S A DECLARATION OF OUR
VALUES TAKING COMMISSIONS OUT DOES NOT CREATE EFFICIENCIES.
>> IT DOESN'T MEAN LESS WORK. IT ONLY MAKES OUR COMMITMENT TO
ISSUES SUBJECT TO POLITICAL WHIMS.
>> LET'S NOT JOIN THE ANTI-WAR MOVEMENT BY TAKING A CHAINSAW
TO THE VALUES EMBEDDED IN OUR CHARTER.
>> I URGE YOU TO PUT THE TWO CHILDREN AND YOUTH COMMISSIONS
THAT HAVE BEEN TAKEN OUT BACK IN THE CHARTER.
NOTHING REFLECTS OUR VALUES MORE THAN OUR COMMITMENT TO OUR
CHILDREN AND THE FUTURE. >> THANK YOU COMMISSIONER
BRACKEN FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> NO APPLAUSE PLEASE IF YOU'D
LIKE TO SHOW YOUR SUPPORT AS SUCH THANK YOU.
>> WELCOME. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS HOPE WILLIAMS AND IT'S WILLIAMS.
>> CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THAT?
SORRY. HEY, IT'S BEEN A LONG TIME.
WE REALLY WANT TO HEAR YOU. THANK YOU.
MY NAME IS HOPE WILLIAMS. I AM A RESIDENT OF TREASURE
ISLAND. I AM ALSO A THIRD GENERATION
RESIDENT OF SAN FRANCISCO. AND I WANT TO THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR WALTON. YOU BROUGHT TEARS TO MY EYES
BECAUSE THAT IS THE TRUTH. TO HEAR THAT YOU WOULD PUT THE
HUMAN RIGHTS UNDER A BLANKET THAT YOU WOULD ELIMINATE
COMMUNITY ADVISORY BOARDS EFFICIENCY DOES NOT MEAN THAT
IT ACTUALLY DOES WORK. I DIDN'T EVEN GET A CHANCE TO
EVEN GET AN OPPORTUNITY TO SAY SO.
WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT WE ARE ENGAGED.
I WAS A COMMUNITY ADVISORY BOARD MEMBER AND MY ROLE AND MY
ADVOCACY ON THE ISLAND WAS STRIPPED AWAY.
ALL I GOT WAS AN EMAIL AND SAID THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
YOU'RE NO LONGER YOU'RE NO LONGER YOUR SERVICE AND TIME IS
NO LONGER NEEDED. THAT IS NOT HOW WE SHOULD
ENGAGE COMMUNITY. THAT IS NOT IF WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT BRINGING BACK A STRONG CITY WE NEED TO VALUE THE
VOICES IN THE PEOPLE THAT ARE HERE.
WE NEED TO GIVE THEM WE ARE TRYING TO SURVIVE FIVE SO THAT
IS NOT THAT YOU CAN SEE THAT WE'RE TRYING TO JUST MAKE IT ON
A DAILY BASIS. >> SO WHEN YOU LOOK AT THIS
REALLY WE'RE ASKING FOR COMMUNITY IS FOR MORE
ENGAGEMENT, MORE OPPORTUNITY AND TO LEAVE A PLACE THAT MY
YOUNGER ONES WILL BE ABLE TO TAKE VALUE I BROUGHT THEM
BECAUSE I WANTED TO SEE WHAT SIDE OF OF HISTORY YOU WERE
GOING TO STAND ON WHERE YOU REALLY GOING TO STAND ON THE
VALUE OF COMMUNITY FIRST. >> THANK YOU HOPE WILLIAMS OF
YOUR CHARTER AND ADMINISTRATIVE CODE IS A SITUATION ENJOYED BY
PEOPLE IN HIGH INCOME BRACKETS .
I DEMONSTRATED YEARS AGO ADMINISTRATION AFTER
ADMINISTRATION 50% OF ALL HOUSING OPPORTUNITIES THAT
COMES OUT OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE ON HOUSING IS SUPPOSED TO BE
FOR VERY LOW AND LOW INCOME BRACKET PEOPLE.
I EXPLAIN THAT TO YOU, WALTON WHEN I GOT YOU ELECTED AND HAD
JANE, CAN YOU ADDRESS YOUR COMMENTS TO THE BOARD AS A
WHOLE? >> I BELIEVE THERE'S A WHOLE
I'M SPEAKING OF. AND RECLAIMING MY TIME I
POINTED THAT OUT TO YOU THE PRICE FIXING AND THE PRICE
GOUGING ON THE API SCALE WHERE YOU SET DOWN THE REQUIREMENT TO
BE ATTENDING ALL THE HOUSING OPPORTUNITIES HIGHER THAN THE
INCOME OF THE PEOPLE WHO ARE HOMELESS OUT ON THE STREET WHO
ALL OF YOU CLAIM THAT YOU WANT TO HELP.
AND PROFESSIONAL STUPIDITY CHINESE JAPANESE NEW YEAR'S
PARADE ON OR ABOUT 1,500,000 PEOPLE COME TO THE BAY AREA TO
WATCH THAT EVENT. USE THE MUNI TRANSPORTATION
SYSTEM MUNI'S $1,500,000 IN DEBT.
YOU HAVE A CHANCE TO MAKE MONEY AND BALANCE OUT THAT BUDGET.
WHAT IS THIS ADMINISTRATION DO YOU LET EVERYBODY RIDE THIS
MUNI TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM FOR FREE?
YOU CAN'T GET NO DUMBER THAN THAT.
YOU GOT THE SAME PATRICK'S DAY PARADE PEOPLE WHO USE THE MUNI
TRANSPORTATION ARE PAYING THEIR FAIR.
AND AS A RESULT IT'S BEEN PREDICTED THAT THIS DAY PERTAIN
TO SAINT PATRICK'S DAY PARADE WILL BRING IN $7.5 BILLION IF
NOT CORRECT IN A NEGATIVE CASH FLOW DEBT THAT MUNI HAS.
YOU COULD HAVE PUT A BIT DENT IN THAT AND WOMEN'S MONEY.
I'M THE ONE THAT GOT RID OF THE STATUE LIMITATIONS ON RAPE.
HOW COME NONE OF YOU STANDING UP ABOUT MEN PLAYING AND FEMALE
SPORTS MR. RIGHT THAT THIS IS ABOUT THE STREAMLINING TASK
FORCE'S REPORT YEAH AND STREAMLINE TASK FORCE THOSE
ARE THE ISSUES THAT I WANT YOU TO HANDLE AND THAT'S WHY I'M
SPEAKING THE WAY I'M DOING. OKAY.
IS THAT CLEAR? ALL THIS IS DERIVATIVE OF WHAT
I'M TALKING ABOUT AND THAT TASK FORCE NEED TO FOCUS IN ON
NEWSOME ON THAT SET. THANK YOU MR. RIGHT INTERRUPT
MR. RIGHT. >> YOU KNOW THE RULES HERE.
YOU'RE YOU'RE ALWAYS WELCOME BUT WITHIN TWO MINUTES SIR.
>> THANK YOU WAS THAT AND I WILL JUST GIVE THAT INFORMATION
TO EVERYONE WHEN I SAY PLEASE CONFINE YOUR REMARKS TO THE
BOARD AS A WHOLE THAT MEANS YOU ARE NOT SPEAKING TO SUPERVISORS
DIRECTLY. THAT MEANS YOU'RE TALKING TO
ALL MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. >> THANK YOU EVERYBODY.
>> THANK YOU, MR. RIGHT LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
WELCOME, SIR. COME ON UP TO THE PODIUM.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS DOUGLAS HAGMAN
AND SOME OF YOU KNOW I WAS PRESIDENT OF PLANNING
COMMISSION AND PRESIDENT OF BOARD OF APPEALS MANY YEARS
AGO. I WAS ALSO A MEMBER OF THE REAL
REFORM COMMITTEE WHICH DEFEATED THE DISASTROUS PROPERTY
AND CREATED PROPERTY PROP E AND THE TASK FORCE WORKED VERY,
VERY HARD BUT THEY TOOK AN ACADEMIC APPROACH TO LOOKING AT
AND IT WAS BASICALLY THE EASIEST WAY TO TAKE A LOOK AT
154 COMMISSIONS AND TRY AND CATEGORIZE THEM.
BUT AS HAS BEEN NOTED HERE THAT THAT'S AN ACADEMIC ISSUE.
WE ARE IN A MIDDLE OF A POLITICAL ISSUE AND WHEN YOU
HAVE THE PRESIDENT OF THIS COUNTRY ATTACKING DCI,
ATTACKING SERVICES FOR FAMILIES AND CHILDREN, ATTACKING CLIMATE
CHANGE AS A HOAX, HOW CAN WE AS A CITY AND YOU AS COMMISSIONERS
DEMOTE THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION, THE HUMAN SERVICES
COMMISSION, THE DISABILITY AND AGENCY SERVICES COMMISSION,
THE CHILDREN'S AND FAMILIES COMMISSION, THE YOUTH
COMMISSION. >> THE DEPARTMENT.
THE COMMISSION ON THE ENVIRONMENT.
IT'S THE WRONG MESSAGE. AS A MEMBER OF THE GROUP THAT
SUPPORTED PROPERLY WHAT WE HOPE WOULD HAPPEN IS YES, THERE ARE
THINGS IN THE CHARTER THAT THESE VOTERS APPROVED THAT NEED
TO BE CHANGED BUT YOU WANT TO DO IT ON A COMMISSION BY
COMMISSION BASIS LOOKING AT WHAT'S IN THE CODE I MEAN
WHAT'S IN THE CHARTER AND DECIDE WHAT TO TRANSFER IT
OUT AND MAKE THOSE CHANGES AND THAT'S WHAT WE HAD HOPE
HAPPEN. THE TASK FORCE DIDN'T HAVE THE
TIME TO DO THAT. >> THE CHARTER IS OUR
CONSTITUTION. CITIES AROUND THE COUNTRY ARE
LOOKING AT US ARE WE GOING TO UPHOLD OUR CONSTITUTION OR NOT
? >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> DOUGLAS HAGMAN WELCOME TO
OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO MY NAME IS LAURA STEIN
AND I'M SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF THE LEAGUE OF WOMEN VOTERS.
THE LEAGUE MEMBERS URGE YOU TO VOTE NO ON THE PROPOSED CHANGES
SUGGESTED BY THE COMMUNICATIONS COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK
FORCE THE ONE SIZE FITS MOST OR WE MIGHT SAY TWO SIZES FIT MOST
TEMPLATES APPROACH UTILIZED BY THE TASK FORCE WOULD REMOVE
POWER FROM HISTORICALLY MARGINALIZED AND UNREPRESENTED
UNDER REPRESENTED GROUPS WHOSE VOICES SHOULD BE AMPLIFIED
AND UPLIFTED ESPECIALLY IN TODAY'S TROUBLING TIMES.
>> SPECIFICALLY, WE URGE YOU TO PROTECT WOMEN'S VOICES ON THE
SUNSHINE ORDINANCE TASK FORCE REMOVING THE LEAGUE'S NOMINATED
SEAT ON THIS TASK FORCE WOULD NOT ONLY UNDERCUT VITAL
REPRESENTATION BUT BROADCAST THAT THE SAN FRANCISCO
GOVERNMENT LEADERS ARE ABANDONING THEIR SUPPORT FOR
LONG FOUGHT AND CONTINUALLY DEFENDED RIGHTS FOR WOMEN TO
PARTICIPATE MEANINGFULLY IN OUR LOCAL GOVERNMENT.
THE LEAGUE OF WOMEN VOTERS HAS BEEN AMONG THE MOST COMMITTED
ORGANIZATIONS TO THE SUNSHINE TASK FORCE AND HAS ENSURED THAT
ITS SEAT IS CONSISTENTLY FILLED WITH HIGH CALIBER MEMBERS WHO
DEMONSTRATE DILIGENCE AND COMMITMENT TO IMPLEMENTING
THE SUNSHINE ORDINANCE. >> WE ALSO ASK THAT YOU KEEP
NONPARTISAN THE NONPARTISAN AND TRUSTED VOICE OF THE LEAGUE
OF WOMEN VOTERS ON THE BALLOT SIMPLIFICATION COMMITTEE LEAGUE
MEMBERS BRING EXPERIENCE WITH PLAIN LANGUAGE AND EFFECTIVE
ENGAGEMENT AS WELL AS KNOWLEDGE OF VOTER EMPOWERMENT TO THE PSC
. THEIR NOMINEES HAVE ADDED MUCH
NEEDED DIVERSITY TO THE COMMITTEE.
THE LEAGUE HAS APPOINTED THOUGHTFUL, QUALIFIED
AND DEDICATED MEMBERS TO THE PSC FOR DECADES SOURCING
NOMINEES WHO ARE TRULY INDEPENDENT.
>> WELL, WE ALSO URGE THAT YOU RETAIN THE INDEPENDENCE OF THE
COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN DESPITE ITS SMALL SIZE.
IT IS ONE OF THE MOST DIVERSE BODIES IN CITY GOVERNMENT
AND WE ASK THAT YOU NOT REMOVE THEIR CHARTER INDEPENDENCE OR
WEAKEN THEIR GOVERNANCE AUTHORITY WHICH WOULD
COMPROMISE THEIR ABILITY TO MEANINGFULLY PROVIDE OVERSIGHT
AND ACCOUNTABILITY. >> WE ALSO ASK THAT YOU UPHOLD
CHECKS AND BALANCES WITH THE ETHICS COMMISSION COMPROMISING
THEIR ABILITY TO PLACE BALLOT MEASURES BEFORE VOTERS WOULD
UNDERCUT THEIR INDEPENDENCE AND AUTHORITY.
>> SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS STRONG INDEPENDENT INSTITUTIONS THAT
ENSURE WOMEN, GIRLS AND NON-BINARY PEOPLE ARE
REPRESENTED AND HEARD IN CITY DECISION MAKING.
>> WE URGE YOU TO REJECT THE PROPOSED CHANGES PUT FORTH BY
THE TASK FORCE. >> THANK YOU.
LAURA STEIN WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI, I'M FLO KELLY AND I WORK WITH THE COALITION ON
HOMELESSNESS. I LIVE IN DISTRICT NINE AND I
KNOW WE JUST HAD A LOT OF PEOPLE RECOGNIZED HERE AND I
JUST WANT TO RECOGNIZE THE PEOPLE WHO ARE CONSIDERED
UNHOUSED IN THIS CITY AND ARE WORKING HARD TO KEEP THEMSELVES
ALIVE AND SUPPORTING EACH OTHER.
>> HMM. SO THAT AS A COMMUNITY THEY CAN
STAY ALIVE. >> I RECOGNIZE THEIR SPIRIT,
THEIR COMMUNITY BUILDING AND THEIR HUMANITY.
>> SAN FRANCISCO'S STRUGGLES TO BE A SMALL D DEMOCRATIC CITY.
CITIZEN CITIZEN OVERSIGHT THROUGH CITIZENS SITTING ON
BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS IS SIGNIFICANT SO THAT PEOPLE CAN
HAVE A SIGNIFICANT SAY ABOUT THEIR OWN LIVES AND THE LIVES
OF THEIR NEIGHBORS. >> THE THOUGHT OF REMOVING
CITIZEN PARTICIPATION IS A STEP IN THE WRONG DIRECTION.
>> SAN FRANCISCO ALREADY HAS A STRONG MAYORAL RUN GOVERNMENT.
IF THE MAYOR IS CONCERNED NOT TO HAVE HIS WAY OR HE'S
CONCERNED THAT TO GET SOMETHING DONE ON IT JUST TAKES TOO LONG
AND HAS TO BE APPROVED BY SO MANY PEOPLE AND COMMISSIONS.
THAT IS JUST TOO BAD. >> THAT'S JUST THE WAY
DEMOCRACY WORKS. I WORK WITH THE COALITION ON
HOMELESSNESS AS I SAID AND WE NEED ALL FIVE OF OUR COMMITTEES
AND COMMISSIONS. I UNDERSTAND THAT ONE OF THE
PROPOSALS IS TO MAKE ALL OF THEM JUST ONE COMMISSION THAT
DOES NOT THAT WOULD NOT WORK AT ALL.
>> I WORK TO GATHER SIGNATURES FOR PROPERTY IN 2018 EXPLAINING
HOW LARGE BUSINESS TAX IS TAX RECEIPTS FROM LARGE BUSINESSES
WOULD BE TAXED AND THE TAX MONEY WOULD GO TO HOMELESS
SERVICES 50% FOR PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING, 25% FOR
MENTAL HEALTH SERVICE, 15% FOR HOMELESS PREVENTION AND 10% FOR
SHORT TERMS SHELTERS. >> AND A LOT OF PEOPLE WERE
WONDERING WHY SHOULD I SIGN THAT BECAUSE THERE'S NO
GUARANTEE THAT THAT'S GOING TO HAPPEN.
AND I SAID YES, IT IS A GUARANTEE.
IT'S PART OF THE LEGISLATION. IT'S GOING TO BE A COMMISSION
THAT WOULD BE CALLED OUR CITY OUR HOME AND THEY WOULD MAKE
SURE THAT THAT THE MONEY WOULD GO THE WAY IT WAS SUPPOSED TO
GO. AND THAT'S ONE OF THE
COMMISSION'S THAT'S BEING CONSIDERED NOT NOT TO EXIST
ANYMORE. GOOD GRIEF.
AND SO WE HAVE WE WERE THRILLED WHEN WE FINALLY HAD THE
HOMELESS OVERSIGHT OVERSIGHT COMMISSION THAT ACTUALLY HAD
TEETH AND HAD TO APPROVE HSA BUDGETS SETTING UP PERFORMANCE
STANDARDS, AUDITING SERVICE DELIVERY, HOLD PUBLIC HEARINGS
AND FORMULATE LONG TERM POLICY GOALS.
>> IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT THAT WE KEEP THINGS THE WAY THEY ARE
. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, FLO KELLY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS LUCY. OVER TO GO AND I GET THE
PRIVILEGE TO SERVE IN THE IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION
AND I'M ALSO THE DIRECTOR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO LATINO PARITY
AND EQUITY COALITION. TODAY I ALSO SPEAK TO YOU AS AN
ARTIST, A WOMAN AND AN IMMIGRANT THAT LIVES IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> I WANT TO SHARE SEVERAL
EQUITY CONCERNS AS YOU REVIEW THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THIS
TASK FORCE. EFFICIENCY IN GOVERNMENT IS
IMPORTANT BUT IT CANNOT COME AT THE COST OF COMMUNITY VOICE
AND CIVIC ENGAGEMENT. MANY COMMISSIONS IN SAN
FRANCISCO WERE CREATED THROUGH THE YEARS OF COMMUNITY
ORGANIZER ORGANIZING SO COMMUNITIES CAN HAVE A REAL
SEAT AT THE TABLE WHEN DECISIONS AFFECT THEIR LIVES
AND LIVELIHOODS. I AM VERY ALARMED ABOUT THE
POTENTIAL CHANGES AFFECTING THE SAN FRANCISCO COMMISSION ON THE
STATUS OF WOMEN WOMEN IN SAN FRANCISCO CONTINUE TO FACE
DISPARITIES IN ECONOMIC OPPORTUNITY AND REPRESENTATION
AND STRUCTURAL CHANGES SHOULD STRENGTHEN, NOT WEAKEN THE
CITY'S COMMITMENT TO GENDER EQUITY.
>> THEIR PROPOSAL TO MOVE SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION FROM THEIR
CHARTER TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE RAISES SERIOUS CONCERNS.
MANY SMALL BUSINESSES ARE IMMIGRANT OWNED AND WOMEN ON
THAT COMMISSION PROVIDES ONE OF THE FEW FORMAL SPACES WHERE THE
ENTREPRENEURS CAN INFLUENCE POLICY AROUND PERMITTING
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT.
MOVING OUT OF THE CHARTER REMOVES AN IMPORTANT LEVEL OF
VOTER PROTECTION AND MAKES IT EASIER FOR STRUCTURE
AND AUTHORITY TO CHANGE OVER TIME.
>> I ALSO WANT TO HIGHLIGHT THE BROADER IMPACT ON OUR CULTURAL
ECONOMY. PROPOSED SHIFTS IN THE ARTS
COMMISSION IS ALREADY AFFECTING THE ARTS ECOSYSTEM.
IT HAS ALREADY IMPACT HOW ARTIST, MUSICIAN, SMALL VENUES
AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATIONS MAKE THEIR VOICES HEARD AND ACCESS
RESOURCES. FINALLY, I WANT TO RAISE TWO
STRUCTURAL CONCERNS. FIRST, THE PROPOSED CHANGE OF
APPOINTMENT STRUCTURES TO MAKE COMMISSIONS MORE DESIRABLE
SHOULD NOT COME AT THE EXPENSE OF EXPERTISE AND LIVED
EXPERIENCE. THESE BODIES WORK BEST WHEN
COMMISSIONERS BRING DEEP KNOWLEDGE OF THE COMMUNITIES
AND ISSUES THEY REPRESENT. SECOND, THE PROPOSED THREE YEAR
SUNSET REVIEWS ARE SIMPLY TOO SHORT.
MOST COMMISSIONERS LIKE MYSELF ARE VOLUNTEERS.
WE ARE NOT CAREER POLITICIANS AND IT OFTEN TAKES 1 TO 2 YEARS
JUST TO FULLY UNDERSTAND THE POLICY LANDSCAPE
AND DEPARTMENTS INVOLVED. A THREE YEAR CYCLE RISKS
EVALUATING COMMISSIONS BEFORE THEY HAVE TIME TO BE EFFECTIVE.
>> THANK YOU COMMISSIONER OF OREGON FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS ASIA NICOLE DUNCAN. I WAS THE CAMPAIGN DIRECTOR FOR
PROPERTY. THIS WAS A VERY DIFFICULT TASK
FOR THE TASK FORCE. I KNOW THAT ALL MY ADVOCATES
CAME TO YOU ALL AND WANTED TO HAVE THEIR OPINIONS.
AND IT WAS A LONG, LONG YEAR FOR ALL OF US AND FOR YOU.
YOU WERE ALL GIVEN A DAUNTING ASSIGNMENT BY THE VOTERS AND WE
BELIEVE THE INTENT OF THAT ASSIGNMENT WAS TO STRENGTHEN
EFFICIENCY WHILE VALUING DEMOCRATIC PARTICIPATION
AND OVERSIGHT. AND I BELIEVE THAT BALANCE WAS
LOST. >> THE RECOMMENDATIONS
UNDERVALUES THE ROLE OF COMMISSIONS THAT PROTECT OUR
COMMUNITIES, ESPECIALLY THOSE FOCUSED ON ARTS CHILDREN, YOUTH
,WOMEN AND OUR CIVIL RIGHTS. ALL OF THOSE THAT CHAIR
HARRINGTON HAS ALSO MENTIONED. THESE BODIES ENSURE
ACCOUNTABILITY AND COMMUNITY VOICE REGARDLESS OF WHO IS
IN POWER. I'M ASKING THIS BOARD TO
CORRECT THE OVERREACH. SAN FRANCISCANS DID NOT WANT
POWER CONCENTRATED IN ONE OFFICE.
OUR SYSTEM IS BUILT ON CHECKS AND BALANCES FOR A REASON.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS STEVEN TORRES AND THE PROGRAM MANAGER FOR THE
CASTRO LGBTQ CULTURAL DISTRICT AND I'M HERE TO CONVEY OUR
STRONG SUPPORT TO PRESERVING CORE OVERSIGHT AND EQUITY
COMMISSIONS IN THE CHARTER ALONG WITH KEEPING BODIES AS
INDEPENDENT STRUCTURES. THE CASTRO LGBTQ CULTURAL
DISTRICT IS DEDICATED TO CENTERING AND UPLIFTING
PEOPLE, PLACES AND CULTURE. AS SUCH, WE ARE INVESTED IN THE
ROLE OF COMMISSIONS TO PROVIDE IMPORTANT CHECKS AND BALANCES
THAT ENSURE RACIAL, GENDER AND CLASS EQUITY FROM VOICES OF
THE PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO CITY GOVERNMENTAL CONVERSATIONS
THAT AFFECT OUR LIVES ON A DAILY BASIS.
COMMUNITIES ALL ACROSS THE UNITED STATES ARE UNDER ATTACK
AT THE FEDERAL, STATE AND LOCAL LEVELS WHICH MAKES COMMUNITY
ABILITY TO ADVOCATE AND POLICY DISCUSSIONS AT THE CITY LEVEL
EVEN MORE CRUCIAL THAN EVER. WE ARE ESPECIALLY INTERESTED
IN SUPPORTING THE PRESERVATION OF THE FOLLOWING COMMISSIONS
THE ENTERTAINMENT COMMISSION, THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION,
THE YOUTH COMMISSION, CHILDREN, YOUTH AND THEIR FAMILIES
OVERSIGHT ADVISORY COMMITTEE. COMMISSIONS ON THE COMMISSION
ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN COMMISSION ON ENVIRONMENT
DISABILITY AND AGING SERVICES COMMISSION HOMELESSNESS
OVERSIGHT COMMISSIONS. SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION
BUILDING INSPECTION COMMISSION SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT OVERSIGHT
BOARD. >> POLICE COMMISSION.
HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION.
SAN FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION. >> ON A PERSONAL NOTE, I JUST
WANT TO ADD AS A FORMER COMMISSIONER THAT I ECHO THE
CONCERN ABOUT SPECIAL SKILLS AND KNOWLEDGE NOT BEING
IMPORTANT TO THESE ROLES. IT'S INCREDIBLY CRUCIAL
AND IMPORTANT AND ANYTHING THAT WOULD TAKE THAT AWAY OR
TARGETING TAHT TARGETING ANYTHING IN THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE TO REMOVE POWER IN THAT REGARD IS JUST SETTING THESE
BOATS TO BE UP TO BE SYCOPHANTIC AND NOT ACTUALLY
REPRESENTING OUR PEOPLE AT ALL .
>> THANK YOU STEPHEN TORRES FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
FORMER SAN ANSELMO MAYOR PAUL SCHNELL, WELCOME.
WELL, THANK YOU, MS.. CARVILLE.
GOOD AFTERNOON TO PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN AND MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS PAUL SCHNELL.
I'M A RETIRED SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT CAPTAIN WHO
PREVIOUSLY COMMANDED BAYVIEW STATION INGLESIDE STATION
TERRIBLE STATION MANAGING HUNDREDS OF POLICE OFFICERS
AND ALSO WORKED FOR MANY YEARS IN THE TENDERLOIN AS A POLICE
OFFICER AND AT NORTHERN STATION IN THE PAST FEW YEARS I'VE BEEN
THE LEGAL DEFENSE ADMINISTRATOR FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
OFFICERS ASSOCIATION. IN THAT CAPACITY I WORK CLOSELY
WITH THE POLICE COMMISSION ON DISCIPLINE CASES AND SUPERVISE
AS WELL AS ASSIGN OUR ATTORNEYS IN DISCIPLINE CASES AND ALSO
WORK WITH OUR ATTORNEYS AND THE COMMISSION AND THE POLICE CHIEF
IN TERMS OF CHANGING POLICIES IN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT.
THE REPORT FROM THE COMMISSION'S STREAMLINING TASK
FORCE ON CHARTER REVISION WILL SERIOUSLY ALTER AN EFFECTIVE
AND WORKABLE CHARTER MANDATED DISCIPLINE SYSTEM FOR THE S.F.
PD AND WE URGE THE BOARD TO REJECT THOSE PROPOSED CHANGES.
THERE ARE OTHER CHANGES THAT THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE HAS
SUGGESTED. I KNOW THAT WE WILL PROBABLY
EMBRACE. >> HOWEVER, HANDING SOLE POWER
TO THE CHIEF OF POLICE FOR ADMINISTRATIVE DISCIPLINE
INCLUDING TERMINATION OF EMPLOYMENT WOULD BE A SEVERE
IMPEDIMENT TO DUE PROCESS FOR POLICE OFFICERS.
>> THE CURRENT SYSTEM ENSURES ACCOUNTABILITY TO DISCIPLINE
ERRANT OFFICERS, FAIRNESS AND CIVILIAN CONTROL.
I NOTE THAT COMMISSIONER ELIAS WAS HERE.
SHE HAD TO DEPART BUT I BELIEVE SHE'LL COME BACK TO SPEAK.
>> THE WEAKENING OF POLICE COMMISSION JURISDICTION WHICH
IS PROPOSED WOULD DISMANTLE THE MOST IORTANT COMPONENT OF
POLICE REFORMS WHICH HAVE OCCURRED OVER THE PAST TEN
YEARS. THEY'VE REDUCED THE USE OF
FORCE POLICE SHOOTINGS AND THE PROGRESSIVE POLICIES THAT WE
HAVE SUPPORTED THE DEFENSE BAR SUPPORTED AND MOST IMPORTANTLY
THE COMMUNITY WE SUPPORT WOULD BE AT RISK IF THE COMMISSION
POWER WAS TAKEN AWAY. THERE IS A NEXUS.
LASTLY BETWEEN POLICE CIVIL LAW AND LAW.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> HI, I'M OFFICER MCKIERNAN. I AM CURRENTLY PRESIDENT OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE OFFICERS PRIDE ALLIANCE WHICH ADVOCATES
FOR, TRANS AND NON-BINARY MEMBERS.
I'M ALSO A PATROL OFFICER IN THE TENDERLOIN DISTRICT.
I WANT TO THANK THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR ALLOWING ME TO
SPEAK ON THIS PROPOSAL. I AND MY FELLOW MEMBERS ARE
FAMILIAR WITH THE CURRENT DISCIPLINE PROCESS AND WE DO
NOT SUPPORT THE PROPOSED CHANGE TO THE CURRENT SYSTEM.
I BELIEVE THIS PROPOSAL GIVES THE CHIEF TOTAL CONTROL OVER
THE DISCIPLINE PROCESS SUBJECTING OFFICERS TO ONE
PERSON SOLE DISCRETION AND BIASES.
THE DISCIPLINE PROCESS IS FAIR WHEN THERE ARE MULTIPLE
PERSPECTIVES. THIS ALSO LESSENS CIVILIAN
CONTROL AND OVERSIGHT. THOUGH SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN
SPARED. I THINK WE ALL HAVE SEEN AROUND
THE COUNTRY WHAT CAN HAPPEN WHEN LAW ENFORCEMENT DOES NOT
HAVE CIVILIAN OVERSIGHT IN ACCOUNTABILITY WHEN IT COMES
TO DISCIPLINE AND USES OF FORCE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, OFFICER MCKIERNAN
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON. PRESENT THE MEN AND THE MEMBERS
OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BORDER SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS MARIO MOLINA. I'M A RETIRED SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE LIEUTENANT AND THE PRESIDENT OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
LATINO PEACE OFFICERS ASSOCIATION METRO CHAPTER.
I WANT TO EMPHASIZE THAT EVERYONE HERE SUPPORTS
ACCOUNTABILITY, INAPPROPRIATE AND APPROPRIATE DISCIPLINE WHEN
MISCONDUCT OCCURS. THAT IS NOT THE ISSUE HERE.
THE CONCERN IS ENSURING THAT OUR DISCIPLINARY SYSTEM REMAINS
FAIR BALANCE AND CONSISTENT. THIS CHANGE WILL ALSO
SIGNIFICANTLY DIMINISHED THE ROLE OF THE POLICE COMMISSION
AS A CIVILIAN OVERSIGHT BODY. THE COMMISSION HAS LAUNCHED
THEIR SERVICES PRESENTED THE BOYS FOR THE COMMUNITY TO SAN
FRANCISCO IN MATTERS OF POLICY AND SERIOUS DISCIPLINE.
I WAS A POLICE OFFICER FOR 21 YEARS AND I EXPERIENCED
FIRSTHAND MAINTAINING THAT INDEPENDENT CIVILIAN BOMBINGS
IMPORTANT TO TRANSPARENCY, PUBLIC TRUST, CONFIDENCE AND IN
THE PROCESS INDEPENDENT REVIEW HAS LONG BEEN AN IMPORTANT PART
OF MAINTAINING CONFIDENCE IN THE DISCIPLINARY SYSTEM BOTH
FOR OFFICERS AND FOR THE PUBLIC.
WHEN THE DISCIPLINE IS PERCEIVED AS A FAIR,
TRANSPARENT AND IMPARTIAL, IT STRENGTHENS THE TRUST IN THE
SYSTEM. OUR GOAL SHOULD BE TO MAINTAIN
STRONG ACCOUNTABILITY WHILE ALSO ENSURING THAT THE PROCESS
REMAINS BALANCE CONSISTENT AND GROUNDED IN DUE PROCESS.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME AND CONSIDERATION ON THIS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. EVENING TO EVERYBODY.
MY NAME IS MARITZA SALINAS AND I AM MY MOTHER.
THREE MINORS. I AM CREATING CURRENTLY
HOMELESS AND RECEIVING SHELTER SERVICES.
I'M AN EMERGENCY SHELTER WHICH IS HAMILTON EMERGENCY.
I'M VERY GRATEFUL TO BE THERE BUT UNFORTUNATELY AT THIS TIME
SOME SITUATIONS HAVE HAPPENED AND YOU GUYS WILL BE WONDERING
WHY. SHE TALKING ABOUT SHELTER
IN THIS CASE BECAUSE UNFORTUNATELY LAST WEEK
SOMEBODY HAD THE AUDACITY TO PUT A PESTICIDE IN MY ROOM
WHICH I WASN'T NOTIFY AND THEN I'M LIKE OKAY, LET ME CALL 902.
THE OFFICERS I CALLED AND THEN THEY'RE LIKE OKAY,
MISCELLANEOUS WE CAN ALL FIRE OUR POLICE REPORT FOR PESTICIDE
BUT WE CAN FOLLOW MISDEMEANOR. I'M PAUSING YOUR TIME FOR A
MOMENT AND ALSO I'M PAUSING YOUR TIME FOR A MOMENT.
ALL RIGHT. ARE YOU SPEAKING ABOUT THE
SHELTER MONITORING COMMITTEE IN THAT CAPACITY?
THAT'S WHAT I'M ABOUT TO GO. OKAY.
I WILL RESUME AND APOLOGIZE. >> BUT I KNOW FROM MY SITUATION
MY CURRENT POSITION RIGHT NOW SO WHEN I START ASKING
EVERYBODY LIKE WHETHER THE BEST WAY TO GO WITH THIS BECAUSE I
MEAN WHAT'S BEST TO SAY I HAVE A BURNING EYES AND YOU KNOW
SYMPTOMS THAT IS UNFORTUNATELY MY CHILDREN TOO SO THEY'RE LIKE
THEY THERE IS A COMMITTEE AND I'M LIKE OKAY I'M GONNA GO
IN. >> I FIND OUT THAT THAT
COMMITTEES IS IN THIS SITUATION RIGHT NOW AND I AM HERE TO ASK
IS A POOR A RESIDENT YOU KNOW THEY IS GOING TO NEED THIS
SERVICES. THAT'S MY SITUATION RIGHT NOW
AND I WOULD LIKE TO LET YOU GUYS KNOW THAT HOW IMPORTANT IT
IS FOR US IS OUR COMMUNITY TO HAVE THESE SERVICES AND I
CANNOT BELIEVE THAT THIS IS GOING TO BE THE ONLY CHANCE I
HAVE IS GOING TO BE REMOVED AND TO MY UNDERSTANDING THEIR
SHELTERS ARE YOU UNIQUE INSTITUTIONS THEY HOUSE
VULNERABLE POPULATIONS BUT HAVE NO STATED A LICENSING
REQUIREMENTS THEY MIX OVERSIGHT ESSENTIALS UNLIKELY HOSPITALS
NURSING HOMES OR A DAYCARE CENTER AND SHELTERS
IN CALIFORNIA DO NOT REQUIRES THEY LICENSING SO WE NEED
COMEDIES LIKE THIS ONE TO REALLY ADVOCATE FOR OUR
CHILDREN'S AND OURSELVES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
KRISTIN OVENS. THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE
BUREAU BUREAUCRATIC LEAD AND COMMISSION STREAMLINING
TASK FORCE NEED TO BE CONSIDERED IN LIGHT OF
MAYOR LAURIE'S PROPOSAL CALLED STRENGTHENING EXECUTIVE BRANCH
ACCOUNTABILITY WHICH IS PROPOSED TO TAKE THE BALLOT
IN NOVEMBER. THE PARALLELS BETWEEN
WASHINGTON DC AND SAN FRANCISCO ARE FRIGHTENINGLY SIMILAR
AND WHAT BRAVE NEW WORLD DO WE THINK THAT BILLIONAIRES ARE
ENTITLED TO DICTATE THE ORGANIZATION AND RESOURCES OF
OUR GOVERNMENT? >> OUR OWN BILLIONAIRE
MAYOR HAS PROPOSED A SEA CHANGE OF CHARTER REFORM AFTER A HASTY
WORKING GROUP PROCESS THAT HAD PUBLIC COMMENT IGNORED
AND FULLY BASED LEGISLATION POSTED ONLINE LESS THAN 24
HOURS FROM THE LAST PUBLIC COMMENT SUBMITTED CHERRY
PICKING FROM THIS COMMISSION'S STREAMLINING TASK FORCE
RECOMMENDATIONS THE MAYOR IS STAGING AN EXECUTIVE POWER GRAB
UPENDING CHECKS AND BALANCES, ASKING THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND OUR CITY COMMISSIONS TO GIVE UP THEIR OVERSIGHT
RESPONSIBILITIES AND HE WOULD CHANGE OUR MORE THAN 100 YEAR
TRADITION OF GOVERNMENT OVERSIGHT WHERE COMMISSIONS
DESIGNED TO THWART CORRUPTION INCOMPETENCE BY SHINING A LIGHT
AND CREATING TRANSPARENCY TO DEPARTMENTAL SPENDING.
THIS MAYORS INITIATIVE WILL NOT BE HEARD BY THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AND IT CHANGES COMMISSION APPOINTMENTS TO BE
AT WILL INSTEAD OF FOR CAUSE MEANING THAT COMMISSIONERS WILL
BE REQUIRED TO FULL THROATED LEE SUPPORT EXECUTIVE POSITIONS
OR FACE REMOVAL. THIS RENDERS OUR COMMISSIONS
SIMPLE RUBBER STAMPS AND REMOVES ACCOUNTABILITY
AND IS A SLAP IN THE FACE TO COMMUNITY EXPERTISE.
>> THIS BILLIONAIRE MAYOR IS TELLING YOU HE KNOWS WHAT'S
GOOD FOR THE WOMEN'S COMMISSION, FOR THE SMALL
BUSINESS COMMISSION, FOR THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION AND FOR
THE POLICE COMMISSION. YET HE HAS NO EXPERIENCE BEING
A WOMAN OR A SMALL BUSINESS OWNER OR FIGHTING FOR HUMAN
RIGHTS AND CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORM.
>> YET HE THINKS HE IS A KING THAT KNOWS BEST AND SHOULD
DICTATE. AS FOR ALL THIS HAM SO-CALLED
CHARTER REFORM PROCESS HAS BEEN SUCH A MESS THAT IS BLATANTLY
IGNORED HOURS OF PUBLIC COMMENT BECAUSE IT HAD PREDETERMINED
AND POLITICALLY MOTIVATED OUTCOMES IN MIND.
>> THAT'S WHY WE SHOULD OPPOSE ALL CHARTER REFORM.
>> NO KINGS IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE. WE APPRECIATE YOUR ENTHUSIASM.
>> JUST HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE WELCOME TO OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS CYNTHIA GOMEZ UNITE
HERE LOCAL TWO THE HOTEL WORKERS UNION THE FOLLOWING
UNIONS HAVE ALSO ASKED TO SIGN ON TO MY COMMENTS THE NATIONAL
UNION OF HEALTH CARE WORKERS IBEW LOCALS SIX AND LOCAL 1245
YOU KNOW YOUR LOCAL TWO IS CONCERNED ABOUT THE GENERAL
TREND AND THE RECOMMENDATIONS COMING OUT OF THE COMMISSION
STREAMLINING TASK FORCE AND THE WAYS IN WHICH THOSE
RECOMMENDATION LINES OVERLAP WITH SOME OF THE PROPOSED
CHANGES TO THE CITY'S CHARTER. WE REMAIN IN FIRM OPPOSITION TO
THE PROPOSED REQUIREMENTS AND THE RESTRICTION TO PLACING
INITIATIVES ON THE BALLOT. IN ADDITION, WE HAVE REAL
CONCERN OVER PROPOSALS THAT IMPOSE TERM LIMITS ON
COMMISSIONERS AND ALLOW COMMISSIONERS TO BE REMOVED ON
AN AT WILL BASIS. THESE PROPOSED AMENDMENTS WHICH
CONCENTRATE POWER AWAY FROM THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND TOWARD
THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH BUT NOT ONLY ERODE THE POLITICAL
INDEPENDENCE OF THOSE BODIES BUT THEY WOULD REMOVE THE
ABILITY FOR COMMISSIONERS TO DEVELOP OR EXERCISE THE
INSTITUTIONAL KNOWLEDGE THAT'S CRUCIAL TO SERVING THE
INTERESTS OF THE CITY. >> THESE CHANGES WOULD APPLY TO
A WHOLE SWATH OF COMMISSIONS THAT ALLOW FOR WORKING PEOPLE
TO HAVE A VOICE AND INFLUENCE IN CITY DECISIONS AND IT IS
WORKING PEOPLE WHO WOULD MOST BE AFFECTED.
THE AMENDMENTS ARE BEING CHARACTERIZED AS
ANTI-CORRUPTION AND GOOD GOVERNMENT BUT IN REALITY THEY
WOULD DO LITTLE MORE THAN ALLOW THE WEALTHY TO VOTE AWAY THE
POWER OF WORKING PEOPLE. WE THEREFORE STAND
IN OPPOSITION TO THE CHANGES AS CURRENTLY PROPOSED.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON AND HAPPY ST
PATRICK'S DAY. I'M DENNIS HENDRICKS A BIPOC
COMMUNITY ORGANIZER. THANK YOU THE TASK FORCE
AND CHAIR HARRINGTON IN PARTICULAR HE DID A REALLY
GOOD PUBLIC SERVICE HERE. SADLY MY CONCERN IS THAT THIS
WAS POLITICALLY HIJACKED. THERE WERE TWO ISSUES ONE IS
THAT SEVERAL S.F. SERVICES ARE HANDICAPPED BY THESE CHANGES
AND THE OTHER IS THAT UNDEMOCRATIC ENGAGEMENT IS AT
RISK BY HOW THIS PROCESS WAS MANAGED.
PROBIE WAS INITIALLY SENT TO COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS AS A
NON-CONFRONTATIONAL AFFAIR. NATURALLY THAT'S AN
OVERSIMPLIFICATION CLEAN UP IS NEEDED AND THERE'S A STRONG
START BUT DECISIONS MAY BE TOUGH OR UNPOPULAR BUT THESE
CROSSOVER THE MANDATE GIVEN TO THE TASK FORCE AND THE EFFICACY
OF THE COMMISSIONS AT RISK TRANSFER TRANSPARENCY IS NOT
THE SAME AS LISTENING AND IT'S A DANGEROUSLY UNDEMOCRATIC
PROCESS. WOMEN UNHOUSED FOLKS
AND CHILDREN NEED TO BE HEARD AND NOT IGNORED.
REMOVING THESE GROUPS FROM THEIR CHARTER IS A DANGEROUS
CHANGE FOR VULNERABLE PEOPLE AND SCARES FOLKS FROM
EMPOWERING THEM IN THE WAY THAT OF POLITICAL ENGAGEMENT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER GOOD AFTERNOON. >> BOARD PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. MY NAME IS SCOTT RIPKEN, TELUS
VICE CHAIR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION
AND I'M SPEAKING IN MY PERSONAL CAPACITY REGARDING THE
COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK FORCE'S RECOMMENDATIONS.
I HAVE ALREADY EMAILED EACH OF YOU A DETAILED WRITTEN COMMENT
WITH MY RESEARCH AND ARCHIVED DOCUMENTS ABOUT THE COMMISSION
ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN BUT I WOULD LIKE TO SHARE A BRIEF
SNIPPET SNIPPET HERE AS WELL. >> THE TASK FORCE HAS
RECOMMENDED STRIPPING THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN FROM A GOVERNANCE BODY TO AN ADVISORY ONE WHICH IS
REFLECTED IN THE PROPOSED CHARTER AMENDMENT REVISING
SECTION 4.19 TO STATE THAT THE COMMISSION SHALL BE AN ADVISORY
BODY AND TRANSFERRING IT FROM THE CHARTER TO THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE. THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN WAS CREATED IN 1975 TO ASSESS THE STATUS OF WOMEN
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND INVESTIGATE THE SYSTEMIC
BARRIERS PREVENTING WOMEN FROM ACHIEVING EQUALITY DUE TO
DISCRIMINATION AND INJUSTICE. NEARLY 50 YEARS LATER THOSE
INEQUITIES HAVE NOT DISAPPEARED WOMEN, PARTICULARLY IMMIGRANT
WOMEN, WOMEN OF COLOR, SINGLE WOMEN, SINGLE MOTHERS CONTINUE
TO FACE DISPARITIES IN ECONOMIC SECURITY, SAFETY, HEALTH
CONCERNS, HEALTH OUTCOMES AND REPRESENTATION
IN LEADERSHIP. >> SO WE NEED THE COMMISSION ON
STATUS OF WOMEN TO BE UNTOUCHED.
I WANT TO BE CLEAR I'M NOT OPPOSED TO REFORM BUT IT RAISES
AN IMPORTANT QUESTION WHY ARE WE WEAKENING CIVILIAN OVERSIGHT
FROM COMMISSIONS THAT SERVE MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES
AND COMMISSIONS THAT ARE ACTUALLY WORKING THE COMMISSION
ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN, THE POLICE COMMISSION?
THE YOUTH COMMISSION EXISTS PRECISELY BECAUSE THE COMMUNITY
THEY REPRESENT DESERVE A VOICE WITHIN THE CITY GOVERNMENT.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG BEEN A NATIONAL LEADER ON GENDER
EQUITY. WE WERE THE FIRST IN THE UNITED
STATES TO SIGN TO IMPLEMENT ACTUALLY.
CEDAW SAYS THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS CONSIDERS THESE
RECOMMENDATIONS AND AMENDMENTS. PLEASE TAKE THIS MOMENT TO ASK
A BROADER QUESTION. >> WELL WE WEAKEN THE
STRUCTURES THAT WERE CREATED TO PROTECT US.
>> REAL WE CHOOSE THE RIGHT SIDE.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU, COMMISSIONER
QADRI FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI. MY NAME IS SAMANTHA CHAVEZ
AND I AM A SAN FRANCISCO VOTER, COMMUNITY ORGANIZER
AND STORYTELLER. HAVING BEEN BORN AND RAISED
IN DALLAS, TEXAS, I UNDERSTAND HOW IMPORTANT COMMUNITY
OVERSIGHT IS IN GOVERNMENT AND THE CONSEQUENCES WHEN WE
STRIP IT AWAY FOR THE SAKE OF EFFICIENCY INDEPENDENT
COMMISSIONS ARE A PART OF THE FABRIC OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
DEMOCRACY. >> THEY WERE EMBEDDED INTO THE
CITY GOVERNMENT AND CHARTER IN THE LATE 1800S WHEN SAN
FRANCISCO WAS BECOMING A CITY AND STRENGTHENED AFTER HARVEY
MILK WAS KILLED FOR THE CRIME OF BEING GAY.
>> WHEN A WHEN GOVERNMENT PRIORITIZES OFFENSIVE
EFFICIENCY OVER DEMOCRACY THEY LEAVE OUR MOST VULNERABLE
BEHIND. >> I WANT TO THANK SOME OF THE
SUPERVISORS FOR MENTIONING THIS AND BEING CLEAR ABOUT THE
CONSEQUENCES OF THESE ACTIONS. >> AT A TIME OF RISING FASCISM
NATIONALLY AND GLOBALLY, SAN FRANCISCO SHOULD BE
STRENGTHENING ITS SUPPORT OF IMMIGRANTS WOMEN, BLACK
AND BROWN COMMUNITIES NOT STRIPPING AWAY THEIR POWER.
>> WE ALL DESERVE A GOVERNMENT THAT SUPPORTS CITIZENS NOT
EFFICIENCY. >> STOP THE TEXAS FICATION OF
SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU SAMANTHA CHAVEZ FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS SOFIANE DARI AND I AM A COMMISSIONER ON THE
COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN SPEAKING IN MY PERSONAL
CAPACITY. SO I JOIN THE COMMISSION TO
ENSURE THAT UNDERREPRESENTED COMMUNITIES HAVE A REAL SEAT AT
THE TABLE. THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN MUST REMAIN A GOVERNMENT'S COMMIT A
GOVERNANCE COMMISSION IN THE CHARTER WITH ALL OF ITS CURRENT
AUTHORITY. CONVERTING IT TO AN ADVISORY
COMMITTEE WOULD STRIP ITS AUTHORITY.
WE CAN COMMUNITY VOICES AND UNDERMINE ITS PURPOSE.
THE RECOMMENDATIONS FROM THE COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK
FORCE IGNORED THE MANY COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO GAVE
PUBLIC COMMENT. AND SADLY THE TASK FORCE LACKED
DIVERSITY AND REPRESENTATION. >> COMMISSIONS MUST RETAIN
THEIR HIRING AND FIRING AUTHORITY.
THE MAYOR ALREADY HIRES THE DEPARTMENT HEADS.
WE JUST GET INVOLVED IN THE PROCESS AND IT ALSO ENSURES
TRANSPARENT AND COMMUNITY CENTERED LEADERSHIP AND GIVING
THE MAYOR SOLE AUTHORITY TO REMOVE COMMISSIONERS WITHOUT
CAUSE WOULD UNDERMINE THE INDEPENDENCE AND IT SETS A
DANGEROUS PRECEDENT. STRONG OVERSIGHT CHECKS
AND BALANCES COMMUNITY REPRESENTATION ARE ESSENTIAL TO
A HEALTHY DEMOCRACY. >> PLEASE DO NOT BE
SHORTSIGHTED OR ALLOW AUTHORITARIANISM TO TAKE ROOT
IN OUR CITY. >> YOU HAVE THE POWER.
NOW PLEASE HAVE THE COURAGE TO DO WHAT IS RIGHT FOR OUR
COMMUNITIES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, COMMISSIONER AND ARI FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. HELLO.
>> MY NAME IS OLIVIA HOFFMAN AND I'M HERE REPRESENTING
COMMUNITY FORWARD SAN FRANCISCO WHO ALSO CO-CHAIRS THE SAN
FRANCISCO WOMEN'S HOUSING COALITION WHICH RECENTLY
PRODUCED ONE OF THE LARGEST DATASETS ON WOMEN EXPERIENCE
IN HOMELESSNESS AND VIOLENCE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I WANT TO START BY SAYING THAT TODAY IS THE 70TH SESSION
OF THE U.N. COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN.
IT'S HAPPENING RIGHT NOW AT THE UNITED NATIONS HEADQUARTERS
IN NEW YORK CITY AND THE 2026 PRIORITY IS ENSURING
AND STRENGTHENING ACCESS TO JUSTICE FOR ALL WOMEN
AND GIRLS. FOCUSING ON REMOVING LEGAL
BARRIERS AND ENHANCING EQUALITY.
AND YET IN THIS ROOM RIGHT NOW WE'RE CONSIDERING REDUCING THE
POWER OF OUR VERY BODY TASKED WITH THE SAME THING THE
COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN.
THAT IS NOT STREAMLINING. WE CANNOT WEAKEN GENDER
OVERSIGHT WHEN WE ARE IN A GENDERED CRISIS.
THE DATA IN OUR CITYWIDE SURVEY THAT I MENTIONED BEFORE SHOWED
US THAT 74% OF WOMEN REPORTED EXPERIENCING VIOLENCE WHILE
UNHOUSED IN OUR CITY. IT ALSO SHOWED US THAT DOMESTIC
VIOLENCE IS THE NUMBER ONE DRIVER OF HOMELESSNESS IN THE
CITY. SAN FRANCISCO IS FACING A
GENDERED PUBLIC SAFETY CRISIS WEAKENING THE COMMISSION ON THE
STATUS OF WOMEN SENDS THE MESSAGE THAT GENDER BASED
VIOLENCE AND INEQUITY ARE NOT CORE GOVERNANCE PRIORITIES
IN THIS CITY. IF 74% OF WOMEN ARE
EXPERIENCING VIOLENCE WHILE UNHOUSED, THE ANSWER IS MORE
ACCOUNTABILITY NOT LESS. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU OLIVIA HOFMANN FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON COMMISSIONERS I
MEAN SORRY SUPERVISORS MY NAME IS AND EVERYWHERE I AM A
COMMISSIONER ON THE DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN AND I'M
HERE IN A PERSONAL CAPACITY TO URGE YOU NOT TO ACCEPT THE
RECOMMENDATION PUT FORTH BY THE STREAMLINING COMMISSION TASK
FORCE. >> I URGE YOU TO MEET WITH
CONSTITUENTS TO FURTHER UNDERSTAND THE IMPACTS
AND DESTABILIZATION THAT WILL HAPPEN SHOULD YOU PROCEED TO
ACCEPT THE RECOMMENDATIONS AS PRESENTED.
>> THESE RECOMMENDATIONS MIRROR A HARMFUL OR EXTREMELY HARMFUL
RHETORIC HAPPENING AT A NATIONAL SCALE AND I'M QUITE
FRANKLY SHOCKED THAT WE HAVE TO BE HERE WHILE I'M HERE
IN SOLIDARITY WITH OTHER FOLKS AS A LATINA, A CULTURAL
WORKER, I URGE YOU TO KEEP THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN AND KEEP THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION
IN THE CHARTER TO REDUCE THEM TO AN ADVISORY BODY.
IT LEAVES LITTLE AUTHORITY OR INCENTIVE FOR THE COMMUNITY TO
OFFER PUBLIC TESTIMONY ON ISSUES THAT CONCERN AND AFFECT
THEM. >> COMMUNITY COMMISSIONERS WILL
LACK THE ABILITY TO MAKE DECISIONS BASED ON THEIR NEEDS.
THIS MEANS THE PUBLIC WILL HAVE LESS ACCESS TO DECISION MAKERS
UNDERMINING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS WE LIVE IN A MOMENT
WHERE REPRODUCTIVE BODIES ARE UNDER ATTACK, WHERE WOMEN'S
VOICES ARE BEING SILENCED AND IN THIS MOMENT WE NEED
LEADERSHIP THAT DEEPLY UNDERSTANDS THE ROLE THAT ART
AND CULTURE PLAYS IN OUR SOCIETY BY HEALING IT
AND ADVANCING ADVANCING JOY IN CIVIC LIFE OUR PUBLIC
BUILDINGS, PUBLIC ART GRANT MAKING PROCESS RECEIVED
NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL ATTENTION AWARDS WE ARE A MODEL
OF BEST PRACTICES. >> THIS IS A HUGE DRIVER OF
CULTURAL TOURISM WHICH FILLS A GENERAL FUND AND THE HOTEL TAX
FUND. I URGE YOU TO KEEP THE
COMMISSIONS ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN IN THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS
COMMISSION IN THE CHARTER AND TO DO BETTER TO STAND UP
AND USE YOUR VOICE AND LIVED EXPERIENCE.
I KNOW MANY OF YOU KNOW IT AND I'M NOT SURE WHY WE'RE
STILL FIGHTING TO HAVE VISIBILITY WHERE SAN FRANCISCO
GOES THE COUNTRY FOLLOWS. REMEMBER THAT.
THANK YOU COMMISSIONER RIVERA FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> HI JENNIFER FRIEDEN BACH OF COALITION ON HOMELESSNESS.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. HOW DO YOU THINK SOCIAL CHANGE
HAPPENS? IT IS REALIZED OUT OF MOVEMENT
MANY OF THE INDEPENDENT OVERSIGHT BODIES GREW OUT OF
MOVEMENT AND CONTINUE TO ENSURE THE VISION OF THOSE MOVEMENTS
CONTINUE TO MOVE THE LONG TRADITION OF PARTICIPATORY
DEMOCRACY IN SAN FRANCISCO THE REALIZATION OF PEOPLE POWER IS
IN OUR VERY DNA. >> THESE RECOMMENDATIONS THEY
BURY ALL OF THAT THE HOMELESSNESS BODY SPECIFICALLY
THERE ARE THREE VERY HYPER FOCUSED BODIES FOCUSED ON VERY
IMPORTANT ISSUES WOULD BE ELIMINATED AND THE HOMELESS
OVERSIGHT COMMISSION WOULD WHICH DOESN'T HAVE TIME TO DO
WHAT THEY NEED TO DO NOW WOULD BE TAKING ON THOSE TASKS
AND WOULD BE MOVE WOULD HAVE THEIR CHARTERED AUTHORITY
REMOVED AND WOULD ONLY BE ADVISORY.
I WAS AROUND BEFORE WE HAD A HOMELESS OVERSIGHT COMMISSION.
>> IT WAS ONLY A LITTLE BIT AGO AND WE HAD AN ADVISORY BODY
AND IT WAS A JOKE. THERE WAS NO OVERSIGHT, NO
TRANSPARENCY AND I THINK YOU THINK WE STILL NEED OVERSIGHT
ON THIS ISSUE. >> PROP C HAS BEEN WILDLY
SUCCESSFUL BECAUSE IT WAS BUILT ON THE CONCEPT THAT THE
SMARTEST PERSON IN THE ROOM IS THE ROOM AND THAT HOMELESS
PEOPLE THEMSELVES EVEN KNOW THE BEST SOLUTIONS.
>> THESE RECOMMENDATIONS WOULD HALT THAT MOVEMENT TOWARDS
ENDING HOMELESSNESS AND INSTEAD CEMENT HOMELESS POLICY
IN POLITICAL WIN. >> HOMELESS PEOPLE ROSE UP TO
PASS PROP C BUT THEY ALSO DEMANDED STANDARDS IN OUR
SHELTER. >> DID YOU KNOW WE HAVE 50
UNLICENSED INSTITUTIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO?
>> YEAH THEY'RE CALLED SHELTERS.
WE FOUGHT FOR STANDARDS OF CARE BUT WITHOUT THE SHELTER
MONITORING COMMITTEE THAT'S LIKE THE TRUMP GUTTING THE
CIVIL RIGHTS AT THE DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE.
IT MEANS YOU HAVE RIGHTS ON PAPER AND PAPER ONLY WITHOUT
ENFORCEMENT THEY'RE MEANINGLESS STAFF CANNOT REPLACE THAT WORK.
>> OH, THANK YOU. THANK YOU, JENNIFER FRYDENBERG
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
I'M ALICE ROGERS. I'M PRESIDENT OF THE SOUTH
BEACH RINCON MISSION BAY NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION.
BUT I'M SPEAKING REALLY JUST PERSONAL COMMENTS.
I ACTUALLY AM HERE TO COMMEND THE PROCESS AND THE WORK THAT
THE TASK FORCE HAS DONE. >> I THINK SUPERVISOR CHERYL
ASKED AN IMPORTANT QUESTION HOW CAN WE BEST UTILIZE THIS REPORT
AND CHAIR HARRINGTON SUGGESTION THAT YOU GO AND LISTEN TO THE
THE DIALOG AROUND EACH ISSUE IS IT IS AN IMPORTANT BYPRODUCT OF
THIS PROCESS. I THE THE COMMISSION THE TASK
FORCE WERE VERY ACCESSIBLE THAT WE WE INVITED THEM TO OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION. THEY CAME EXPLAIN THE PROCESS
THEY WERE METICULOUS IN SETTING UP A FRAMEWORK IN IN INVITING
DISCUSSION AND INVITING INVITING PEOPLE TO COME BACK
AND REBUT A DECISION IF THEY FELT IT WAS IN APPROPRIATE AS
THEY DID IN A CASE WITH A CIC THAT I WAS ENGAGED WITH.
SO I THINK THEY REALLY THE BULK OF THE DECISIONS HELD
SEPARATELY I THINK THEY HAVE REALLY ENCOURAGED AND AN
IMPORTANT DIALOG TO HAPPEN AND THEY'VE INVITED THIS TO
CONTINUE SO THANK YOU. >> TASK FORCE THANK YOU FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS RANDY BLAUSTEIN.
SO I WAS AT THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION BUDGETARY HEARING
WHEN I WENT TO SUPPORT THE OFFICE OF TRANSGENDER
INITIATIVE BEFORE I GOT A CHANCE TO SPEAK I SAT THERE FOR
2.5 HOURS LISTENING TO ONE PERSON AFTER ANOTHER PLEAD FOR
THEIR NONPROFIT THAT SERVED THE MOST MARGINALIZED PEOPLE THAT
LIVE IN THIS CITY TO CONTINUE TO BE ABLE TO EXIST.
THEY WERE TASKED WITH A VERY LARGE BUDGET CUT CUTTING ACROSS
. THEY PUT UP A SLIDE OF THE
MAYOR'S PRIORITIES AND IT THE WAY IT READ TO ME WAS WE HAVE A
MAYOR WHO IS MORE CONCERNED WITH MAKING THE CITY LOOK
PRETTY AGAIN THAN SERVING THE NEEDS OF THE MOST MARGINALIZED
PEOPLE WHO LIVE HERE AND THE MAJORITY OF PEOPLE WHO SPOKE
WERE PEOPLE OF COLOR. SO I'M HERE TODAY TO TALK ABOUT
THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION REMAINING IN THE CHARTER ALONG
WITH ALL OF THE OTHER COMMISSIONS BECAUSE IT VARIED
DUE TO ADVISORY COMMITTEES WHERE ARE PEOPLE GOING TO GO?
WHERE ARE PEOPLE GOING TO GO TO BE ABLE TO VOICE.
PLEASE, PLEASE SUPPORT US PLEASE LET US CONTINUE TO DO
THE WORK WE DO. LET US CONTINUE TO SERVE THE
MOST MARGINALIZED PEOPLE WHO LIVE HERE WHERE ARE PEOPLE
GOING TO GO IF IT'S JUST THEY'RE JUST REDUCED TO
ADVISING ADVISORS AND I'M NOT COMFORTABLE WITH THIS PRESENT
MAYOR HAVING MORE POWER TO MAKE DECISIONS LIKE THIS.
QUITE HONESTLY, AFTER SEEING A LIST OF WHAT HIS PRIORITIES ARE
SO I IMPLORE YOU TO LEAVE THE CHARTER AS IT IS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. YOU WRITE THANK YOU
SUPERVISORS. I'M ROSLYN SCHMALZ, LONG TIME
NORTH BEACH ARTIST AND RECIPIENT OF MULTIPLE
GRANTS FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION TO AMPLIFY
AND DIRECT NORTH BEACH FIRST FRIDAYS ARTWALK IT WOULD BE
CRIMINAL TO STREAMLINE THE SABC AND REDUCE IT TO AN ADVISORY
BOARD. >> OF COURSE THIS PROBLEM
EXTENDS FAR BEYOND THIS WHITE WEALTHY NIMBY TASK FORCE WORKS
TASK FORCE'S WORK TO AN END UNCANNILY RESEMBLES LAST YEAR'S
NATIONAL PURGES IN THE ARTS AND HUMANITIES SCIENCES,
IMMIGRATION, HEALTH AND EDUCATION ALL IN THE NAME
OF EFFICIENCY. THE CITY IS BEING DODGED
AND ITS NON-DIVERSE TASK FORCE STINKS OF MUSK.
>> THIS CHARTER REFORM HAS OFTEN BEEN COMPARED TO PROJECT
2025 WITH ITS WILD REDUCTION OF POWERS TO YOU.
OUR LEGISLATIVE BODY IS MASSIVE RE APPROPRIATION OF VOTER
APPROVED FUNDS WITHOUT VOTER CONSENT AND ITS EXTREME GIFT OF
MORE YOU UNILATERAL POWER TO THE MAYOR AND HIS EXECUTIVE
TEAM REDUCING COMMISSIONS TO ADVISORY BODIES STRIP THEM OF
ANY MUSCLE FOR EXAMPLE SFA C DECISIONS MADE BY FORMER
COMMISSIONERS WOULD INSTEAD BE MADE BY THE MAYOR AND YOU EVEN
THOUGH NONE OF YOU OR THE TASK FORCE IS AN ARTIST THAT IS JUST
MORE UNQUALIFIED AUTHORITARIANISM
AUTHORITARIANISM REPLACING PUBLIC INPUT AND OVERSIGHT IT'S
TOO CLOSE TO THE WE ARE LIVING AT THE NATIONAL LEVEL
AND EXPERIENCE MATTERS. IT'S THEFT.
IN 2018 VOTERS APPROVED PROPOSITIONS ALLOCATING OVER
$25 MILLION FOR THE ARTS AND 44 HOUSING.
>> THESE SET ASIDES ARE OURS REAPPROPRIATE FUNDS THE VOTERS
APPROVED SEEMS TO BE CALLING A CALLING CARD NOT ONLY OF THE
TRUMP ADMINISTRATION BUT ALSO OF LURIE'S AND AS SAN FRANCISCO
START STARTS TO BEHAVE MORE AND MORE LIKE WASHINGTON D.C.
ARTISTS AND ACTIVISTS ARE WAKING UP AND PAYING ATTENTION
TO WHO IS VOTING HOW THIS YEAR. SO AS AN ARTIST I PROMISE TO
MAKE IT MY 2026 MAGNUM OPUS TO MAKE SURE EVERYBODY KNOWS WHO
VOTES HERE AND AGAINST WRONG INDEPENDENT ARTS LEADERSHIP
AND ESSENTIAL PUBLIC COMMISSION OVERSIGHT.
>> EVERYBODY IS GOING TO FIND OUT WHERE YOU STAND.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE. THANK YOU.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS REYNOLDS ACABA, EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR FROM 2015 TO
2019 OF THE FRIENDS OF THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN. >> I'M HERE IN SUPPORT OF
KEEPING THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN IN THE CITY
CHARTER AND PRESERVING THIS CITY'S ELIGIBLE ABILITY TO ACT
AND FOCUS AND FOLLOW THROUGH ON ISSUES THAT AFFECT REAL
PEOPLE'S SAFETY AND LIVES. >> OVER TIME SAN FRANCISCO HAS
BUILT STRONGER, MORE CONNECTED RESPONSES TO DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
MAKING IT EASIER FOR SURVIVORS TO FIND HELP AND HARDER FOR
CASES TO FALL THROUGH THE CRACKS.
THE CITY HAS ALSO TAKEN MEANINGFUL STEPS TO CONFRONT
HUMAN TRAFFICKING NOT JUST BY RAISING AWARENESS BUT BY
IMPROVING COORDINATION AND PROTECTION.
MORE IMPORTANTLY, WOMEN SAFETY HAS REMAINED A VISIBLE PUBLIC
RESPONSIVE BULLET AND SOMETHING THAT'S NOT SOMETHING THAT'S
HANDLED IN ISOLATION. >> THAT KIND OF PROGRESS DIDN'T
HAPPEN ON ITS OWN. IT REQUIRED THE COMMISSION ON
THE STATUS OF WOMEN TO SIT ACROSS DEPARTMENTS AND ASK HARD
QUESTIONS AND MAKE SURE COMMITMENTS MOVE FROM PROMISES
TO PRACTICE. WHEN THAT ROLE IS REDUCED
ADVISORY ONLY THE WORK BECOMES EASIER TO OVERLOOK AND HARDER
TO SUSTAIN IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN HAS MADE A NAME FOR ITSELF
BY TAKING GENDER EQUITY SERIOUSLY IN HOW DECISIONS ARE
MADE NOT JUST IN WHAT IT SAID BUT IN WHAT IT GETS MEASURED
AND IMPROVES THROUGH THE LENS OF CEDA THE COMMISSION, THE
CONVENTION ON THE ELIMINATION OF ALL FORMS OF DISCRIMINATION
AGAINST WOMEN. THAT COMMITMENT HAS TRANSLATED
INTO POLICIES AND PRACTICES THAT MOVE OUR CITY INTO WHERE
EQUITY IS NOT ASPIRATIONAL BUT OPERATIONAL KEEPING.
>> WE KNOW THAT WHAT WE KNOW WHAT WORKS.
WOMEN, GIRLS AND GENDER EXPANSIVE YOUTH ARE SAFER
AND HAVE REAL ACCESS TO OPPORTUNITY.
THEIR BEEN THE BENEFIT. >> THANK YOU FOR AN ELISA COVER
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI MY NAME'S KAREN WOO. HELLO.
NERVOUS? KAREN ADAMS.
I'M THE DIRECTOR OF PROGRAMS WITH HOMELESS YOUTH ALLIANCE.
WE'RE A SMALL NONPROFIT IN THE HAY ASHBURY SERVING YOUTH
AND YOUNG ADULTS EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS.
>> I'M HERE TODAY SPEAKING DIRECTLY IN REGARDS TO ENSURING
THE PRESERVATION OF THE SHELTER, MONITORING COMMITTEE
THE SHELTER GRIEVANCE ADVISORY COMMITTEE.
OUR CITY OUR HOME OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE AND THE LOCAL
HOMELESS COORDINATING BOARD. >> PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS ARE TOO OFTEN SPOKEN ABOUT MANAGED AND MOVED
RATHER THAN HEARD, RESPECTED AND INCLUDED.
>> THE CONSOLIDATION OF THESE COMMITTEES REFLECTS A SIMILAR
EFFORT TO DISEMPOWER OUR MOST VULNERABLE COMMUNITY MEMBERS.
EFFORTS TO END THE DIVERSITY OF STRATEGIES NECESSARY TO ADDRESS
THE DIVERSITY OF NEEDS OF THIS POPULATION IS UNACCEPTABLE.
>> TRANSPARENCY IN CITY GOVERNMENT IS NOT OPTIONAL.
IT IS THE FOUNDATION OF TRUST AND DEMOCRACY.
POLICIES FUNDING DECISIONS AND ENFORCEMENT PRACTICES MUST
BE CLEAR, ACCESSIBLE AND ACCOUNTABLE TO THE VERY
PEOPLE THEY IMPACT MOST. WITHOUT TRANSPARENCY SYSTEMS
BECOME BARRIERS INSTEAD OF BRIDGES.
AUTONOMY IS A BASIC HUMAN RIGHT.
NO COMMUNITIES SHOULD BE STRIPPED OF THEIR ABILITY TO
ACCESS APPROPRIATE SPACES AND MAKE DECISIONS ABOUT THEIR
LIVES SIMPLY BECAUSE THEY LACK HOUSING.
>> TRUE SUPPORT IN DEMOCRACY EMPOWERS CHOICE.
>> IT DOES NOT IMPOSE CONTROL AND ACCESS TO SELF ADVOCACY IS
ESSENTIAL. PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS MUST HAVE REAL OPPORTUNITIES TO SPEAK FOR
THEMSELVES. SHAPE POLICIES AND HOLD
INSTITUTIONS ACCOUNTABLE. AND I'LL SAY THAT AGAIN PEOPLE
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS MUST HAVE REAL OPPORTUNITIES TO
SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES TO SHAPE POLICIES AND HOLD INSTITUTIONS
ACCOUNTABLE. IF WE ARE SERIOUS ABOUT EQUITY
AND JUSTICE THEN OUR CITY MUST COMMIT TO TRANSPARENCY,
AUTONOMY, DIGNITY AND THE POWER OF SELF ADVOCACY FOR ALL
INCLUDING PEOPLE WHO EXPERIENCE HOMELESSNESS.
AT A TIME OF RISING AUTHORITARIANISM AND THE
NORMALIZATION OF PUNITIVE APPROACHES TO POVERTY, THESE
PRINCIPLES ARE MORE URGENT THAN EVER.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU KAREN ADAMS FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. PLEASE WELCOME.
GOOD EVENING. POOR SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS CARLA JACKSON LANE. I AM A FORMER COMMISSIONER ON
THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN.
I WAS UNDER FEINSTEIN'S ADMINISTRATION WHEN THE
COMMISSION WAS FOUNDED IN 1975. I AM ALSO CURRENTLY A
COMMISSIONER ON THE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH COMMISSION AND I JUST
RETURNED FROM NEW YORK FROM SEATTLE IN TERMS OF THE NGO
AND COMMISSION FOR WOMEN KSW 70.
WHAT I WANT TO SAY TO YOU IS THAT IT IS IMPERATIVE THAT WE
ACTUALLY STAND BY ALL THE WORK THAT HAS BEEN DONE BY THE
COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN.
>> ORIGINALLY WE FOUGHT FOR SEXUAL HARASSMENT ON THE JOB SO
WE HAD SITUATIONS WHERE THERE WERE ACTUAL CASES THAT WERE
BEING INVOLVED WITHIN A DEPARTMENT MULTIPLE DEPARTMENTS
OF THE CITY AND COUNTY AND THE COMMISSIONERS AS WOMEN FOUGHT
TO TO SET UP A ACTUAL PROCESS AND THEN LATER ON WAS ACTUALLY
PART OF THE PROCESS THAT DID THE CLARIFICATION.
PEOPLE NOW ACTUALLY YOU KNOW, THEY GET THEIR PUNITIVE
DAMAGES. I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO STATE THAT
AT THE TIME WHEN THE COMMISSION WAS I WAS IN COMMISSION WE WERE
UP UNDER THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION AND SO I WANTED TO
GIVE A DIRECT PLEAD FOR THE FACT THAT WE NEED TO KEEP THE
CHARTER FOR BOTH THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION AS WELL AS
THE COMMISSION AS THE WOMEN. >> I WANTED TO SAY THAT
IN TERMS OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO I HAVE BEEN A
RESIDENT SINCE 1960. >> MY FATHER JAMES EARL JACKSON
SENIOR WAS 35 YEARS IN THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT
AND THERE WAS ALWAYS BEEN ISSUES WITH A CONSENT DECREE
MOVING FORWARD WHERE WE NEEDED THE ASHEVILLE POLICE
COMMISSION. AND I THINK THAT AS SUPERVISORS
AND ALL OF THE LOVE AND CARE THAT YOU HAVE FOR THIS CITY
THAT YOU WILL STAND UP AND TAKE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> IS THIS ON? YES.
>> WELCOME. SUPERVISORS.
>> I ASKED EACH ONE OF YOU TO LOOK WITHIN YOUR OWN SELF TO
LOOK WITHIN YOUR OWN BODY. YOU ARE MADE OF SO MANY
DIFFERENT TISSUES. A LOT OF YOUR TISSUES ARE
DISGUSTING. >> I'LL GIVE YOU AN EXAMPLE.
>> THE LIVER. >> IT PURIFIES ALL OF THE WHAT
WASTE MATERIAL IN YOUR BLOOD SYSTEM.
I ASK YOU THIS QUESTION. WOULD YOU OPTIMIZE YOUR LIVER
WHICH PART OF YOUR BODY WILL YOU OPTIMIZE?
WHICH PART OF YOUR BODY WILL YOU DO AWAY WITH YOUR FEET?
>> SO POOR YOU. I ASKED YOU WELL YOU CUT OFF
YOUR FEET SO IT DOESN'T HAVE TO TOUCH THE NASTY GROUND THAT WE
WALK ON. >> >> HOW DARE YOU EVEN
CONSIDER OH HOW DARE YOU CONSIDER?
>> NOT UNLESS YOU'RE FROM MARS. NOT UNLESS YOU'RE FROM SOME
OTHER ENTITY FROM OUTER SPACE. >> HOW DARE YOU?
HOW DARE YOU? HOW DARE YOU?
HOW DARE YOU? >> THANK YOU.
>> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HELLO. MY NAME IS JASON WYMAN.
I AM AN ARTIST AND SMALL BUSINESS OWNER HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> LIVING IN 99.
I WANT TO COME BACK TO TWO WORDS THAT I HEARD EARLIER
IN THE NIGHT DURING THE PRESENTATION EARLIER IN THE DAY
DURING THE PRESENTATION. AND THOSE TWO WORDS WERE POWER
AND TRUST. WE'RE BEING ASKED TO HAVE A
WHOLE LOT OF TRUST AND A PROCESS THAT ONLY TOOK A YEAR
VERSUS GENERATIONS OF FIGHTING FOR OVERSIGHT
AND ACCOUNTABILITY. >> THAT SEEMS LIKE LOPSIDED
POWER ESPECIALLY WHEN WE'RE TOLD THAT WE NEED TO TRUST
THOSE IN POWER. >> I REMEMBER RECENTLY THE
CONTROVERSY OF MAYOR BREED ASKING POLICE COMMISSIONER
CARTER OVER STONE TO RESIGN. THERE WAS RIGHTFUL OUTRAGE OVER
THAT OVERREACH OF THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH AND THAT EXACT SAME
THING IS HAPPENING HERE TODAY AND THAT EXACT SAME OUTRAGE
OUTRAGE IS BEING EXPERIENCED HERE IN THIS AUDIENCE TODAY.
>> AND I HOPE ALL OF THE SUPERVISORS HERE THAT I'M
REMINDED OF A PHOTO OF HARVEY MILK THAT I SAW IN THE HALLWAYS
HERE WHERE HE HAS A SIGN THAT SAYS AN INJURY TO ONE IS AN
INJURY TO ALL. >> THIS REFORM PROCESS IS
INJURING MORE THAN ONE. >> IT IS INJURING MANY
COMMUNITIES THAT HAVE BEEN LEFT OUT HISTORICALLY
AND SYSTEMICALLY FROM PUBLIC POWER AND PUBLIC PROCESS.
>> AND IT IS IN SEARCH OF A SOLUTION THAT IS CANCEL
SEDATING POWER IN THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH.
>> THAT'S NOT SAN FRANCISCO. THAT'S NOT WHAT WE SHOULD BE
DOING. THAT'S NOT MY INTRODUCTION TO
THIS CITY AND CIVIC ENGAGEMENT WHICH WAS WAY BACK AT THE
BEGINNING OF THE FIRST CHILDREN'S AMENDMENT MOVEMENT.
>> AND IT'S SAD TO BE HERE TODAY TO FIGHT FOR WHAT WE'VE
FOUGHT FOR FOR GENERATIONS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS JILL MANTON. I WAS A LONG TIME STAFF MEMBER
OF THE ARTS COMMISSION MANAGING THE PUBLIC ART PROGRAM
AND OVERSEEING THE CIVIC DESIGN COMMITTEE.
AND I'M HERE TO SAVE AND PRESERVE TWO IMPORTANT
FUNCTIONS AND SERVICES PROVIDED BY THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS
COMMISSION. LEAVING SAN FRANCISCO ARTS
COMMISSION IN THE CHARTER IS A PERFUNCTORY GESTURE WHICH MEANS
LITTLE IF ALL OF THE ARTS COMMISSION FUNCTIONS ARE MOVED
TO THE ADMIN CODE. >> THIS CHANGE WILL NEGATIVELY
IMPACT AT LEAST TWO ARTS COMMISSION PROGRAMS TWO OF
WHICH I'LL TALK ABOUT THE CIVIC DESIGN REVIEW AND THE PUBLIC
ART PROGRAM. >> THESE TWO PROGRAMS ARE WELL
COORDINATED AND HAVE AN INTEGRAL RELATIONSHIP TO ONE
ANOTHER. >> THE 1932 CHARTER MANDATES
THAT THE ARTS COMMISSION SHALL REVIEW THE DESIGN OF ANY
STRUCTURE PLACED ON PUBLIC PROPERTY TO ENSURE THE QUALITY
OF SAN FRANCISCO'S BUILT ENVIRONMENT.
REVIEW IS PERFORMED BY HIGHLY QUALIFIED ARCHITECTS
AND LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTS APPOINTED TO THE ARTS
COMMISSION TO SERVE US AS COMMISSIONERS ON THE CIVIC
DESIGN COMMITTEE. CIVIC DESIGN APPROVAL IS
REQUIRED FOR A BUILDING TO EVEN GET A BUILDING PERMIT IN THE
CITY. >> AND JUST FOR YOUR
INFORMATION ANNUALLY CIVIC DESIGN REVIEWS CAPITAL PROJECTS
TOTALING IN THE BILLIONS OF DOLLARS.
IT'S A VERY IMPORTANT RESPONSIBILITY.
>> AN UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCE OF MAKING CIVIC DESIGN ADVISORY IF
IT'S MOVED TO THE ADMIN CODE IS THAT IT COULD HARM OR EVEN
DISABLE THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE CITY'S ART ENRICHMENT
ORDINANCE WHICH WAS ESTABLISHED IN 1969.
THIS REQUIRES 2% OF THE CONSTRUCTION COST OF THE CITY'S
CAPITAL IMPROVEMENT PROJECTS TO BE ALLOCATED FOR PUBLIC ART.
>> HOWEVER, AS AN ORDINANCE THERE WAS NO PENALTY NOR A FINE
FOR NONCOMPLIANCE AND NO WAY TO ENSURE COMPLIANCE UNTIL THE
ARTS COMMISSION ESTABLISHED AN INTERNAL POLICY THAT
ARCHITECTURAL PROJECTS COULD NOT BE CALENDARED FOR CIVIC
DESIGN REVIEW UNTIL THEY ALLOCATED THEIR 2%.
>> THUS EARLY ACCESS ALLOWS THE ARTS COMMISSION TO PLAN PUBLIC
ART AS THANK YOU JOE MANTON FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> I OPPOSE THE MAYOR AND THE
COMMISSION STREAMLINING TASK FORCE ELIMINATING OR WEAKENING
THE COMMISSIONS THAT GIVE CRITICALLY NECESSARY OVERSIGHTS
TO THE POLICE AND SHERIFFS. I OPPOSE THE SAME THING BEING
DONE TO COMMISSIONS THAT GIVE A VOICE AND INFLUENCE FROM
IGNORED, MARGINALIZED OR DISCRIMINATED FOLKS LIKE THE
HOMELESS DISABLED PEOPLE OF COLOR, LGBTQ PLUS FOLKS YOUTH
AND WOMEN. >> I ACTUALLY PROPOSE A NEW
COMMISSION CALLED THE MAYORAL OVERSIGHT COMMISSION WHERE THE
MAYOR AND WEALTHY WHITE MAN WILL WEAR A BODY CAM WHEN HE
INTERACTS WITH HOMELESS PEOPLE ON THE STREETS.
NOW I'M AGAINST BODYCAMS BUT I'M WILLING TO COMPROMISE HERE
AS WE LEARNED SINCE MARCH 5TH, THE MAYOR LIKE THE POLICE WILL
LIE ABOUT HOW THEY TREAT BLACK AND HOMELESS PEOPLE AND SO WE
MUST OVERSEE THEIR ACTIONS SO AS TO HOLD THEM ACCOUNTABLE
WHEN THEY DO HARM. THE MAYOR HAS BEEN UNAPOLOGETIC
AND IS SPREADING A LIE ABOUT HOW HIS SPEEDY BODYGUARD CAME
INTO PHYSICAL CONTACT WITH THE BLACK HOMELESS MAN IN THE
TENDERLOIN AND NOW DUE TO THE MAYOR'S INSTIGATOR INTERACTIONS
THE TWO VICTIMS FACE CHARGES DROPPED THE CHARGES BROOKE
JENKINS. THE MAYOR HAS EXPRESSED NO
REGRETS AND EVEN IN A MARCH 11TH INTERVIEW WITH THE
CHRONICLE STATES THAT HE PLANS TO CONTINUE HIS SPONTANEOUS
STREET CHECK INS. >> I DID IT AGAIN THIS MORNING,
HE SAID. SOUNDS LIKE IT'S THE MAYOR THAT
HAS AN INSATIABLE APPETITE FOR INTIMIDATING UNPROTECTED
HOMELESS FOLKS WITHOUT OFFERING REAL SOLUTIONS LIKE REAL
HOUSING OR BASIC INCOME. THE MAYOR ALSO SAID HE NEEDS TO
SEE QUOTE WHAT OUR SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS, OUR FAMILIES
AND OUR CHILDREN ARE GOING THROUGH.
WHAT ABOUT WHAT OUR HOMELESS PEOPLE ARE GOING THROUGH PEOPLE
WITHOUT A HOME? DID YOU KNOW THAT BLACK PEOPLE
ARE ONLY TWO 6% OF THE CITY'S POPULATION BUT ACCOUNT FOR 38%
OF HOMELESS PEOPLE OR THAT TRANS PEOPLE AN EVEN SMALLER
PERCENTAGE? SAN FRANCISCO ACCOUNTS FOR 9%
OF HOMELESS PEOPLE. NOW IMMIGRANTS CAN'T FIND
HOUSING ANYWHERE AND THE MAYOR USES A TWO HOUR PARKING
LIMIT TO TERRORIZE THOSE FORTUNATE ENOUGH TO HAVE RVS TO
LIVE IN. >> I ASKED THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO NOT ENACT UNAPOLOGETICALLY RACIST,
CLASSIST, PHOBIC AND SEXIST CHANGES TO OUR COMMISSIONS.
>> THANK YOU LIAM MCGEEVER FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> HELLO EVERYONE. MY NAME IS BRANDY.
I'M FROM CULLMAN ADVOCATES. I WANT TO CHECK WHAT THEY SAID
AND I ALSO WANT TO EXPRESS MY SUPPORT FOR THE YOUTH
COMMISSION AND ALL THE COMMISSIONS THAT I THINK HAVE
THE INTERESTS OF OUR CITY'S YOUNG PEOPLE AND I KNOW THAT
THAT INCLUDES THE INDEPENDENT OVERSIGHT OF OUR POLICE
COMMISSION. >> AND I JUST KNOW THAT A VOTE
FOR PROP E WAS NOT A VOTE AGAINST INDEPENDENT CIVILIAN
OVERSIGHT, ESPECIALLY IN THE CASE OF THE POLICE COMMISSION.
THIS IS NOT A REDUNDANT COMMISSION AND IT DOES NOT HAVE
REDUNDANT POWER AS IT STANDS. THIS IS ACTUALLY AN OBLIGATORY
COMMISSION IS THE LEAST THAT WE COULD BE DOING AND IT IS YOUR
OBLIGATION TO PROTECT AND PRESERVE THIS COMMISSION
ESPECIALLY KNOWING THAT CIVILIANS HAVE LOST THEIR LIVES
AT THE HANDS OF LAW ENFORCEMENT.
SO WHY WOULD WE BE PUTTING AT RISK THE INDEPENDENCE OF
CIVILIAN OVERSIGHT RIGHT NOW? >> PROPOSALS COMING OUT OF THE
COMMISSION ABOUT A STREAMLINING PROCESS WOULD TAKE THE
AUTHORITY AWAY FROM THE COMMUNITY AND HAND IT TO THE
MAYOR. THAT IS NOT STREAMLINE.
THAT IS A TRANSFERENCE OF POWER.
AND THE TASK FORCE SAID IN THEIR PRESENTATION EARLIER
THAT ACCOUNTABILITY WAS A GUIDING PRINCIPLE FOR THEIR
JUST FOR THEIR RECOMMENDATIONS .
BUT THEIR FINAL RECOMMENDATIONS THAT THEY TALKED ABOUT TODAY
ARE CONTRADICTORY AND ANTITHETICAL TO THOSE
GUIDELINES. SO WHAT IS THE REAL MOTIVATION
BEHIND THESE RECOMMENDATIONS? >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, BRANDY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> HELLO EVERYONE. MY NAME IS RACHEL JONES.
I AM A YOUTH JUSTICE DIRECTOR AT COMMON BUT MORE SO I AM A
SAN FRANCISCO BORN AND RAISED NATIVE.
I HAVE MULTIPLE GENERATIONS AS WELL AS SIX DAUGHTERS THAT
ENJOY THE LUXURIES OF LIVING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND WHEN I LOOK AROUND MY CITY I DON'T SEE MY CITY.
I SEE WHAT MILLIONS AND BILLIONS OF DOLLARS HAVE
GIVEN TO MY CITY AND I DON'T WANT TO REPEAT WHAT MY
COUNTERPART HAS SAID. SO I'M GOING TO ASK YOU TO LOOK
WITHIN YOURSELF AND LOOK WITHIN THESE CHARTER PAPERS AND SEE
WHO EXACTLY IS TARGETED, WHO EXACTLY WE'RE SPEAKING ABOUT.
BECAUSE WHEN WE'RE IN A ROOM AND WE'RE SPEAKING ABOUT WOMEN
CHILDREN AND HOMELESSNESS, WE'RE TALKING ABOUT THE MOST
VULNERABLE POPULATIONS OF OUR CITY.
>> AND WHEN WE DISMISS UNTIL THE GUARDRAILS AND THE SAFETY
ISSUES THAT WE HAVE IN PLACE THAT WE'VE BEEN FIGHTING FOR
FOR DECADES, THERE'S A REAL PROBLEM IN THE ROOM.
>> AND I'LL JUST ENDED WITH A VERY SMALL QUOTE THAT MY
HOMEGIRL ANGELA DAVIS LOVES TO SAY AND THESE ARE FROM MY
PEOPLE BEHIND ME MORE SO THAN YOU GUYS IN FRONT OF ME.
>> THE POWERFUL DON'T GIVE UP POWER BECAUSE WE ASK NICELY.
LET ME SAY THAT AGAIN. >> THE POWERFUL DON'T GIVE UP
POWER BECAUSE WE ASK NICELY FOR THE CHANGE IS WHEN RESISTANCE
BECOMES TOO COSTLY TO IGNORE. AND RIGHT NOW THE RESISTANCE IS
KEEPING TABS. SO I JUST WANT YOU TO KNOW THE
RESISTANCE WILL BE COSTLY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, RACHEL JONES FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> PRESIDENT MANDOLIN SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS TOM HORNE. I'M VICE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD
OF TRUSTEES OF THE WAR MEMORIAL.
I'M HERE WITH THE PRESIDENT OF MY BOARD, DIANE WILSEY AS WELL
AS TRUSTEE JOYCE NEWSTEAD. THERE ARE THREE CHARITABLE
TRUSTS DEPARTMENTS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
FINE ARTS COMMISSION, THE ASIAN ART MUSEUM AND THE WAR MEMORIAL
AND PERFORMING ARTS CENTER. ALL OF THEM COME OUT OF A LOVED
BY PEOPLE WHO SUPPORTED THE VARIOUS ORGANIZATIONS TO WANT
THE ARTS TO BE IMPORTANT IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND IT DATES BACK TO THE GOLD RUSH AND IF YOU LOOK AT HOW AT
THE CHARTER PROPOSALS IN THE STREAMLINED TASK FORCE
PROPOSALS, THE WAR MEMORIAL HAS BEEN CUT OUT FROM THE OTHER TWO
CHARITABLE TRUSTS DEPARTMENTS. AND IT'S NOT EVEN CLEAR EXACTLY
WHY BECAUSE WE ALL SUPPORT WE ALL SUPPORT THE ARTS AND WE ALL
ARE CHARITABLE TRUSTS. THE LOGIC HAS BEEN THAT WE ARE
A PROPERTY MANAGEMENT COMPANY BUT THAT'S REALLY NOT THE CASE
. THE WAR MEMORIAL WELCOMES ABOUT
A MILLION PEOPLE A YEAR. WE PUT ON OVER 900
PERFORMANCES. WE HAVE SEVEN PERFORMING ARTS
VENUES AND WE MAKE AN ECONOMIC CONTRIBUTION IMPACT TO THE CITY
OF SOME $350 MILLION ANNUALLY. THE IDEA OF LOSING THE AUTONOMY
ME OF THE WAR MEMORIAL WOULD MAKE US LIKE THE KENNEDY CENTER
IN NEW YORK AND I DREAD TO SEE SOMEONE ELSE'S NAME ABOVE THE
WAR MEMORIAL OPERA HOUSE. SO WE JUST ASK THAT THE WAR
MEMORIAL BE TREATED IN THE SAME WAY THAT THE OTHER TWO
CHARITABLE TRUST DEPARTMENTS ARE.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
TRUSTEE TOM HORN. >> OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
COME ON UP. >> MY NAME'S CHERYL JACKSON.
PEOPLE OF THE NATION WE'RE AT A CRITICAL JUNCTURE WHEN THE
PEOPLE OF THIS NATION CAN'T UPHOLD CIVIL DEMOCRACY, WHEN IT
DOESN'T HAVE CHECKS AND BALANCES.
>> THE OVERSIGHT IS TO ENSURE JUSTICE AND TO ENSURE THAT WE
HAVE AN ADDITIONAL SET OF EYES WHEN SYSTEMS IN PLACE ARE NOT
SHOWING US JUSTICE. >> AND I CAN TELL YOU FROM A
LIVED EXPERIENCE. >> DISHEARTENING TO SEE HOW
MANY POLICE REPORTS DOES IT TAKE TO SEE JUSTICE?
>> WE SIT HERE IN A ROOM FULL OF PEOPLE ADVOCATING DAY IN AND
DAY OUT FOR THE PEOPLE THEY REPRESENT.
THAT'S BLACK WOMEN. THAT'S WOMEN, THAT'S LGBTQ.
I A PLUS I'LL SAY THEM ALL BECAUSE I DO REMEMBER TRANS.
>> THE MOST IMPORTANT THING YOU WILL HEAR TODAY IS HOW
IMPORTANT IT IS TO UPHOLD JUSTICE IN COMMISSION SYSTEMS.
>> SHAME ON YOU FOR HAVING A CONVERSATION AND CONTEMPLATING
IT. >> SHAME ON YOU FOR WASTING
THESE PEOPLE'S TIME WHEN THEY SHOULD BE SERVING THE PEOPLE
FALLING THROUGH THE CRACKS. >> SOME OF YOU SITTING HERE
IN OUR FACES SAYING THAT YOU UPHOLD THE SYSTEM THAT IS
SUPPOSED TO BE WORKING FOR US. >> YOU HAVE FAILED.
>> RETHINK HOW YOU SEE JUSTICE IN THIS SYSTEM.
BUT RETHINK ABOUT HOW YOU UPLIFT AND EMPOWER PEOPLE HERE
IN THIS CITY. >> DO NOT LET THEM DOWN.
YOU KNOW I ONLY COME WHEN THERE'S SOMETHING WRONG.
THE ONE THING I'M GOING TO LEAVE YOU WITH TODAY YOU'RE
STANDING UP WITHOUT A COMMISSION.
>> SO ARE YOU STILL A CITY BUT STILL UPHOLDING JUSTICE.
THANK YOU, CHERYL JACKSON FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> MY NAME IS MICHAEL KYLE.
I'M COMING AS A FIELD REPRESENTATIVE FROM SEIU 10 TO
1. I JUST WANT TO START WITH
POINTING OUT IN TERMS OF THE WORD EFFICIENCY.
WE'VE SEEN AS I PLAY WITH THOSE IN DC WE'VE SEEN I PLAY THE
TRUMP. IT IS A FALSE FLAG.
THIS IS NOT A CONVERSATION ABOUT EFFICIENCY.
IT'S A CONVERSATION ABOUT CONSOLIDATING POWER FOR THE
MAYOR A MAYOR WHO BOUGHT HIS WAY INTO HIS POSITION TO BEGIN
WITH. SO AS I SAID 10 TO 1 WE ARE
OPPOSING THE SUGGESTED RECOMMENDATIONS THAT A
STREAMLINING COMMISSION TERM LIMITS HARM INSTITUTIONAL
KNOWLEDGE OF VOLUNTEER EXPERTS, IMPORTANT COMMITTEES, CHANGING
COMMISSIONERS FROM OUR TO FROM CORES TO OUT WILL GREATLY
EXPAND THE POWER OF THE MAYOR IS AN ANTI LABOR PRACTICE
MANY OF OUR COMMISSIONERS DICTATE HOW WORKERS ARE TREATED
IN OUR RIGHTS PROTECTED. AND THESE CHANGES ERODE THE
POWER AND RIGHTS OF OUR MEMBERS.
SO AS THE LARGEST PUBLIC SECTOR UNION IN SAN FRANCISCO WE URGE
YOU TO VOTE NO AND PROTECT OUR WORKERS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MICHAEL KYLE FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTER A NUMBER OF SUPERVISORS.
>> MY NAME IS BLANCA CATALAN AND I'M HERE WITH GOVERNMENT
ADVOCATES AND I'M HERE TODAY IN SUPPORT OF KEEPING THE SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE COMMISSION OR BLACK AND BROWN COMMUNITIES
NEED A SYSTEM THAT ENSURES REAL ACCOUNTABLE PD WHERE COMMUNITY
VOICES TRULY MATTER AND WHERE DECISION S ARE NOT MADE BEHIND
CLOSED DOORS. OUR FAMILIES DESERVE
TRANSPARENCY ESPECIALLY BECAUSE THE DATA SHOWS DISPARITIES
STILL EXIST. REPORTS FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
POLICE DEPARTMENT AND THE PUBLIC DEFENDERS OFFICE SHOWS
THAT BLACK AND BROWN DRIVERS HAVE BEEN FAR MORE LIKELY TO BE
STOP SEARCHED AND SUBJECT TO USE OF FORCE COMPARED TO OTHER
COMMUNITIES. >> WHILE RECENT POLICIES LIKE
THE PROTECT STUFF'S BAN HAVE STARTED TO REDUCE SOME OF THESE
DISPARITIES, THIS PROGRESS IS STILL FRAGILE.
THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE COMMISSION EXCEEDS BECAUSE OF
YEARS OF COMMUNITY ADVOCACY DEMANDING ACCOUNTABILITY
AND END OF THESE INEQUITIES. >> WE IN THESE COMMISSIONS NOW
RISK UNDOING THAT PROGRESS IN SILENCING THE COMMUNITIES
MOST IMPACTED BY OVERPOLICING. WE CANNOT GO BACKWARDS.
I REFUSE TO PROTECT THE POLICE COMMISSION'S INDEPENDENCE
AND AUTHORITY TO ENSURE SAFETY WITH RESPECT FOR EVERY VOTE FOR
EVERYONE IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER HI, MY NAME IS
ZACH. >> I'M A COMMUNITY VOLUNTEER
AND ORGANIZER. >> SO ALL THESE CUTS HAVE BEEN
MADE ON THE GUISE OF EFFICIENCY ,SEE?
>> AND REALLY WHAT'S INEFFICIENT IS THE FACT THAT WE
HAVE MEETINGS LIKE THIS EVERY WEEK TWICE A WEEK IN THE MIDDLE
OF THE WORKING DAY SO WE DON'T HAVE VERY MUCH DEMOCRATIC
PARTICIPATION. >> ON THE CONVENIENCE OF YOUR
WORK SCHEDULES AND NOT ON THE MASSES WORK SCHEDULES SO
THEY'RE NOT ABLE TO PARTICIPATE.
WHAT'S INEFFICIENT IS THE FACT THAT YOU GUYS HAVE JOBS HERE
THAT YOU COULD HAVE LIKE $275,000 A YEAR OF TAXPAYER
MONEY TO RUBBER STAMP THE WHATEVER THE MAYOR OF POLICIES
WANT TO BE. >> MAYBE WE SHOULD JUST
ELIMINATE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ENTIRELY.
>> ANYHOW, I'M HERE TO PROTEST ANY SORT OF ELIMINATION OF
HOMELESS OVERSIGHT COMMITTEES NOT JUST THE HOMELESS OVERSIGHT
COMMITTEE BUT SPECIFICALLY THE SHELTER AGREEMENTS ADVISORY
COUNCIL AND SHELTER MONITORING BOARD.
>> I DON'T KNOW A WHOLE LOT ABOUT HOW ALL THESE THINGS WORK
AND NUTS AND BOLTS BUT I DO KNOW PEOPLE.
I HAVE MET ONE WOMAN HER NAME IS SHE'S ELDERLY DISABLED
WOMAN. HER NAME IS MELODY.
I HAD TO HELP HER MOVE OUT OF A CLOSED SHELTER FROM THE MONARCH
AND THEY WOULD NOT LET HER RETRIEVE HER LAST FEW
BELONGINGS OUT OF HERE. >> WE HAD TO TALK TO FOUR
PEOPLE TO DO THAT. WE HAD TO TALK TO HER CASE
MANAGER. WE HAD TO TALK TO SOMEBODY FROM
THE COALITION ON HOMELESSNESS. >> WE HAD TO TALK TO THE
SUPERVISOR AT THAT SHELTER AND WE HAD TO TALK TO THE BAY
AREA LEGAL FUND IN ORDER TO FINALLY GET HER TO BOXES OUT OF
THAT SHELTER SO SHE COULD MOVE TO OUR NEW SHELTER.
ANOTHER PERSON I MET LIVES IN AN RV NOW WHO IS NOW AT RISK
FOR BEING TOWED FOR THE TWO HOUR PARKING BAN THAT YOU GUYS
PASSED LAST YEAR. SHE MOVED OUT OF A SHELTER
WHERE SHE HAD BEEN STOLEN FROM ASSAULTED AND RAPED THERE
MULTIPLE TIMES AND SHE IS NOW LIVING IN AN RV.
SO WE NEED TO PROTECT THESE OVERSIGHT COMMITTEES AND WE
NEED TO PROTECT THESE ADVISORY COUNCILS.
>> THANKS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER HI, MY NAME IS ZOE KELMAN.
MY COMMENTS REFLECT MY DESIRE FOR SAN FRANCISCO TO BECOME THE
MODEL OF DEMOCRACY OUR COUNTRY SO DESPERATELY NEEDS.
I'M HERE TO STRONGLY OBJECT TO REMOVING THE ENVIRONMENTAL
COMMISSION FROM THE CHARTER AND MAKE MAKING THE CASE THAT
WE NEED TO STRENGTHEN THIS COMMISSION.
>> AS A FORMER CHEMICAL ENGINEER, CHEMICAL
ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEER IN THE CHEMICAL INDUSTRY AND THEN AT
EPA IN NEW JERSEY DEP, I SPEAK WITH EXPERIENCE ON HOW ELECTED
OFFICIALS THREATEN GOVERNMENT SCIENTISTS AND ENGINEERS TO
PRIORITIZE THE INTERESTS OF THE POLITICALLY WELL-CONNECTED YOU
KNOW YOUR CORPORATE CEOS AND BILLIONAIRES OVER PUBLIC
HEALTH. >> I WISH NEW JERSEY HAD HAD AN
ENVIRONMENTAL COMMISSION INSTEAD.
I BECAME A WHISTLEBLOWER AND WORKED WITH THE COMMUNITY
TO SUE THE GOVERNMENT AND THE CORPORATIONS.
HONEYWELL TOOK THE CASE TO THE US SUPREME COURT WHERE WE
PREVAILED. OVER $1 BILLION TO REMEDIATE
CHROMIUM SITES IN JERSEY CITY DOWNGRADING THE ENVIRONMENTAL
COMMISSION TO AN ADVISORY ROLE IS CONTRARY TO THE NEEDS WE ARE
WITNESSING TODAY. >> ALTHOUGH MY COMMENTS ARE
FOCUSED PRIMARILY ON THE ENVIRONMENTAL COMMISSION, I'M
AFRAID THAT DOWNGRADING OTHER COMMISSIONS WILL HAVE PAINFUL
CONSEQUENCES IN THE FUTURE. SAN FRANCISCO PRIDES ITSELF AS
A LEADER IN PROMOTING ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION IN AND
PUBLIC HEALTH. UNFORTUNATELY THAT REPUTATION
HAS BEEN SEVERELY DAMAGED WITH NATIONAL CONSEQUENCES IN 2025.
THE SAN FRANCISCO CITY ATTORNEY SUED EPA'S ENFORCEMENT OF THE
CLEAN WATER ACT. THE NINTH DISTRICT THREW OUT
THE CASE. YET SAN FRANCISCO APPEALED TO
THE U.S. SUPREME COURT WHERE THE SUPREME COURT DECIDED
IN SAN FRANCISCO'S FAVOR PERMANENTLY WEAKENING EPA TO
ENFORCE THE CLEAN WATER ACT THAT HAS NATIONAL CONSEQUENCES
FOR. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. YES.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> AM I ABLE TO USE THIS?
YES. YES.
OKAY. DON'T START MY TIME.
OKAY. RIGHT.
OKAY. SO.
ALL RIGHT. >> UH, YOU CAN START MY TIME
NOW. ALL RIGHT.
HAPPY ST PATRICK'S DAY, EVERYBODY.
MY NAME IS JESSICA PASCOE. I'M RUNNING FOR DISTRICT TEN
SUPERVISOR. ALL RIGHT.
I'VE TALKED TO HOW MANY PEOPLE IN THIS LINE AND ASK THEM FOR
WHAT THEIR PERSPECTIVES WERE ON PROP EIGHT AND A MAJORITY OF
THEM WANTED. THEY WERE AGAINST STREAMLINING
THE TASK FORCE. >> IN FACT, MOST OF THEM STATED
IF NOT ALL STATED THAT THEY WANTED IT TO BE STRONGER.
THEY WERE PARTICULARLY CONCERNED ABOUT THE MONITORING
THE HOMELESS NESS. RIGHT.
AND A COUPLE OTHER TASK FORCE RELATED TO HELPING THE
UNHOUSED. OKAY.
I WILL GIVE YOU PARTICULAR NAMES BUT HERE'S MY MAIN
CONCERN IS THAT WHEN I TRY TO REACH OUT TO DANIEL LAURIE
AND ASK HIM TO COME TO THESE MEETINGS LIKE FOR EXAMPLE THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH MEETING THAT'S SCHEDULED OR
THAT HAS BEEN SCHEDULED THE LAST ONE HE DOESN'T ANSWER.
IF PEOPLE ARE THIS UPSET ABOUT REFORMING THE CHARTER, I THINK
COULD WE ASK HIM TO BE HERE SO THAT HE CAN HEAR THESE PEOPLE'S
VOICES? >> I WANT.
IT WOULD BE GREAT IF YOU GUYS I KNOW YOU GUYS CAN DO YOUR JOBS.
YOU GUYS DO A GREAT JOB AS SUPERVISORS AND YOU GUYS CAN
PERSUADE HIM TO NOT REFER TO GO AGAINST STREAMLINING THE TASK
FORCE. OKAY.
FOR PROP C FOR POPPY. >> ALL RIGHT.
THANKS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS GWEN MCLAUGHLIN. I'M A BORN AND RAISED SAN
FRANCISCAN AND I WANTED TO SAY HAPPY WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH
AND ST PATRICK'S DAY TO EVERYONE.
>> I THINK THERE'S SO MUCH IN THIS PROPOSED CHARTER
AMENDMENT THAT CAUSES A LOT OF CONCERN FOR ME.
>> IT'S REALLY TROUBLING AND IT'S REALLY TROUBLING THAT
THE WORKING GROUP PROCESS WAS RUSHED THROUGH WITH LITTLE
OPPORTUNITY FOR PUBLIC COMMENT AND WHEN THERE WAS AN
OPPORTUNITY FOR PUBLIC COMMENT IT SEEMED AS IF NO ONE IN THE
WORKING GROUP WAS TRULY LISTENING AS THE MAYOR'S
PROPOSED AMENDMENTS TO THE CHARTER WERE THEN RELEASED LESS
THAN 24 HOURS AFTER THAT PUBLIC COMMENT WITH NONE OF THE
SUGGESTIONS RAISED IN THAT MEETING INCORPORATED INTO THE
PROPOSAL. >> I'M SURE MANY OF YOU HERE
ARE AWARE OF THE ABSOLUTE HORRIFIC ACTS OF SEXUAL
VIOLENCE AND ABUSE THAT TOOK PLACE IN OUR CITY JAILS WHEN
CITY OFFICERS FILMED AND TAUNTED WHILE STRIP
SEARCHING 19 WOMEN IN OUR CITY JAILS JUST THIS LAST FALL
WEAKENING THE COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN WHILE ALSO
TRYING TO TAKE AWAY POWER FROM THE CITY'S POLICE COMMISSION
TASKED WITH POLICE OVERSIGHT IS EGREGIOUS.
>> ALLOWING THE MAYOR TO FIRE ANY COMMISSIONER AT AT WILL IS
EVEN MORE DEEPLY CONCERNING LIKE SOME PEOPLE HAVE ALREADY
REMARKED ON TODAY, THE CHANGES HAPPENING IN THE GOVERNMENT
HERE ARE EERILY DOGE LIKE. NOT A COMPLETE SURPRISE COMING
FROM AN ADMINISTRATION THAT USED AN AID SHOP BOT TO RESPOND
TO OUR CITY'S RV RESIDENTS WHO WERE TRYING TO REACH OUT FOR
THE CORRECT PERMITS AND CITY SERVICES SO THEY COULD
RELOCATE. ONE EFFECTIVELY BEING EVICTED
BY THE MAYOR AND THE BOARD'S NEW POLICY.
COMMUNITIES NEED A REAL SEAT AT THE TABLE IN OUR GOVERNMENT
AND OUR CITY COMMISSIONS ENABLE THAT DEMOCRATIC PARTICIPATION
IN OUR LOCAL GOVERNMENT. >> MOST COMMISSIONERS ARE
VOLUNTEERS AND REAL MEMBERS OF OUR COMMUNITIES NOT JUST
BILLIONAIRE TRUST FUND KIDS OR WEALTHY TECH EXECUTIVES TAKING
THEIR FIRST STAB AT SUPPOSEDLY TRYING TO CREATE MORE
EFFICIENCY WITHIN OUR GOVERNMENT.
>> WHAT'S THAT TECH PHRASE MOVE FAST AND BREAK THINGS.
PLEASE DON'T MAKE OR BREAK OUR DEMOCRACY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS SONNY ANGULO AND I'M HERE AS A BOARD MEMBER BOARD
STEWARD OF ARTS FOR A BETTER BAY AREA AND ALSO AS SOMEONE
THAT TRIED TO HELP STEER PROPERTY INTO BEING MORE
TAILORED, MORE SURGICAL. THAT WAS THE INTENT ANYWAY.
>> THE CITY'S CHARTER IS OUR GUIDING DOCUMENT A CONSTITUTION
THAT IS INTENDED TO STAND THE TEST OF CHANGING POLITICAL
WHIMS AN ELECTED THAT COME AND GO.
OF COURSE IT'S STILL A LIVING DOCUMENT THAT CAN BE AMENDED BY
A MAJORITY OF THE ELECTORATE BUT AT A TIME WHEN WE'RE ALL
LIVING THROUGH EGREGIOUS DODGE ATTACKS ON JOBS, PUBLIC
PROGRAMS AND BASIC DEMOCRATIC PRINCIPLES OF TRANSPARENCY,
ACCOUNTABILITY AND EQUITY A WHOLESALE AMENDMENT OF THE
CHARTER IS UNWISE. >> ANY CHANGES SHOULD BE TAKEN
VERY SERIOUSLY AND WITH SIGNIFICANT COMMUNITY INPUT.
AND SO I WANT TO SAY BROADLY THAT I THINK IT'S A SHAME AND A
DISAPPOINTMENT THAT PUBLIC INPUT IS REALLY ONLY BEING
SOLICITED RIGHT NOW ON THE PROP E TASK FORCE RECOMMENDATIONS
PER A VOTER MANDATE. GIVEN THE SWEEPING CHARTER
CHANGES THAT ARE BEING PROPOSED BY THE MAYOR, I URGE THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS TO ENGAGE WITH THE PUBLIC ON CHARTER REFORM
AND OWN THE WORK THAT SOME OF YOU HAVE BEEN DOING ON THIS
TOPIC AT CITY HALL. AS OF RIGHT NOW IT'S CONFUSING
AND OVERWHELMING AND THE BOARD IS REALLY ABDICATING ITS DUTY
TO PROVIDE GOVERNMENT CHECKS AND BALANCES WITHOUT GUTTING
OUR CITY'S CONSTITUTION. >> WITH ALL DUE RESPECT TO MY
FRIEND AT HARRINGTON, I WANTED TO CORRECT HIS ASSERTION THAT
THE PUBLIC DID NOT WEIGH IN STRONGLY ON THE S.F. ARTS
COMMISSION. >> IT WAS A VERY CONFUSING
DISCUSSION ACTUALLY AND IT NECESSITATED NOT JUST ONE BUT
TWO HEARINGS WHERE NUMEROUS ADVOCATES CAME OUT TO VOICE
CONCERNS WITH REMOVING THE DUTIES AND POWERS OF THE ARTS
COMMISSION FROM THE CHARTER. >> SO WHILE I APPRECIATE HIS
ADVOCACY TO KEEP THE BASE VALUES OF THE AC IN THE CHARTER
PROP, HE WAS SPECIFICALLY DRAFTED TO SURGICALLY IMPROVE
THE STRUCTURE OF COMMISSIONS AND HELP THEM WORK BETTER.
IT WAS NOT INTENDED TO BE A WHOLESALE AXING OF KEY
FUNCTIONS. IT IS A HORRIBLE IDEA TO
RESTRUCTURE ENTIRE DEPARTMENTS VIA THE BALLOT BOX AND THAT
WASN'T POPPY'S INTENT. >> ARBOR HAS PROPOSED A SLIGHT
CHANGE TO THE MAKEUP OF THE SFA C AND I'M INCLUDING THIS THANK
YOU SENT SUNNY ANGULO FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI MY NAME IS JUDE DIEBOLD
NYMAN SEIU SHOP STEWARD AT THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION AND I'M
SPEAKING IN MY PERSONAL CAPACITY TODAY AND I AM HERE
TODAY BECAUSE I'M CONCERNED ABOUT THE FUTURE OF DEMOCRACY
AND HUMAN RIGHTS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THE PROPOSED STREAMLINING CONSOLIDATES MORE AND MORE
POWER INTO THE MAYOR'S HANDS. >> MY CONCERN IS THIS MOVE
ECHOES TRUMP'S DOGE CUTTING AND CONSOLIDATING POWER IN A
WAY THAT ALLOWS AN ALREADY VERY POWERFUL MAYOR TO MAKE
EXECUTIVE DECISIONS THAT IMPACT OUR STAFFING SUBPOENA POWER
ABILITY TO SERVE THE PUBLIC AND FRANKLY TO EVEN EXIST BY
TAKING HRC OUT OF THE CHARTER WOULD MAKE IT POSSIBLE FOR
WHOEVER HAPPENS TO BE SITTING IN OFFICE TO SLASH AND BURN OUR
BUDGET AND MAKE IT IMPOSSIBLE FOR TEAMS LIKE MY OWN TO
CONTINUE TO FIGHT DISCRIMINATION IN HOUSING
EMPLOYMENT AND PUBLIC ACCESS IN THE CITY AT A TIME OF RISING
HOMELESSNESS AND POVERTY. OUR WORK HELPS PREVENT
DISCRIMINATORY EVICTIONS, TERMINATIONS AND HOLDS
ACCOUNTABLE THE STEWARDS OF PUBLIC SPACES.
>> PLEASE SIDE WITH THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO AND DEMOCRACY.
THIS IS NOT THE TIME POLITICALLY TO DISEMPOWER WORK
THAT FIGHTS RACISM, SEXISM, HOMOPHOBIA, TRANSPHOBIA AND THE
WORK THAT SUPPORTS ALL VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES UNDER
ATTACK AT THE FEDERAL LEVEL. >> FRANKLY, I AM TIRED OF
HAVING TO COME HERE EVERY YEAR AND BEG THOSE IN POWER NOT TO
TAKE MORE AND MORE RESOURCES THAT GO TO SAN FRANCISCANS WHO
ALREADY HAVE LESS AND LESS. WHEN WILL ENOUGH BE A TOUGH
VOTE NOW. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. HELLO SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS GIGI. I AM FROM SEIU 1021 AND A
DELEGATE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO LABOR COUNCIL.
JACKIE, CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE?
WE WANT TO HEAR YOU BEST. THERE YOU GO.
THANK YOU. I'M SPEAKING IN MY PERSONAL
CAPACITY AND AS A LABOR ORGANIZER OUR SUPERVISORS
SHOULD PROTECT THE INDEPENDENCE OF OUR COMMISSIONS FROM
POLITICAL INTERFERENCE AND THE TRANSPARENCY OF THE CITY'S
GOVERNANCE. I URGE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
TO VOTE NO ON THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE RECOMMENDATIONS
AND COMMIT TO PROTECTING PUBLIC SERVICES.
>> YOU KNOW, TO YOU KNOW, CITY WORKERS ARE PROVIDING THESE
SERVICES. SUPERVISORS AND MAYORS COME
AND GO. RIGHT.
BUT THE EXPERTISE AND THE KNOWLEDGE OF OUR CIVIL SERVICE
EMPLOYEES KEEPS THE SERVICES OF THE CITY RUNNING.
>> THESE COMMISSIONERS HAVE A SAY ON HOW CITY A CITY WORKERS
ARE TREATED. >> THESE CHANGES ERODE THE
POWER OF WORKERS AND THEIR UNIONS.
>> AND FINALLY TURNING THESE COMMISSIONERS INTO ATWELL
POSITIONS GREATLY INCREASES EXECUTIVE OVERREACH AND IT'S AN
ANTI-LABOR PRACTICE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ANDY GILLIS. I'M A RESIDENT OF D8.
I SUSPECT THE ALL THE SUPERVISORS WHO SUPPORT THESE
MEASURES CALL THEMSELVES MODERATES BUT THERE'S NOTHING
MODERATE ABOUT WHAT IS BEING PROPOSED HERE.
REDUCING PUBLIC INPUT AND PROTECTIONS OVER THE CITY'S
BUSINESS AND DECISION MAKING AND INCREASING THE POWER OF AN
ALREADY POWERFUL MAYOR IS NOT MODERATION.
BUT OUR CLASSIC PLATFORMS OF A CONSERVATIVE AGENDA.
>> THIS IS IN FACT THE VERY THING WE'RE FIGHTING IN THE
TRUMP ADMINISTRATION. ON A LARGER SCALE, YES.
BUT SAN FRANCISCO IS EXPERIENCING THE VERY SAME
ATTEMPTS BY CONSERVATIVE TECH BILLIONAIRES TO ERODE THE VOICE
OF VOTERS AND INCREASE THEIR OWN INFLUENCE.
THE TASK THE TASK FORCE DID NOT TAKE INTO ACCOUNT THE MINIMAL
PUBLIC INPUT IT WAS PROVIDED OUTLINING CONCERNS AROUND THE
IMPORTANCE OF OUR COMMISSIONS BUT EFFECTIVENESS NOT
EFFICIENCY SHOULD BE OUR GOALS. DEMOCRACY CAN BE SLOW
AND CUMBERSOME BUT THAT'S BETTER THAN THE OPPOSITE.
I'M SURE YOU'LL SAY I'M ENGAGING IN HYPERBOLE AND THAT
THERE IS NO COMPARISON BETWEEN WHAT YOU'RE DOING AND WHAT
TRUMP IS DOING. BUT YOU ARE BOTH PROCEEDING
AND EXCUSE ME WITH PERMANENT CHANGES AND EXCUSE ME YOU'RE
BOTH PROCEEDING WITH PERMANENT CHANGES IN OUR SYSTEM OF
GOVERNMENT WHICH WILL PROVIDE SIGNIFICANTLY FEWER OPPORTUN
CITIES FOR SAN FRANCISCANS TO HAVE A SAY IN HOW THE CITY IS
GOVERNED AND SO OUR DEMOCRACY WILL BE WEAKENED.
ON YET ANOTHER FRONT IF EVER THERE WAS IF EVER WE NEEDED
MORE CHECKS AND BALANCES ON POWER IT IS NOW.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> THANK YOU FOR STILL BEING
HERE. I KNOW SUPPER TIME FOR ALL OF
US. I'M JULIE FISHER.
I HAVE BEEN WORKING AND LIVING IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 40 YEARS
AND ALL OF THAT WORK HAS BEEN UNION WORK.
>> I THINK MANY OF THE SPEAKERS HERE TODAY HAVE MADE MORE THAN
ADEQUATE POINTS ABOUT THE CHANGE IN THE CHARTER
IN COMMISSION. SO I'M GOING TO JUST JUMP AHEAD
TO TELL A FEW QUICK STORIES THAT ALL OF US HAVE OUR OWN
VERSION OF. >> WHEN I USED TO WORK AT
MACY'S DOWNTOWN IN UNION SQUARE AND GO HOME LATE AT NIGHT AFTER
THE STORE CLOSED. I WOULD SEE PEOPLE AND THIS WAS
30 YEARS AGO OR LONGER PEOPLE SLEEPING IN THE DOORWAYS OF ALL
THE OPEN BUSINESSES AS MIGHT BE THE CASE, MANY OF THE SALES
WOMEN WOULD PICK SOMEBODY TO KIND OF TAKE CARE OF OFFER THEM
A SANDWICH CASH AND ONE GENTLEMAN THAT WAS MY GENTLEMAN
TO TAKE CARE OF WOULD NEVER TAKE CASH BECAUSE HE WAS AFRAID
OF BEING ROBBED EITHER WHILE HE WAS AT A SHELTER OR JUST
SLEEPING ON THE STREET. A FRAGILE OLD MAN.
SO HERE WE ARE 30 PLUS YEARS LATER AND WE STILL HAVE THAT
PROBLEM AND MORE. SO I ASK THAT YOU LOOK AT THIS
AS AN OPPORTUNITY TO FIX SOME OF THOSE PROBLEMS.
WHY THIS CITY WITH ALL ITS RESOURCES HAS PEOPLE STILL
SLEEPING ON THE STREETS SUFFERING FROM DRUG ABUSE
AND MORE. >> AND I'D ALSO LIKE TO SAY
THAT LIKE A LOT OF PEOPLE I AM THE GRANDDAUGHTER OF IMMIGRANTS
FROM LITHUANIA IN MY CASE AND I AM ABLE TO LIVE SUCCESSFULLY
IN THIS COUNTRY BECAUSE THEY MADE THE JOURNEY OVER HERE ON
BOATS INSTEAD OF HOUSEKEEPING. >> AND I ALSO WANT TO MENTION
PEOPLE THAT ARE NOT HERE TODAY. I'M A MEMBER OF SEIU 2015.
SO MANY OF MY COLLEAGUES WHO ARE CAREGIVERS AND THE PEOPLE
THEY TAKE CARE OF COULD NOT BE HERE BUT THEY ARE ALSO LARGELY
NUMBERS OF WOMEN, LARGELY PEOPLE OF COLOR AND MANY, MANY
IMMIGRANTS. SO PLEASE KEEP ALL OF US
IN MIND AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR ATTENTION.
THANK YOU. JULIE FISHER FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> THANK YOU. MY NAME'S ART PERSICO AND I'VE
HAD THE PLEASURE OF MEETING AND TALKING TO MANY OF YOU ON
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. SO THANK YOU FOR KEEPING THE
DOORS OPEN AND THE CHANNELS OF COMMUNICATION OPEN TO THINGS
LIKE THIS AS WELL. YOU KNOW SAN FRANCISCO AS YOU
KNOW, HAS A STRONG MAYOR FORM OF GOVERNMENT AND I DON'T THINK
WE NEED TO STRENGTHEN AN ALREADY STRONG MAYOR FORM OF
GOVERNMENT. THE COMMISSIONERS WERE CREATED
IN SAN FRANCISCO IN 1898 TO ENSURE CIVILIAN OVERSIGHT,
PROMOTE TRANSPARENCY AND ACT AS A CHECK AND BALANCE AGAINST THE
MAYOR'S POWER AND A STRONG MAYOR SYSTEM.
SO I THINK WE HAVE TO KEEP THAT IN MIND.
I DON'T THINK EFFICIENCY IS THE CYNICAL CANNON.
IT'S ONE OF THE FEW LATIN PHRASES I KNOW.
IT'S NOT THE HIGHEST VALUE FOR A DEMOCRACY.
I THINK THE PROBLEM MAY HAVE BEEN THE INITIAL MANDATE FOR
THE WORK OF THIS BODY ON STREAMLINING STREAMLINING.
SO THAT MAY HAVE BE AT THE ROOT OF THE PROBLEM.
SAN FRANCISCO IS A HAS A PROUD HISTORY OF PROGRESSIVISM
AND HUMAN RIGHTS. WE CELEBRATE HUMAN RIGHTS ON
THE CITY HALL STEPS EVERY EVERY YEAR ON DECEMBER 10TH.
HUMAN RIGHTS ARE PART OF MANY OF THE MOTIVATIONS FOR SOME OF
THESE COMMISSIONS THAT YOU HAVE.
SO LET'S NOT WEAKEN THAT. LET'S NOT WEAKEN PUBLIC INPUT.
LET'S NOT STIFLE THE CREATIVITY AND KNOWLEDGE OF SAN
FRANCISCANS IN A RUSH TOWARD EFFICIENCY.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU ART PERSICO FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS
AND MY FELLOW CLERKS. >> MY NAME IS JOSHUA RUDY OCHOA
AND I SERVE AS THE YOUTH COMMISSION'S COMMUNITY
PARTNERSHIP SPECIALIST. >> I SPEAKING TODAY TO URGE YOU
TO PROTECT OUR YOUTH VOICES AND REPRESENTATION IN OUR LOCAL
GOVERNMENT BY PROTECTING AND KEEPING THE YOUTH
COMMISSION IN OUR CITIES CHARTER.
IT'S BEEN A PRIVILEGE AND AN HONOR TO SEE OUR INCREDIBLE
COMMISSIONERS BECOME MORE POWERFUL LEADERS, POWERFUL
SPEAKERS AND CHANGEMAKERS IN THEIR COMMUNITIES AS THEY
LEARN THE INS AND OUTS OF CITY HALL AND ITS MANY DEPARTMENTS.
OUR CITY'S YOUTH COMMISSION CAN CONTINUES TO BE AN EXAMPLE THAT
YOUTH COUNCILS AND ADVISORY BOARDS ACROSS THE STATE AND THE
NATION LOOK UP TO AS THEY SUPPORT THEIR YOUTH TO BECOME
MORE POWERFUL LEADERS IN THEIR COMMUNITIES.
ADDITIONALLY, I WANT TO SHOUT OUT THE DCF OVERSIGHT ADVISORY
COMMITTEE AND THE SERVICE PROVIDERS WORKING GROUP TO
REMAIN IN THE CITY CHARTER AS WELL AS THEY HAVE BEEN
INCREDIBLE PARTNERS IN OUR ADVOCACY TOWARDS CREATING A SAN
FRANCISCO THAT WHERE YOUTH DON'T JUST SURVIVE BUT THEY
THRIVE ENOUGH TO BECOME THEIR COMMUNITIES STRONGEST
ADVOCATES, LEADERS AND FUTURE SUPERVISORS.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR TIME AND THANK YOU TO THE PUBLIC
COMMENTERS WHO SUPPORT OUR EFFORTS TO REMAIN IN THE CITY'S
CHARTER COMMISSION. SORRY IN THE CITY'S CHARTER.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU JOSHUA OCHOA FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS GABBY LA STARNER
AND I'M THE CHAIR AND DISTRICT SIX YOUTH COMMISSIONER OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO YOUTH COMMISSION. >> WHEN PROPOSITION F WON 60%
ON THE NOVEMBER NOVEMBER 1995 BALLOT AND THE YOUTH COMMISSION
WAS CREATED, SAN FRANCISCANS MADE IT CLEAR WHAT THEY VALUED
AND STILL VALUE. YOUTH VOICES AT THE CENTER OF
HOW WE GOVERN DECISIONS AFFECTING CHILDREN AND FAMILIES
TODAY. THAT STRUCTURE IS AT RISK.
THE YOUTH COMMISSION WAS INTENTIONALLY PLACED IN THE
CITY CHARTER TO ENSURE TRANSPARENCY, ACCOUNTABILITY
AND SHARED GOVERNANCE. SINCE THEN WE HAVE LAUNCHED
SUCCESSFUL INITIATIVES SUCH AS FREE ME FOR YOUTH AND EXPANDED
WELLNESS CENTERS ALONG WITH ACTIVATING YOUTH THROUGH
MOVEMENTS SUCH AS VOTE 16. THE WORK OF THE YOUTH
COMMISSION HAS DONE HAS AND WILL CONTINUE TO POSITIVELY
IMPACT YOUNG PEOPLE IN THE CITY FOR GENERATIONS TO COME.
IN MY PERSONAL EXPERIENCE I HAVE BEEN ON THE YOUTH
COMMISSION FOR SIX YEARS AND I DON'T THINK I WOULD HAVE
LEARNED ANYWHERE ELSE JUST HOW IMPORTANT GOVERNANCE AND USE OF
ENGAGEMENT IS IF I WASN'T ON THE COMMISSION.
ADDITIONALLY, I PERSONALLY HAVE BEEN ABLE TO WORK ON IMPORTANT
INITIATIVES SUCH AS LANGUAGE ACCESS AND IMMIGRANT
PROTECTIONS IN OUR CITY. >> PROPOSED CHANGES WOULD MOVE
US OUT OF THE CHARTER GROUP, WEAKENING THE STRUCTURAL
PROTECTIONS VOTERS PUT IN PLACE WHEN YOUNG PEOPLE HAVE A FORMAL
SEAT AT THE TABLE. >> DECISIONS ARE STRONGER, MORE
TRANSPARENT AND BETTER ALIGNED WITH COMMUNITY NEEDS.
>> SAN FRANCISCO'S YOUTH DESERVE STABLE SYSTEMS THAT
ELEVATE THEIR VOICES AND SAFEGUARD PUBLIC
INVESTMENTS. I URGE YOU TO KEEP THE YOUTH
COMMISSION IN THE CHARTER AND PROTECT SHARED GOVERNANCE
FOR SAN FRANCISCO'S YOUTH. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANK YOU VICE CHAIR LIZ DONNER FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
I'M PETER WARFIELD, CO-FOUNDER AND HEAD OF LIBRARY USERS
ASSOCIATION AT OUR LIBRARY IN SAN FRANCISCO IS A
TREMENDOUS ASSET. AND IN GENERAL LIBRARIES PUBLIC
LIBRARIES IN PARTICULAR HAVE A VERY IMPORTANT ROLE AND A
VALUABLE ROLE IN HELPING TO EDUCATE AND ENTERTAIN THE FOLKS
THAT ARE FUNDING THEM. AND TO PROVIDE A BROAD RANGE OF
MATERIALS SO THAT THEY CAN FUNCTION IN A DEMOCRACY FOR ONE
THING, WE'RE OPPOSED TO ANY WEAKENING OF COMMISSIONS
AND ESPECIALLY THEIR INDEPENDENCE.
IN THAT RESPECT I WOULD SAY THAT THE LAW LIBRARY SHOULDN'T
BE DEPENDENT FOR ITS EXISTENCE ON A STATE LAW.
>> HMM. THERE MIGHT BE BETTER IT MIGHT
BE BETTER TO HAVE REDUNDANCY RATHER THAN DEPEND ON A STATE
LAW. AND THAT COMMISSIONERS IF
ANYTHING OUGHT TO HAVE SOME LEVEL OF SECURITY WITH RESPECT
TO THEIR POSITIONS SO THAT THEIR ROLE IN ADVISING AND IN
DETERMINING POLICIES HAS SOME STRENGTH AND RESISTANCE TO THE
POTENTIAL OF WHAT WE'VE SEEN ALREADY AND ACTUALLY HAPPENED
AT THE LIBRARY COMMISSION WHERE THERE WAS A BROAD SWEEP OF THE
MAYOR GETTING RID OF A WHOLE GROUP OF COMMISSIONERS WHOSE
POLICIES HE DIDN'T LIKE. >> WE'VE WORKED TO IMPROVE A
GREAT DEAL OF THINGS THAT WE LEARNED ABOUT THROUGH COMING TO
THE COMMISSION AND SOME OF WHICH THE COMMISSION ACTUALLY
AGREED WITH AND ADOPTED ITSELF. WE WORKED ON PRIVACY ISSUES
WITH ELECTRONIC FRONTIER FOUNDATION AND ACLU TO PREVENT
THE IMPOSITION AND INSTALLATION OF RFID TAGS.
WE'VE WORKED AGAINST EXCESSIVE FINES AND FEES.
WE WORKED ON CREATING A POST OCCUPANCY EVALUATION FOR THE
FLAWED DESIGN OF THE NEW MAIN LIBRARY AND IMPROVEMENTS
IN SIGNAGE AND SO ON. THOSE WOULD NOT BE AS EASILY OR
AT ALL POSSIBLE HAD IT NOT BEEN FOR THE EXISTENCE OF THE
COMMISSION SYSTEM. >> THANKS VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS
AND CLERK'S OFFICE. MY NAME IS JOYCE AND AND I HAVE
THE HONOR OF SERVING AS THE ACTING DIRECTOR FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO YOUTH COMMISSION. AND I WOULD LIKE TO LET
EVERYONE KNOW THAT THE COMMISSION IS OFFICIALLY 30
YEARS OLD THIS YEAR AND OVER THE PAST 30 YEARS THE YOUTH
COMMISSION HAS ENSURED THAT YOUNG PEOPLE WERE AT THE TABLE
FOR MANY ISSUES. THE ADULTS IN THE ROOM OFTEN
FORGET TO INVITE THEM TOO. 1998 WE HAD THE LGBTQ YOUTH
TASK FORCE TO ADDRESS ISSUES THAT OUR LGBTQ YOUTH FACED 2000
TURNS WHEN THE SCHOOL BUSSES STOPPED TAKING YOUNG PEOPLE TO
SCHOOL. THE YOUTH COMMISSION WORKED
WITH COMMUNITY TO ESTABLISH WHAT WE SEE TODAY AS FREE MUNI
FOR YOUTH. SINCE THE 2000S THE UV
COMMISSION MADE SURE THAT YOUNG PEOPLE WERE THERE WHEN THEY
WERE TALKING ABOUT PUBLIC SAFETY.
>> MAKING SURE THAT POLICIES ARE NOT OVER CRIMINAL OVER
CRIMINALIZING YOUNG PEOPLE AND THAT WE FOCUS ON
PREVENTION. THE YOUTH COMMISSION MADE SURE
THAT WE ARE THE BRIDGE BETWEEN YOUNG PEOPLE AND GOVERNMENT
AND MAKE SURE THAT WE ARE EQUIPPING EVERY YOUNG PERSON
WITH THE SKILL AND POWER TO ADVOCATE FOR THEMSELVES, THEIR
FAMILIES AND COMMUNITIES. THAT'S WHY WE NOW HAVE THE
DISTRICT ONE DISTRICT THREE DISTRICT SEVEN AND DISTRICT
NINE YOUTH COUNCILS AND MANY OTHERS AND THERE WILL BE MORE
TO COME. >> WE HAVE ALSO SERVED AS A
BLUEPRINT FOR YOUTH THROUGHOUT CALIFORNIA AND THE NATION AS
WELL. AND THE EFFECTIVE YOUTH
COMMISSION LOOKS LIKE TO OTHER YOUNG PEOPLE WHO WANT TO START
THEIR OWN. >> I URGE THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO REJECT THE RECOMMENDATION TO MOVE THE
YOUTH COMMISSION TO THEM. INITIATIVE CODE.
WE HOPE TO STAY IN THE CITY CHARTER TO ENSURE THAT THE
COMMISSION RETAINS ITS INDEPENDENCE FOR YOUNG PEOPLE
TO BE PUBLIC SERVANTS TO THE YOUTH OF SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE
THERE WILL ALWAYS BE YOUNG PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
DIRECTOR ZANE FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
GOOD EVENING. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ELVIRA FOR MONGO I AM BORN AND RAISED IN THE CITY
. >> I WAS A COMMISSIONER ON THE
SHERIFF'S OVERSIGHT BOARD FROM 2020 TWO.
I'VE UNTIL RECENTLY OF THIS YEAR.
I'M JUST ADDING MY VOICE TO THE CHORUS OF VOICES RIGHTFULLY
UPSET WITH THE PROPOSED LASTING CHANGES BY THE TASK FORCE.
>> I ALSO WANT TO ECHO SUPERVISOR WALTON'S EARLIER
STATEMENT REGARDING THE TASK FORCE BOARD NOT BEING
REFLECTIVE OF THE CITY'S DIVERSITY ESPECIALLY THE
COMMUNITY THAT I COME FROM. >> FROM MY EXPERIENCE
AND PHYSICALLY ATTENDING THESE TASK FORCE MEETINGS I DON'T
BELIEVE THEY TOOK INTO CONSIDERATION OUR CALL OUTS
AND CONCERNS WITH CHANGING THE NATURE OF THE SHERIFF'S
OVERSIGHT BOARD AND POLICE COMMISSION.
THESE CIVILIAN RUN BOARDS ARE THE VERY LEAST THAT WE CAN DO
TO HELP ADDRESS THE SYSTEMIC INEQUITIES THAT WE SAY WE CARE
ABOUT. AND JUST LIKE MY LAST POINT IS
JUST LIKE MY BIGGEST CONCERN AS YOU KNOW, THE TASK FORCE DID
NOT HAVE THE RIGHT TO MAKE THESE SWEEPING POWER CHANGES TO
A VOTER APPROVED BOARDS SUCH AS THE SHERIFF'S OVERSIGHT BOARD
THAT WAS VOTER APPROVED AS RECENTLY AS 20 20.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER AND BEFORE YOU BEGIN, MR.
GUAITA, IF THERE ARE OTHER SPEAKERS IN THE PUBLIC GALLERY
WHO'D LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD ON THE PROPER COMMISSION
STREAMLINING TASK FORCE RECOMMENDATIONS PLEASE LINE UP
ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OTHERWISE BRITTANY MAY BE OUR
LAST SPEAKER. >> WELCOME.
THANK YOU. CLERK CALVILLO.
GOOD EVENING. MY NAME IS BRITTANY TICWATCH.
I SERVE AS A DIRECTOR AT THE SAN FRANCISCO HUMAN RIGHTS
COMMISSION BUT I'M HERE IN MY PERSONAL CAPACITY AND I WANTED
TO GIVE MY OPPOSITION VISION TO MOVING THE HUMAN RIGHTS
COMMISSION FROM THE CHARTER TO THE ADMIN CODE AS WELL AS THE
SPECIFIC RECOMMENDATION TO REMOVE OUR CHARTER.
>> OUR CONTRACT ENFORCEMENT AUTHORITY.
AND I JUST WANTED TO REMIND FOLKS THAT THE HUMAN RIGHTS
COMMISSION WAS ESTABLISHED IN THE 60S DURING A TIME THAT
WE ASSOCIATED WITH THE SEGREGATED SOUTH.
THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION WAS ESTABLISHED IN 1964 BECAUSE OF
SIT INS AT MEL'S DINER, THE SHERATON PALACE HOTEL, THE
CADILLAC DEALERSHIP THAT'S RIGHT ON VENICE AND MARKET THAT
WOULDN'T HIRE BLACK PEOPLE. SO ANTI-BLACK RACISM
AND FIGHTING THAT AND A MAYOR WHO SAW THAT FIGHTING
THAT WAS NECESSARY IS WHAT CREATED THE HRC AND TO WEAKEN
OUR CIVIL RIGHTS AUTHORITY AND OUR HUMAN RIGHTS ADVOCACY
IN THIS MOMENT IS REALLY DANGEROUS.
>> AND I REMEMBER WHEN I FIRST LEFT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND WENT TO THE HRC PEOPLE SAID WELL WHAT DO THEY EVEN DO?
>> WE KEEP PEOPLE IN HOUSING. WE'RE GROUND ZERO FOR THE
DEMOGRAPHY OF SAN FRANCISCO. AT ONE POINT WHEN WE WERE
FIGHTING SOURCE OF INCOME DISCRIMINATION WE WERE MAINLY
SEEING BLACK MOTHERS WHO HAD SECTION EIGHT VOUCHERS AND WERE
BEING TOLD THAT THEY COULDN'T GET HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SO AS A MOTHER, ARE YOU GOING TO GO TO FIVE DIFFERENT
PLACES OR ARE YOU GOING TO START MOVING OUT TO RICHMOND,
TO ANTIOCH TO THE FAR STRETCHES OF THE BAY AREA WHILE YOU'RE
STILL COMMUTING INTO SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE THIS IS WHERE
YOUR NETWORK IS WHERE YOUR KIDS GO TO SCHOOL, WHERE YOUR
DOCTORS ARE SAN FRANCISCO YOU KNOW, WE THE HUMAN RIGHTS
COMMISSION THAT IS WE I THINK GIVE A LOT OF CREDENCE TO WHAT
YOU ALL CAN STAND ON TO SAY YOU'RE A LIBERAL DEMOCRACY,
THAT YOU'RE FIGHTING FOR THE PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE
WE'RE AN AGENCY THAT IS FURTHERING HUMAN RIGHTS
AND SHOULD BE FORTIFIED IN THIS MOMENT NOT WEAKEN.
AND I THINK THAT IF YOU DO WEAKEN US THEN THE PUBLIC WILL
HAVE NO ASPERSIONS ABOUT YOUR PRIORITIES.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, DIRECTOR SHIKATA FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC. >> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT,
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
. >> WELL, I HOPE TO DRAW ON.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MADAM. AND FIRST I JUST WANT TO SAY
THANK YOU OF COURSE, TO ALL OF THE PUBLIC WHO CAME IN TO SPEAK
TODAY. WE APPRECIATE YOUR INPUT.
>> I DO WANT TO THANK THE TASK FORCE AGAIN FOR THEIR WORK
AND A I THINK WHAT WE HAVE TO ASK OURSELF HERE REALLY IS IS
THIS THE SAN FRANCISCO THAT WE WANT TO SEE MOVING FORWARD IF
WE'RE OKAY WITH MORE POLICE DEATHS, IF WE'RE OKAY WITH THE
ELIMINATION OF YOUTH VOICE, IF WE'RE OKAY WITH NO DIVERSITY,
IF WE'RE OKAY WITH LOSING RESOURCE FOR CHILDREN AND YOUTH
AND IF WE'RE OKAY WITH THE REALLY THE ATTACKS ON OUR ARTS
THEN I THINK THAT THESE RECOMMENDATIONS OR SOME OF THEM
MAY BE SOMETHING WE SHOULD SUPPORT.
BUT BUT I HAVE TO SAY THAT I REALLY DON'T THINK PEOPLE TRULY
UNDERSTAND WHAT'S AT STAKE HERE IN THE MAGNITUDE OF HARM OF
SOME OF THESE RECOMMENDATIONS THAT HAVE BEEN PROPOSED PROPOSE
AND IT IS A MAJOR PROBLEM TO HAVE A GROUP WITH NO DIVERSITY
ASSEMBLING TO PUSH CHANGE THAT AFFECTS EVERYONE.
I MEAN I WAS SITTING HERE LAUGHING TO MYSELF BECAUSE I
HAVE PROBABLY SEEN MORE DIVERSITY AT A TRUMP RALLY
AND I SAY THIS NOT TO BE FUNNY BUT I SAY THIS BECAUSE IT'S
SCARY AS A BLACK MAN THAT AFTER WE'VE SEEN ALL OF THE DEATHS,
AFTER WE'VE SEEN ALL OF THE SHOOTINGS, AFTER WE'VE SEEN ALL
THE HARMS OF LAW ENFORCEMENT ON BLACK PEOPLE AND PEOPLE OF
COLOR THAT WE CAN HAVE RECOMMENDATIONS THAT GIVE
UNILATERAL REAL POWER ALMOST TO ONE PERSON TO MAKE DECISIONS
ABOUT DISCIPLINE. AFTER ALL OF THAT HISTORY HERE
WE HAVE PEOPLE IN THIS CITY WHO CAN MAKE THOSE TYPES OF
RECOMMENDATIONS AND THEN TELL ME THEY VALUE AND RESPECT
DIVERSITY. SO WE HAVE A DECISION TO MAKE
OBVIOUSLY AS A BOARD BUT FUNDAMENTALLY FROM ONSET
DECISIONS SHOULD NOT BE MADE ABOUT THE MASSES OF SAN
FRANCISCANS BY THE MAJORITY AND BY A VERY, VERY, VERY, VERY
,VERY, VERY, VERY, VERY, VERY, VERY SMALL GROUP THAT LACKS ANY
TYPE OF DIVERSITY. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, PROFESSOR WALTON. >> I WANT TO THANK ALL THE
FOLKS WHO HAVE COME OUT TO THOSE 23 TASK FORCE MEETINGS
WHO CAME OUT TODAY. I WANT TO THANK AGAIN THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR AND HER STAFF FOR THEIR WORK AND THE
COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE FOR THE WORK THEY'VE DONE TO SUPPORT
THE TASK FORCE. I WANT TO THANK THE CHAIR
AND VICE CHAIR OF THE TASK FORCE AND THE MEMBERS FOR THE
WORK THEY HAVE DONE OVER THAT YEAR.
>> WE DO AS PRESIDENT SAID, HAVE WORK AHEAD OF US.
WE HAVE YOU KNOW, LESS THAN TWO MONTHS A LOT ACTUALLY YOU KNOW,
MORE LIKE A MONTH TO SIX WEEKS TO SEE WHAT IN THE TASKFORCE
RECOMMENDATIONS AND THE REST OF THE CONVERSATION ABOUT CHARTER
REFORM THAT WE HAVE SEEN IN THE CITY CAN BE PUT FORWARD AS A
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS CONTRIBUTION TO THE
CONVERSATION. AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING
WITH YOU ALL ON THIS BOARD AND I THINK THERE IS EVEN IF WE
ONLY DID THE NONCONTROVERSIAL ELEMENTS OF WHAT THE TASK FORCE
HAS RECOMMENDED, THAT WOULD BE A BIG CHUNK OF CHARTER REFORM
AND IT WOULD BE A POSITIVE CONTRIBUTION.
WE MAY DO A LITTLE BIT MORE THAN THAT.
I DON'T THINK WE'RE GOING TO TOUCH MANY OF THE LIVE WIRES
THAT FOLKS HAVE EXPRESSED THE GREATEST CONCERNS ABOUT, BUT
WE'LL SEE. WE'RE A BODY OF 11 PEOPLE, SIX
OF US HAVE TO DECIDE WHAT TO DO.
>> AND WITH THAT THIS MATTER HAS BEEN HEARD AND IS NOW FILED
. AND POOR SUPERVISOR CHEN, SHE
WAS STRUGGLING WITH ILLNESS THROUGH THROUGH THE FIRST PART
OF THIS MEETING BUT SHE HAS SUCCUMBED AND HAD TO LEAVE.
AND SO I WOULD LIKE A MOTION TO EXCUSE SUPERVISOR CHEN FROM THE
REMAINDER OF THE MEETING MOVED BY CHERYL SECONDED BY WALTON.
MADAM CLERK, CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
>> YES, MR. TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION SUPERVISOR CHEN IS
EXCUSED. >> OKAY.
SO THEN I THINK THAT TAKES US TO REGULAR REGULAR PUBLIC
COMMENT, IS THAT RIGHT? >> AND I DON'T WORK THAT TAKES
US TO REGULAR PUBLIC. OKAY.
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT OR IF YOU ARE IN THE CHAMBER
AND YOU'D LIKE TO PROVIDE THE BOARD WITH GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED.
ITEMS 21 THROUGH 24 ARE ELIGIBLE FOR YOUR COMMENT.
>> THOSE ARE THE ITEMS UP FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED
AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER
JURISDICTION AND ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT HAS ALREADY BEEN
REPORTED OUT TO THE BOARD BY AN APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE WHERE
PUBLIC COMMENT OCCURRED. AND LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
SPEAKER MR. RIGHT. WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. >> TASK FORCE EVERYTHING THAT
THIS TASK FORCE IS PROPOSING TO DO IS THE JOB.
MR. RIGHT ABOUT YOUR TIME THE STREAMLINING TASK FORCE HAS
ALREADY BEEN HEARD AND WAS DISPOSED OF.
THAT IS NOT A TOPIC FOR YOU TO HAVE COMMENT ON AT THIS POINT.
>> SO PLEASE CONTINUE SIR, YOU HAVE ALREADY DEMONSTRATED TO
HAVE ANY RESIDENT INTERRUPT ME BEFORE I MAKE MY POINT.
OKAY. YOU'RE JUMPING THE GUN, MR.
RIGHT? >> YEAH.
JUST GO PAST YOUR TIME. OKAY?
NOW YOU START MY TIME. >> BACK UP PLEASE.
MR. RIGHT CONTINUE. GOT ME OVER TO THE 41.
THIS WON'T BE TWO MINUTES MR. RIGHT PLEASE CONTINUE.
OKAY. >> THE TASK THE THE
RESPONSIBILITY PERTAINING TO THE TASK FORCE IS A
RESPONSIBILITY OF YOUR BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
YOU TALK ABOUT SAVING MONEY AND TAKE CARE OF BUSINESS THE
WAY IT'S SUPPOSED TO BE TAKEN CARE OF IS THE JURISDICTION OF
THE BOARD SUPERVISORS. IF YOU TAKE CARE OF BUSINESS
THE WAY IS SUPPOSED TO BE TAKEN CARE OF.
WE WOULDN'T NEED NO TASK FORCE UNDERSTAND ME NOW ABOUT
SUPERVISION AND MANAGEMENT OF FUNDS.
I'VE ALREADY DEMONSTRATED WHAT YOU MISSED OUT ON THE
OPPORTUNITY TO TAKE CARE AT A MINIMUM OF A HUNDRED MILLION
500,000 NEGATIVE DOLLAR CASH FLOW MEANING WELL AWAY BY
HAVING PEOPLE WHO USE THE MUNI TRANSPORTATION ON CHINESE NEW
YEARS IN THE PARADE YOU TURN AROUND AND PUT ALL THAT WEAR
AND TEAR ON THE MUNI SUBWAY SYSTEM AND ABOVE GROUND SUBWAY
SYSTEM BY LETTING PEOPLE RIDE FOR FREE.
YOU ACTUALLY INCREASED THE DEBT THAT YOU'RE COMPLAINING ABOUT
WHERE YOU WANT TO PUT IT ON A BALLOT AND HAVE PEOPLE VOTE TO
TAX US TO PAY FOR THE NEGATIVE CASH FLOW THAT YOU DEVELOPED
WITH THE MUNI RAILWAY SYSTEM DOESN'T MAKE ANY SENSE.
I WENT TO GO RENT A U-HAUL VAN THIS WEEKEND TO MOVE SOME OF MY
PROPERTY ADDED UP. THE NUMBERS COME TO FIND OUT
THE NUMBERS DON'T MATCH WHAT THEY'RE CHARGING ME.
COME TO FIND OUT I'M PAYING FOR SERVICES, SCHOOL, HEALTH CARE.
I DIDN'T COME DOWN HERE TO PAY FOR YOUR HEALTH CARE.
I CAME TO RENT A U-HAUL VAN TO MOVE MY PROPERTY.
YOU ALWAYS MAKE ANOTHER PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE A THING TO
PROBLEM PAY FOR A PROBLEM THAT'S BEEN FIVE YEARS.
>> THANK YOU. MR. RIGHT AND FINALLY IN ALL MY
TIME AND YOU GOT TO LET ME MAKE UP THAT TIME THAT YOU LOVE ME
MR. RIGHT YOU KNOW HOW THE PROCEDURES WORK HERE.
YOU YOU HAVE NOT DEBATABLE IT'S A BOARD ROOM.
>> BOARD RULE. YEAH.
LET PEOPLE SPEAK AND YOU INTERRUPT THEM AND YOU PASS
THEIR TIME. >> MR. RIGHT WHY DON'T WE TALK
ABOUT THIS AFTER THE BOARD MEETING BECAUSE ESPECIALLY ON
MY BACK. >> OKAY, WE GOT WE GOT TO KEEP
MOVING. >> YOU GOT TO MOVE.
I GOT TO BE DEALING WITH OTHER PEOPLE.
>> WELL, LET'S LET'S CONTINUE. MS..
MCGEEVER, WE'RE READY FOR YOU. IT'S NOT LIKE YOU GUYS WAS NOT
FAIR. >> YOU DID THAT TO OTHER
PEOPLE. I WAS THREE PEOPLE COME UP HERE
WHEN THEY HAD CONTROVERSY. >> MS..
MCGEEVER, PLEASE BEGIN. >> OKAY.
OKAY. SO I'M JUST WOULD LIKE TO PUT
THIS ON THE PUBLIC RECORD. MY NAME IS LEAH MCKEEVER.
I LIVE IN DISTRICT SIX SAN FRANCISCO AND THIS IS AN
ARTICLE THAT WAS PUBLISHED IN THE GUARDIAN WHICH IS AN
INTERNATIONAL NEWSPAPER. I SUPPORTS FAMILY INCLUDING
DEAF BOY WHO WASN'T GIVEN HIS ASSISTANCE DEVICES.
>> CALIF IS SUPERINTENDENT IS CALLING FOR THE RETURN OF A
HEARING IMPAIRED SIX YEAR OLD AFTER HE, HIS MOTHER AND HIS
FIVE YEAR OLD SIBLING WERE DETAINED ON TUESDAY WHILE
REPORTING FOR THEIR CHECK IN AT AN ICE OFFICE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND DEPORTED TO COLUMBIA. THAT ICE OFFICE IS ON TO
MOHAMMAD STREETS. IT IS IN THE DISTRICT THAT I
LIVE IN. >> LESLIE RODRIGUEZ GUTIERREZ
AND HER SONS WERE ARRESTED DURING THEIR VISIT TO ICE'S
INTENSIVE SUPERVISION OPINION APPEARANCE PROGRAM ICE APP SAID
ALAMEDA COUNTY IMMIGRATION LEGAL AND EDUCATION
PARTNERSHIP, A RELATIVE WHO WAS WAITING OUTSIDE FOR GUTIERREZ
AND HER SONS WAS UNABLE TO HAND OFF THE ASSISTIVE DEVICES
NECESSARY FOR THE SIX YEAR OLD WHO IS DEAF AND HAD A COCHLEAR
IMPLANT NO CHILD SHOULD BE RIPPED FROM THEIR HOME
COMMUNITY AND HIDDEN IN A DETENTION CENTER ESPECIALLY NOT
A DEAF CHILD WHO IS BEING DEPRIVED OF THEIR ABILITY TO
COMMUNICATE AND UNDERSTAND WHAT IS HAPPENING TO HIM.
>> I MAY HAVE MISSED SOMETHING BUT WHAT DID OUR MAYOR SAY
ABOUT THIS? WHAT DID MY SUPERVISOR SAY
ABOUT THIS SINCE THIS HAPPENED IN OUR DISTRICT I DO FEEL THIS
IS SERIOUS. I FEEL THAT SAN FRANCISCO
AND THE PEOPLE IN POWER HERE SHOULD BE TRYING TO HELP RIGHT
THIS WRONG THAT WAS ALLOWED TO BE DONE IN OUR CITY TO THIS
FAMILY AND I JUST GOT TO SAY THAT I.
>> I DON'T UNDERSTAND I DON'T I DON'T UNDERSTAND WHY THE
SILENCE SO SO MUCH SILENCE AROUND THIS.
THERE'S NOT SILENCE AROUND PARTIES AND PARADES BUT THERE'S
SILENCE ABOUT THESE ABDUCTIONS. WE KNOW WHAT HAPPENS AT THESE
DETENTION CENTERS, CONCENTRATION CAMPS.
PEOPLE ARE DEPRIVED OF FOOD THEIR THEIR WATER'S DIRTY.
THEY DON'T GET MEDICAL ATTENTION.
THEY'RE BEING FORCED TO LABOR FOR LIKE HARDLY ANYTHING
AND THEY'RE DYING AND BEING KILLED.
SO LIKE WE SHOULD CARE RIGHT? THANK YOU, LEAH MACGYVER FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON. >> I HAVE THREE RECOMMENDATIONS
ONE 24 FOR MISSION AND 16 FOR MISSION THAT THEY BE TURNED
OVER TO A VENDOR, A HISPANIC VENDORS ASSOCIATION BECAUSE
WHAT YOU HAVE DOWN THERE NOW IS JUST A CANCER AND I'M TIRED OF
GETTING CONTACTED BY DOPE PEOPLE ADDICTED ON DOPE SELLING
ARTICLES OUT OF THE WALGREENS ACROSS THE STREET TO 2416 FOR
MISSION TURN IT OVER TO THE TO THE VENDORS ASSOCIATION.
NUMBER TWO I WOULD LIKE TO TURN BART WHICH IS 50 STATIONS INTO
THE WORLD OR UNITED STATES LARGEST STUDENT MUSEUM.
I WOULD LIKE ARTWORKS CULTURAL ARTWORKS FROM EVERY SCHOOL
SYSTEM IN THE BAY AREA THAT IMPINGES ON BART TO BE
DISPLAYED IN OUR ART. IT AS ARTWORKS, SCULPTURES,
ART, POETRY, WHATEVER IN OUR STATIONS I WOULD LIKE
COOPERATION. I WOULD LIKE SOME KIND OF PILOT
PROGRAM THAT WOULD FOCUS ON THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO FIRST TO
SEE HOW IT WOULD WORK AND THEN I WOULD LIKE IT TO GO TO ALL 50
STATIONS WHICH IS FIVE COUNTIES.
THE THIRD THING IS THE BODIES THAT YOU'RE DUMPING OFF OF THE
GOLDEN GATE UNCLAIMED BODIES. I WOULD LIKE YOU TO STOP THAT
PRACTICE AND HONOR HUMAN LIFE AND DESIGNATE A BUILDING FOR
THE DEAD OR A BUILDING DEDICATE A BUILDING FOR THE UNKNOWN DEAD
AT LEAST NEW YORK CITY HAS AN ISLAND WITH 1 MILLION PEOPLE
UNCLAIMED BODIES. THE LEAST YOU COULD DO IS
DEDICATE A BUILDING, PUT THEIR ASHES IN A BUILDING, DEDICATE
THAT TO HUMAN LIFE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC
WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT? >> EXCUSE ME, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. >> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW
CLOSED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR FOR
ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA AGENDA PLEASE
CALL ITEMS 21 THROUGH 24 ITEMS 21 THROUGH 24 WE'RE INTRODUCE
VOTE FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS
VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
READING TODAY ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE SUPERVISOR ON YOU LIKE TO USE A
SEPARATE 24 FOR SEPARATE VOTE CAP 24 IS GETTING SEVERED.
I DON'T SEE ANYBODY ELSE IN THE QUEUE SO MADAM CLERK COULD YOU
CALL THE ROLL ON THE REMAINING BALANCE OF THE ITEMS ON ITEMS
2122 AND 23 SOUP PROVIDES FOR MAHMUD MAHMOOD I MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE SEVEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED AND THEN MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 24 ITEM 24
THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO EXPRESS THE INTENT OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO TO ESTABLISH THE SUNSET IRISH
CULTURAL DISTRICT TREE TO RECOGNIZE AND PRESERVE THE
HISTORY, LEGACY AND LIVING CULTURAL TRADITIONS OF THE
IRISH AND THE IRISH-AMERICAN COMMUNITY IN SAN FRANCISCO'S
SUNSET DISTRICT SUPERVISOR WONG THANK YOU TODAY I'M PROUD TO
HAVE US CONSIDER THIS RESOLUTION AND TO EXPRESS
SUPPORT FOR A IRISH CULTURAL DISTRICT IN THE SUNSET WE'VE
RECEIVED OVER 600 LETTERS IN ONE DAY FROM MY COMMITTEE
MEMBERS URGING US TO SUPPORT THIS.
WHEN PEOPLE THINK ABOUT THE HISTORY OF SAN FRANCISCO THEY
OFTEN THINK ABOUT THE GOLD RUSH, THE EARTHQUAKE.
THEY DON'T ALWAYS THINK ABOUT THE IRISH BUT THEY SHOULD.
IRISH IMMIGRANTS WERE HERE FROM THE VERY BEGINNING ARRIVING
IN THE 1840 AND 1950S, MANY OF THEM FLEEING STARVATION
AND BUILDING A LIFE IN A CITY THAT WASN'T ALWAYS WELCOMING.
BY 1871 AND EIGHT SAN FRANCISCANS WAS IRISH.
THEY DUG THE ROADS, ORGANIZED UNIONS STAFFED THE FIREHOUSES
AND POLICE STATIONS. THEY DIDN'T JUST LIVE HERE.
THEY BUILT HERE. WHAT I WANT MY COLLEAGUES TO
UNDERSTAND IS THAT THIS RESOLUTION IS ISN'T JUST AN ACT
OF NOSTALGIA. THE TRADITIONS THAT WE WERE
TALKING ABOUT THE MUSIC, THE DANCE, THE LANGUAGE, THE
SPORTING CLUBS ARE NOT PRESERVED BEHIND GLASS.
THEY'RE ALIVE. THEY'RE BEING PASSED DOWN RIGHT
NOW IN THE SUNSET DISTRICT TWO NEXT GENERATION A CULTURAL
DISTRICT DESIGNATION WOULD GIVE THAT LIVING COMMUNITY THE SAME
INSTITUTIONAL SUPPORT AND RECOGNITION THAT OTHER
CULTURAL COMMUNITIES IN THIS CITY ALREADY HAVE ACCESS TO
THAT THAT IS WHAT WE'RE ASKING FOR AND I THINK IT'S LONG
OVERDUE. I WANT TO THANK THE IRISH
UNITED IRISH CULTURAL CENTER, THE ST PATRICK'S DAY PARADE,
THE UNITED IRISH SOCIETIES OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR THEIR
PARTNERSHIP IN BRINGING THIS FORWARD.
AND I WANT TO THANK THE RESIDENTS OF A SUNSET DISTRICT
IRISH AND NON IRISH ALIKE WHO HAVE SUPPORTED THIS EFFORT.
THIS IS THE BEGINNING OF THE PROCESS AND I LOOK FORWARD TO
DOING WHAT DOING THAT WORK ALONGSIDE THIS COMMUNITY.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG WITH
THAT I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED AND MADAM
CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS TO REPORT?
MR. PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED.
IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS.
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THE LATE MS..
BASIL WONG ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR THE LATE
MR. JOO JI YI AND I BELIEVE THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF
OUR AGENDA, MADAM CLERK. DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS
BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. WELL THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED
. >> NASA.GOV TV.
>> SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION